<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reason and authority, or, The motives of a late Protestants reconciliation to the Catholic Church together with remarks upon some late discourses against transubstantiation.</title>
            <author>Basset, Joshua, 1641?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1042</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12541228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12541228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26741)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 304:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reason and authority, or, The motives of a late Protestants reconciliation to the Catholic Church together with remarks upon some late discourses against transubstantiation.</title>
                  <author>Basset, Joshua, 1641?-1720.</author>
                  <author>Gother, John, d. 1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 130 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Joshua Basset. Ascribed in error to John Gother. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Publisht with allowance"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Transubstantiation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62979:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62979:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASON AND AUTHORITY: OR THE MOTIVES OF A LATE Proteſtants Reconciliation TO THE Catholic Church.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With Remarks upon ſome late Diſcourſes AGAINST <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſht with Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, For his Houſhold and Chappel, 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62979:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62979:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Reaſon and Authority, OR THE MOTIVES OF A LATE Proteſtants Reconciliation TO THE <hi>Catholic Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THAT I may pay my <hi>due Reſpects</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to which I am indebted for a conſiderable part of my Education; I think it juſt to publiſh thoſe Motives which obliged me to <hi>take my leave</hi> of Her: And if it ſhall appear, that I have not raſhly quitted her Communion, but have uſed herein the utmoſt ſtrength, and dictates of my moſt Impartial Reaſon; I hope She will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me, if I have followed that <hi>light,</hi> which She her ſelf ſo <hi>preſſingly</hi> recommends.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore <hi>(moſt Reverend Fathers)</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate my Motives to you, in a ſhort, but plain Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod; and if my Brevity in this, ſhall not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſs the ſtrength of my Arguments; cenſure
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62979:3"/>not from thence the Faith which I profeſs: For having peruſed many Excellent Authors, which have treated more particularly, and fully of it; I purpoſely avoided a long Repetition of thoſe things, which you may find more largely, and better hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Originals themſelves. I have been guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (I hope) by the <hi>grace</hi> of God, and <hi>reaſon,</hi> redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing things almoſt to Demonſtration; I have no Charm, nor Conjuration upon me, that I know of, but ſhall be always ready to follow the ſtrongeſt Evidence, of <hi>common</hi> Reaſon. I will not trouble you with all thoſe circumſtances which made me <hi>doubt;</hi> but only tell you, in ſhort, that by reading, and diſcourſing with Catholic <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>Authors,</hi> I did really <hi>doubt</hi> concerning the truth of my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant profeſſion.</p>
            <p>One main Reaſon of my Diffidence was, <hi>this,</hi> That I did not find in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a <hi>lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> ſufficient to oblige my <hi>reaſon,</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> to ſubmit to her Decrees, in matters of <hi>Faith, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 133.</note> For Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> tells me,
<q>All men ought to be left to Judge according to the Pandects of the Divine Laws, becauſe each Member of this Society, is bound to take care of his Soul, and of all things that tend thereto.</q> And Dr.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 48, 49.</note> 
               <hi>Ferne,</hi> in his Caſe between the two Churches, ſays further,
<q>That in matters propoſed by my Superiours, as Gods Word, and of Faith, I am not tied to believe it ſuch, till they manifeſt it to me to be ſo; and not that I am obliged to believe it ſuch, unleſs I can manifeſt it to be contrary; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Faith can reſt on <hi>no humane Authority,</hi> but only on Gods Word, and Divine Revelation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is your conſtant Doctrine, as to our <hi>faith,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62979:3"/>or <hi>internal aſſent,</hi> as may be proved by many of your beſt Authors; and indeed, the Juſtice of your Reformation cannot conſiſt with ſtricter Principles; for how can you bind our Conſciences, by a late u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpt Authority, (I ſpeak as to declaring Articles of <hi>faith,</hi> not of <hi>diſcipline</hi>) when you would not ſubmit your <hi>own</hi> to the greateſt Authority, under which our Anceſtors were born; and which was incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably, the moſt lawful, the moſt eſteem'd, the moſt certain, and moſt univerſal, that ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in the Chriſtian Church ſince the Apoſtles? And accordingly Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> (of the juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Councils, and Synods) ſays,
<q>Any thing beſides Scripture, and the plain, irrefragable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitable conſequences of It, well may Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants hold it, as matter of Opinion, but as matter of Faith, and Religion, neither can they, with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to their own ground believe it themſelves, nor require the Belief of it, of others, without high, and moſt Schiſmatical preſumption.</q> Now theſe plain, irrefragable and indubitable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, muſt need be plain to every man, who is not mad, or a fool; and ſo need no Authority: But in all thoſe which are leſs plain (and ſuch <hi>muſt</hi> be the Points controverted between Catholics, and your ſelves) I have my liberty: for I am fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured (from the ſame hand)
<q>that God doth not, and that therefore Man ought not to require any more of any Man, than this, to believe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to be Gods Word, to endeavour to find the true ſenſe of it, and to live according to it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore (worthy <hi>Fathers</hi>) been taught <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> in your Grammar Schools, and keeping the <hi>Holy Bible</hi> with me, which contains
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62979:4"/>all things neceſſary to Salvation, and to which (according to your Inſtructions) I muſt at laſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal; I reſolved to give you no further trouble in this matter; eſpecially, ſince (as I ſaid) you could not teach me infallibly; nor impoſe your Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, by vertue of any <hi>legal Authority,</hi> which might ultimately conclude my <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſecure my <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finding, that I was not only at liberty, but advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alſo by your ſelves, to <hi>work out my own Salvation,</hi> and to <hi>ſtand upon my own bottome,</hi> I thought it reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that my Enquiry ſhould <hi>Set out</hi> from the very beginning, and examine whether there was a <hi>God;</hi> and indeed I found ſome learned men, even among the greateſt Philoſophers, ſpeaking very doubtfully concerning this matter, if not denying it. 'Twas not only the Fool had ſaid in his heart, <hi>there is no God;</hi> but hear what <hi>Cardan</hi> Writes of our famous <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>de Sap.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtoteles</hi> (ſays he) <hi>tam callidè mundi or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; animae praemia, &amp; Deos, &amp; Daemones ſuſtulit, ut hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> omnia apertè quidem diceret, argui tamen non poſſet.</hi> And the great <hi>Pontif Cotta</hi> to <hi>Velleius,</hi> upon the ſame Queſtion concerning a God, <hi>Credo (inquit) ſi in concione quaeratur:</hi> But in private it ſeems, he was very eaſie in his Belief. I will not mention <hi>Epicure,</hi> and <hi>Lucretius,</hi> their names are grown ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally too ſcandalous; but if you examine <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, Anacharſis, Protagoras, Euripides, Diagoras</hi> and many others, whoſe reputations carry no ſmall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority along with them, you will obſerve ſuch a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſion of mind concerning a Deity, that if they were afraid, <hi>poſitively</hi> to <hi>deny;</hi> ſo neither would they <hi>confidently affirm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next (ſuppoſing a Deity) whether the <hi>World was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62979:4"/>govern'd by God?</hi> The <hi>Epicureans</hi> totally deny it; <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam omninò habere humanarum rerum procurationem Deos:</hi> which <hi>Ennius</hi> alſo plainly profeſſeth in theſe words,
<q>
                  <l>Ego Deûm genus ſemper eſſe dixi; &amp; dicam Coelitum,</l>
                  <l>Sed Eos non curare Opinor, quid agat humanum genus.</l>
               </q> Which opinion <hi>Grotius</hi> takes care to confute in his <hi>Cap. de poenis. l.</hi> 2. And no wonder if the Heathens denied a Point, full of ſo many difficulties, ſince the Royal Prophet himſelf was almoſt ſtumbled at it. <hi>My feet</hi> (ſays he) <hi>were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well nigh ſlipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the <hi>Souls Immortality</hi> (a very conſiderable Point) ſeem'd ſo hard to Reaſon; eſpecially when I found it diſputed in ſome Set philoſophical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes, and it's Mortality proved, almoſt to a phyſical Demonſtration; and beſides, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine concerning it, had not been deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd above <hi>two hundred years</hi> in any Council; that truly, <hi>Fathers,</hi> my reaſon (notwithſtanding the beſt aſſiſtance I could procure) was put to a great plunge; I will not tell you how I got off from theſe, and many other ſuch like difficulties; but proceed, and acquaint you how I ventur'd upon the <hi>Bible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I examined the firſt <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> I obſerved that many great Men were ſcandaliz'd at <hi>Moſe</hi>'s Philoſophy; and yet upon the Truth of his Hiſtory, concerning the <hi>Creation,</hi> and <hi>fall</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> depends the greateſt Myſtery of our Salvation. I proceeded further, and found ſome ſtrange Miſtakes, and (for ought I could ſee) irreconcileable Errours in that Hiſtory; inſomuch, that many Learned men (well read in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language and Hiſtory of the <hi>Jews</hi>), poſitively affirm, by very ſtrong Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, That the <hi>Penteteuch,</hi> or <hi>five Books</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62979:5"/>(ſuch as they appear to us) were ſo far from being writ by <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, that they were writ (ſay they) by <hi>Eſdras</hi> the Scribe, many hundred of years after the death of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed (Reverend <hi>Fathers</hi>) when I heard this, I began heartily to wiſh that God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in his Providence, and Goodneſs to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, (infinitely fallen from that knowledge, in which our firſt Parent was happily created) would have pleaſed (as ſome reparation for ſo great a loſs) to have left us ſome unerring Authority, and Sovereign Guide, who might have conducted all that truly ſought the way, to that bleſt Paradice, from whence long ſince we had been baniſhed.</p>
            <p>With great pains, I broke through many rubs (how ſucceſsfully I cannot ſay) and came to the <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> Here I hoped that my Reaſon would find an eaſier paſſage through thoſe Divine Authors, as being of a <hi>later date,</hi> and the <hi>laſt Teſtament</hi> of our bleſſed Saviour. I began with the firſt <hi>Chapter</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and found the Genealogie of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> deduc't through <hi>Joſeph</hi> his <hi>reputed</hi> Father, from <hi>David,</hi> out of whoſe Royal Root, the long expected <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was to Spring. Would not a Man reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly believe, that the holy Evangeliſt, to prove <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who was to be the <hi>Son of David,</hi> made him rather appear the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> than the <hi>Son of God?</hi> But if he was not the <hi>Son of Joſeph,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it appear from thence that he was the <hi>Son of David.</hi> Nay, more, when I would have proceeded further, I found, that of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> the 2 Epiſtle of <hi>Peter;</hi> 2 and 3 of <hi>John;</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> the Epiſtles of <hi>James, Jude,</hi> and the <hi>Revelations</hi> maintain'd to be Apocryphal by <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62979:5"/>Luthers</hi> great Scholar; and many important Texts, left out, or ſomething added, or different Tranſlations by your firſt great Proteſtant Reformers. And that ſome of theſe were not received, even by the Orthodox, into their Canon, till nere Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after the death of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>However, I paſt this by; and, to be ſhort, I read over the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> (ſuch as we have fit) with great attention. But truly, <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers,</hi> either your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and the Reaſon of every particular Chriſtian, is infinitely above my poor Judgment; or elſe you muſt not tell me, that every Chriſtian, upon a ſincere peruſal of this holy Book, would <hi>certainly</hi> have compos'd the Creed of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> ſuch as you receive, and profeſs in your Common-Prayer Books.</p>
            <p>But, before I examined every particular Point of Faith contained in that ſacred Writ; I reſolved to conſider what Religion was in <hi>general,</hi> and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, <hi>the Chriſtian;</hi> In that, what <hi>Faith</hi> was, and how eſteem'd, when compar'd with <hi>Obedience</hi> and good <hi>Works</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and oppos'd to <hi>Works</hi> under the <hi>Law:</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> what were the great, and neceſſary Articles. Then I preſum'd to look into the great myſtery of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> and bleſſed deſign of our Saviour, in ſubmitting to the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of humane life, and ſhameful death of the Croſs; and I extended the great benefits of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as univerſally, as I judged He himſelf intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. Next, I ventur'd to examine with my Reaſon the great Doctrines of the <hi>Trinity, Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiality, Tranſubſtantiation, Predeſtination</hi> and <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will,</hi> and many other main Points of Divinity: and, as a help to my Reaſon, I diligently peruſed your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62979:6"/>learned Comments upon particular Texts, and <hi>Chapters;</hi> as alſo the Comments of <hi>Catholics, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, Socinians, Calviniſts, Zuinglians;</hi> and I did not totally neglect the Cenſure of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> concerning the whole Hiſtory in General.</p>
            <p>When I had done all this, I began to make up my <hi>account,</hi> and drew a <hi>Scheme</hi> of Divinity, in which (abſtracting from all Authority) I receiv'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected what ſeem'd moſt agreeable to my Reaſon: But I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs, that this was not done without ſome kind of force upon my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in general; for methoughts, the Authority of <hi>General Councils, Ancient Fathers,</hi> and the moſt <hi>univerſal concurrence</hi> of learned Men, ought to ſway a private Reaſon, altho it were not <hi>ſcientificè,</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitively</hi> convinc'd of every particular Point which they had determin'd. However, being taught by your ſelves to ſuſpect General Councils; to Judge the Works of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> whether they were <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine,</hi> or <hi>ſuppoſititious;</hi> and of the <hi>trueſt,</hi> to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret them according to our own <hi>private Opinions,</hi> or condemn them, as <hi>erroneous,</hi> when they differ'd from our Sentiments; I ſtuck cloſe to my Reaſon, finiſht my Scheme, and my Reaſon ſubſcrib'd to it.</p>
            <p>When this was done, I compar'd it with your <hi>Thirty nine Articles;</hi> with the <hi>Catechiſms</hi> of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics, Lutherans, Calviniſts, Socinians,</hi> and obſerv'd, that in the <hi>whole,</hi> I diſagreed from them <hi>All,</hi> even in Doctrines (commonly reputed) abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation. But yet, this my confuſed <hi>Babel</hi> of Religion, was built up with ſome particular Points, taken from all the Heretics, and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, even from <hi>Ebion,</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> to <hi>Naylor</hi> and <hi>Muggleton.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62979:6"/>
            <p>Now I thought my ſelf ſufficiently ſtockt to ſet up for a Hereſiarch, and a <hi>New Light</hi> in the Church; but when I ſeriouſly confider'd, how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly our poor Nation was already torn and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with ſuch Sects, and Schiſms, to the great diſturbance of our temporal Peace, and Happineſs, and ſcandal to Chriſtianity; I reſolv'd to keep my Reaſons to my ſelf, and cenſur'd in my heart that great Liberty, and <hi>Supream Authority</hi> in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which you your ſelves, and (as you ſay) God Almighty had been pleas'd to allow us. You may blame my Reaſon for all this, and extol your own, who (it may be) have interpreted Scripture otherwiſe; but I had learned Men to back me, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly as learned (tho not ſo <hi>lucky</hi>) as your ſelves, and we thought we had as ſtrong Reaſons to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you, as you to accuſe us.</p>
            <p>I return'd then to a <hi>Second,</hi> and a <hi>Third</hi> more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent peruſal of my Scheme; and tho I ſtill found every particular Point correſponding with my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet altogether, I ſoon perceiv'd (by what I had read) that the whole Chriſtian World of all Sorts and Sects univerſally condemn'd it.</p>
            <p>I profeſs, <hi>Fathers,</hi> I was ſtrangely ſtumbled at this conſideration, and my Reaſon began ſtrongly to inſinuate, that <hi>poſſibly,</hi> and very <hi>probably</hi> I might be all this while in the wrong; for I had learnt, that <hi>Ariſtotle, Ariſtides,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin, Grotius</hi> and many excellent Scholars, counted it more Madneſs <hi>(inſolentiſſimae Inſaniae eſt)</hi> to contradict the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>All,</hi> or the <hi>Moſt,</hi> or the <hi>moſt Wiſe;</hi> and of the moſt wiſe, <hi>All,</hi> or <hi>Moſt,</hi> or the <hi>moſt Excellent;</hi> for (ſays one of them) as in matter of Fact, we ought to believe the moſt, and moſt proper, and credible
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62979:7"/>Witneſſes; ſo in matters of Opinion, we are oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſubmit to the <hi>moſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>Excellent Authors;</hi> Now ſure, theſe <hi>praeſtantiſſimi Auctores,</hi> are thoſe who write with <hi>beſt Authority,</hi> and have Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Higheſt Powers, ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Yet, notwithſtanding all this, I followed my own private Reaſon, in my particular Points; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til a ſtronger Reaſon, I mean, the <hi>joint</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon of Mankind,</hi> and my <hi>Conſcience</hi> too, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dictating that my Judgment in particular Caſes, might fail; that all, had not equal ſtrength; that God therefore had not left the World without Government; nor given us Laws without lawful Judges and Interpreters; that theſe Judges ought to be obeyed: Theſe, I ſay, and ſuch like conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, interrupted the quiet of my life, until at laſt my <hi>united</hi> Reaſon made its laſt effort, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and totally convinc'd me, that if any ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority was to be found upon Earth, I ought in reaſon, to ſubmit my particular Reaſons to it.</p>
            <p>Truly, <hi>Fathers,</hi> when upon deliberate counſel, I had determin'd to take this moſt reaſonable courſe; Give me leave to tell you, that I began to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how your ſelves (tho moſt learned, moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and moſt pious Men) could be ſatisfied un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of your private Reaſons, if there may be found any legal Supream Judge which might <hi>ultimately,</hi> and <hi>Authoritatively</hi> guide, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you. Pardon me, I do not preſume to meaſure my Reaſon againſt the meaneſt among yours, for I queſtion not but <hi>yours</hi> would err much leſs, than <hi>mine;</hi> but yet leſt your own ſhould err <hi>at all,</hi> methinks, it were ſafeſt, and by conſequence, moſt reaſonable, to ſeek ſome Authority (if any ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62979:7"/>there be) under which you might be ſecur'd from <hi>all</hi> Errour; at leaſt, as far as humane nature is capable of it: For my part, my Reaſon, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience forc't me to take that method, and I reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either to find that Authority, and ſubmit to it, or keep to my own Principles, how erroneous ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they might be eſteem'd by others.</p>
            <p>My firſt enquiry after this Authority, was, in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for tho you had often told me, that it was <hi>not</hi> there; yet I was more inclin'd to ſuſpect your Modeſty, than condemn your want of Prudence, in pretending to ſubſiſt ſecurely without it. But when I had again examined the holy Scriptures together with the beſt Records and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories concerning your <hi>legal Title</hi> to this Supream Juriſdiction; I found indeed you had <hi>reaſon,</hi> and were very ingenuous in diſowning, what did not of <hi>right</hi> belong unto you,: For if the Church of <hi>England</hi> enjoys this Power, by the ſame Rule, and for the ſame Reaſons, <hi>Holland, Denmark, Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> would have the ſame Title to it, as your ſelves; nay perhaps, <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans:</hi> But my Reaſon told me (from the ſad effects which we daily ſee) that this muſt needs be moſt contrary to the Unity of the <hi>One, Holy, Catholic</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolic Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I then recollected, how you had often told me, <hi>that the Catholic Church could never Err,</hi> but that it would always hold the <hi>purity</hi> of <hi>Faith uncorrupt.</hi> I remember then to have askt of your Reverences, where this Catholic Church was to be found; and you told me, <hi>That it was diſpers'd all over the Chriſtian World.</hi> I was troubled that your anſwer was <hi>ſo wide,</hi> however, I reſolved to ſearch; and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62979:8"/>firſt I enquired in the <hi>Roman Church:</hi> Indeed they aſſured me, that I ſhould there find what I lookt for: 'Tis true, I found them all of <hi>one mind,</hi> in <hi>neceſſaries;</hi> but when I examin'd their Doctrines, I perceived (as you had often declar'd) that, if, <hi>yours were true;</hi> their's was <hi>much corrupt;</hi> or, if they diſſembled, they muſt needs be under as great a condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Among them, therefore, there could be no part of the Catholic Church. Then I went into the <hi>Greek Church,</hi> but found there alſo, the ſame obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and difficulties.</p>
            <p>In a word, I went through the <hi>Aſian,</hi> and <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Churches, the <hi>Denmark, Swedeland, Lutheran,</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> Churches; yet found nothing but <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> or, the <hi>true Faith</hi> (according to your Standard) <hi>notoriouſly corrupt.</hi> I name not <hi>Holland,</hi> becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, I ſaw ſuch a Medley of Faiths, that it look't to me, as <hi>Babel</hi> might have done, when God confounded their Language; but certainly if the Catholic Doctrine had been practis'd in thoſe parts where I had been; <hi>Holland</hi> ſurely of any Nation, would beſt have repreſented the Univerſal Church: But believe me, <hi>Fathers,</hi> it muſt then have quitted its Titles of Unity, and Holineſs; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> can conſiſt with <hi>Diviſion;</hi> or <hi>Holineſs</hi> with the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt, I return'd to your ſelves, and acquainted you how unſucceſsful my Journey had been; you ſtill replied that there was undoubtedly a <hi>Catholic Church Militant upon Earth;</hi> and that this Church did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hold the <hi>true Faith of Chriſt, uncorrupt;</hi> but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that it was not neceſſary it ſhould be <hi>viſible;</hi> quoting at the ſame time the complaint of <hi>Elijah, that he, only he was left;</hi> to whom God anſwered,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62979:8"/>
               <hi>that he had ſeven Thouſand left in Iſrael</hi> (unknown to <hi>Elijah) who had not bent the knee to Baal:</hi> And that this was a Type of the Chriſtian Church. Truly, <hi>Fathers</hi> (may it not diſpleaſe you) I began to think, that you had trifled with me all this while, and pleas'd your ſelves to ſend me of an <hi>April Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand;</hi> for to look for a thing which is inviſible, is a kind of a fooliſh Meſſage. Perceiving that you had not us'd me kindly, I reſolved to ſet out once more upon my own ſtrength, eſpecially, ſince I believ'd <hi>with you,</hi> that there was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Catholic Church; and <hi>more than you</hi> that this Church was certainly, and eaſily viſible. This my Belief was alſo the more confirm'd, when I had well conſider'd the Story of <hi>Elijah;</hi> for I found, that this defection, and falling away, from the worſhip of the true God, was in <hi>Iſrael</hi> only, a rebellious Kingdom, ſeparated from the choſen Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> (God knows, how like our Caſe in <hi>England);</hi> but in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> God had a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Temple, a public High Prieſt, and public true Worſhippers, and ſo they continued (except ſome little time they were puniſht with Captivity) until the coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I made my firſt ſtep (as I had done before) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and indeed, I there found, all the marks, and ſigns of a true Catholic Church. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. Univerſality and Viſibility. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>that the Mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the Hills.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>And the people ſhall flow unto her.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>And if he ſhall neglect to hear them, tell it to the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62979:9"/>2. Uninterrupted continuance, and Succeſſion. <hi>This is my Covenant with them, ſaith the Lord, my ſpirit that is upon thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21.</note> 
               <hi>and my word which I have put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy Seed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, from henceforth, and for ever. And he gave ſome Apoſtles; and ſome Prophets; and ſome Evangeliſts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>And ſome Paſtors and</hi> Teachers; <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, for the edifying the body of Chriſt: Till we all come in the</hi> unity <hi>of faith, unto a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Unity and Uniformity. <hi>Now I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that ye all ſpeak the</hi> ſame thing, <hi>and that there be be no</hi> diviſions <hi>among you; but that ye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly joyned together in the</hi> ſame mind,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>and in the</hi> ſame Judgment. <hi>That ye ſtand faſt in</hi> one ſpirit, <hi>with</hi> one mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>ſtriving together for the faith of the goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Holy Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs; General Councils,</hi> and <hi>Synods;</hi> a <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and a <hi>Holy Sacrifice; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Miracles</hi> and <hi>Divine Sacraments; Holy Orders,</hi> and <hi>Religious Colledges, Abſtinence,</hi> and <hi>Pennance, Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience, Charity</hi> and <hi>Good Works:</hi> And in a word, fundamental Doctrines, <hi>Authoritatively</hi> impos'd, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> receiv'd throughout the whole Chriſtian World. Be not offended, <hi>Fathers,</hi> that I ſpeak ſo largely of their Doctrine, for (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well examin'd) I ſay again, that nere eight parts in ten among Chriſtians, agree in thoſe very Articles, or moſt of them which are controverted between your ſelves, and them: And theſe believ'd from the <hi>beginning</hi> of their Converſions, whether in <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having met with theſe great inducements to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62979:9"/>me I had found the true Catholic Church; and believing that a <hi>viſible Body</hi> could not ſubſiſt without a <hi>viſible Head;</hi> I made it my next buſineſs to enquire after this <hi>Supream Vicegerent,</hi> or <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative</hi> of the whole: And indeed methought there was no great difficulty in it. I began at the Head, (I mean) Chriſt Jeſus; and found, 1. That he was a <hi>High Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſedec:</hi> That he inſtituted a new Law; and gave Commiſſions to his Apoſtles to promulgate, and interpret it; and promiſed the aſſiſtance of his <hi>holy Spirit, to the end of all Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, that of theſe, he appointed one to be Chief (I mean) St. <hi>Peter:</hi> ſo reputed, and unanimouſly eſteemed by the <hi>Fathers</hi> in the Eldeſt times of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſo underſtood, by <hi>many</hi> among your ſelves; and not to be diſputed without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt injury, and violence to their plain Writings; and ſo received by the whole Catholic Church. His Succeſſion, for many years, deliver'd to us by St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and brought down even to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age, and Pope. Theſe, worthy <hi>Fathers,</hi> are pregnant Arguments of a lawful Authority. I wiſht you could have ſhewn me ſuch another in your own Church.</p>
            <p>I next lookt into this Eccleſiaſtical Government (as far as it concern'd me) and found, that all Points of Faith were determin'd in General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, which repreſent the <hi>Catholic Church aſſembled,</hi> and in which our Saviour promis'd his holy Spirit ſhould ever aſſiſt. That they were always as Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral as the Circumſtances of <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> would permit; or the weight of the Matters to be debated, required; and <hi>free</hi> and <hi>indiſputable,</hi> when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62979:10"/>ſecur'd from <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>force;</hi> that their Decrees were then made with deliberation, and according to the received Doctrines of the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors, preſerv'd in the Writings of <hi>Fathers;</hi> or conſtant Apoſtolical Tradition, kept inviolable in the Church: And when <hi>thus</hi> made, that they were <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory</hi> to <hi>bind</hi> our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>conclude</hi> our <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I examined further, whether this <hi>Vicegerent,</hi> and Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter</hi> was received, as <hi>ſuch,</hi> in theſe General Councils, or Catholic Church; and found his Authority <hi>own'd,</hi> and <hi>confirm'd</hi> by them, and that he was many hundred of years in the peaceable poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it; no man upon Earth pretending a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority; or, if any did, that he was thereupon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, as an <hi>Intruder,</hi> or <hi>Uſurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, I concluded (as the nature, and neceſſary Laws of Government requir'd) that the Pope <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> or <hi>General Council,</hi> or <hi>Both united,</hi> could not poſſibly grant this Supream Authority, to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mortal <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> to hold <hi>independently</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> or <hi>them;</hi> becauſe this muſt conſtitute another Supream independent <hi>Head</hi> of the ſame <hi>Body,</hi> which is monſtrous; or a <hi>Head</hi> without a <hi>Body,</hi> which is ridiculous; or elſe there would be two diſtinct <hi>Heads,</hi> and two <hi>Bodies,</hi> which is directly contrary to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and <hi>Eſſence</hi> of Chriſts Church, as fruſtrating, or obſtructing the main End, and deſign of Chriſt, (that is) of preventing Hereſies, or condemning them when they ariſe; for <hi>par in parem, non habet Imperium:</hi> Two equal Sovereign Authorities have no Juriſdiction one over the other: Beſides, this Vicegerent, is but a <hi>Truſtee,</hi> or <hi>Fidei commiſſarius:</hi> and can have no greater Power, than what is given him
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62979:10"/>by his <hi>Principal,</hi> or <hi>Fidei Commiſſor;</hi> now this is a <hi>perſonal</hi> Truſt, and cannot be alienated, or divided; becauſe he holds not this Power in his <hi>own right,</hi> as a <hi>Property,</hi> or in <hi>pleno Jure Proprietatis;</hi> he hath only the adminiſtration of it, <hi>in truſt</hi> for another: So neither can he alienate the <hi>Patrimonium Eccleſiae;</hi> or St. <hi>Peters</hi> Patrimony; all Contracts therefore, in theſe Caſes, would be <hi>fraudulent: Tanquam facti de re alienâ,</hi> and the <hi>Grantees,</hi> become <hi>malae fidei poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores,</hi> or unjuſt Poſſeſſors, of what they could not lawfully purchaſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, all Sovereign Power, in the ſame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is <hi>Indiviſible,</hi> and can only be delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, in the <hi>Executive</hi> part, for the adminiſtration of Juſtice, but accountable ſtill to the <hi>Head,</hi> from whence it derives.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Equal priviledges</hi> therefore, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, granted to the Patriarck of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> prove nothing againſt this <hi>Supremacy</hi> of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor: For Firſt, They were only <hi>honorary,</hi> in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was become the Seat of the Empire. Secondly, <hi>Patriarchal,</hi> or <hi>quatenus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarcha,</hi> but not <hi>quatenus Caput Eccleſiae,</hi> or as Head of the Univerſal Church: And laſtly, it is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly expreſt in the ſame Canon, that theſe <hi>Honours,</hi> or <hi>Priviledges</hi> ſhould be held, and enjoy'd, <hi>poſt Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificem Romanum,</hi> after the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and it appears <hi>de facto,</hi> that (during the Third General Council held at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and allow'd by Proteſtants) Pope <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> the Firſt, did, by his ſubſtitute <hi>Cyril, authoritatively,</hi> depoſe, and Excommunicate <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> then Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Pope <hi>Victor</hi> who lived <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 198. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia,</hi> for their keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62979:11"/>of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> contrary to the Inſtitutions of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> tho <hi>tolerated</hi> therein by St. <hi>John.</hi> Nor could Ambition, or Avarice in thoſe days of Perſecution, move the Supream Heads of the Church to exerciſe ſuch Juriſdiction; for they got little by being Eminent and Conſpicuous, but Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, and ſo it hapned to this Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> who died a Martyr, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 203.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Fathers,</hi> beſides theſe great <hi>Marks</hi> of the true Catholic Church, I perceived alſo, that, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Command, and Inſtitution of our Saviour) his Vicegerent here, did ſend out his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Baptizing through all Nations;</hi> Inſomuch, that ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great (before whoſe time you tell us, that this Holy Church began to fall) there have been converted to the Chriſtian Faith (otherwiſe call'd the <hi>Roman Catholic Faith</hi>) neer <hi>Thirty</hi> great Kingdoms, or Provinces (among which, Our <hi>Saxon Anceſtors,</hi> help to make up the number) beſides infinite multitudes in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi> And, ſo much pains ſhould be taken, in obedience to our Saviours commands, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his aſſiſtance; ſo much blood of holy Martyrs ſpilt; and all this, to bring <hi>Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> from the worſhip of their falſe Gods, into another Idolatrous, and damnably corrupted Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, may poſſibly to your Reaſons, appear conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Mercy and Goodneſs of Almighty God; but pray excuſe me, if I tell you, that to my Reaſon, it ſeems altogether repugnant; but this is matter of Opinion.</p>
            <p>Having got thus far, toward that Sovereign Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Authority in Matters of Faith, abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation; and believing, according to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62979:11"/>the ſtrongeſt Evidences of Senſe, and Reaſon, that it muſt be in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> or, <hi>no where;</hi> which laſt Opinion muſt diſſolve that whole Fabrick, againſt which our Saviour promis'd <hi>the gates of Hell ſhould not prevail;</hi> I reſolved to make yet one ſtep fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and enquire, Whether this Ancient Catholic and Apoſtolic Church, could have ſo far forfeited her great Priviledges, and Prerogatives, by the practice of <hi>damnable Doctrines,</hi> and <hi>pernicious Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> (of which your ſelves, and others have moſt greivouſly accuſed her) as to render her, not only unworthy of the name, and Title to which She pretends; but alſo to make her Communion moſt <hi>unſafe,</hi> and <hi>deſperately dangerous</hi> to all honeſt, and pious Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, <hi>Fathers,</hi> when I conſider'd what ſome of your ſelves had often told me, and what I found in many of your Eminent Authors, concerning the <hi>late Innovation</hi> of thoſe Doctrines controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>two</hi> Churches; I began to have hard thoughts of the preſent Roman Catholic Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Much more, when enquiring, how late theſe Doctrines were introduced into the Church, you generally told me, that they were not impos'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Faithful, before the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> which hath not been ended much above an Hundred and twenty three years: But when I compar'd the <hi>date</hi> of your Reformation, with <hi>that,</hi> of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; I plainly perceiv'd, that the proteſting againſt theſe Errors was <hi>begun,</hi> and well nigh <hi>perfected,</hi> before theſe Errours were (as you ſay) then <hi>impos'd:</hi> which, (tho it ſeem'd ſomewhat ſtrange, and might have paſt with others for a reaſonable Anſwer to this Objection of Novelty) yet I reſolv'd to peruſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62979:12"/>the Councils themſelves, and <hi>(de point en point)</hi> note the time, when theſe Doctrines were in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Eſtabliſht.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I began with the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> which I found confirm'd in the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> Act. 16. (one of the firſt four General Councils own'd by Proteſtants) above <hi>Twelve Hundred</hi> years ſince, <hi>Six Hundred and thirty Fathers</hi> preſent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year of our Lord 451. and relation had to the <hi>firſt</hi> Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> Can. 6. This Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy alſo <hi>allow'd, profeſt,</hi> and <hi>taught</hi> by the moſt Ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> after the Apoſtles, and <hi>confeſt</hi> ſo to have been by <hi>Melancton, Luther, Bucer, Bilſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cooper, Bunny, Fulk, Middleton, Oſiander,</hi> the <hi>Centuriſts,</hi> and many others too long to mention.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Books which you call <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> were taken into the Canon of the Old Teſtament, in the Third Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> Signed by St. <hi>Auguſtin (Baruch</hi> only not named, becauſe an Appendix to <hi>Jeremiah</hi> whoſe Secretary he was) <hi>Can.</hi> 47.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The unbloody Sacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> in the Sixth Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> a <hi>Thouſand</hi> years, ſince, <hi>Can.</hi> 32. And alſo in the Ninth Council of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Decreed, <hi>That a Biſhop,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall communicate when Sacrifice</hi> is made.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Veneration,</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>Saints Relicks</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Apoſtolical Tradition) as alſo of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and <hi>holy Images,</hi> in the Second Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> Three Hundred and Fifty <hi>Fathers</hi> preſent, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 780. See more in <hi>Act</hi> 7. With the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Concurrences of Ancient <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Communion under one kind</hi> ſufficient in the Council of <hi>Conſtance, Seſſ.</hi> 13. and practis'd in the Church <hi>Twelve Hundred</hi> years ſince.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62979:12"/>6. <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and many more, too long to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, in the Council of <hi>Florence,</hi> and believed in the Primitive times.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And laſtly, the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> confirmed in the great Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> in which neer <hi>Thirteen Hundred Fathers</hi> aſſiſted: And in Seven or Eight other Councils, <hi>before that of Trent;</hi> and all the controverted Points, <hi>particularly,</hi> and by <hi>name,</hi> declared by ſome of your ſelves, to have been brought into <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk,</hi> above a <hi>Thouſand</hi> years ſince.</p>
            <p>Indeed, <hi>Fathers,</hi> when I had diligently examin'd this Truth, and found it moſt Evident, beyond the poſſibility of any juſt or reaſonable Contradiction; I was much ſcandaliz'd at the diſingenuity of your Writers, who, whilſt they accuſe others of <hi>Fallacy, Impoſture,</hi> and <hi>Impudence,</hi> dare advance ſo great, and demonſtrable a Falſehood in <hi>Matter of Fact,</hi> that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Ignorance</hi> can excuſe them; ſo they expoſe themſelves to the greateſt Cenſure of <hi>raſhneſs,</hi> and <hi>indiſcretion,</hi> as uncharitable, and unjuſt to thoſe whom they call their <hi>Enemies;</hi> as alſo unſafe, and abuſing the Credulity of their <hi>Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will not conſiſt with the <hi>Brevity</hi> here intended, to ſpeak fully of every particular Point in diſpute between us. I ſhall content my ſelf therefore to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm (as I do) that there are but <hi>few</hi> of them, which have not been <hi>tolerated,</hi> and <hi>practis'd</hi> (more or leſs) by ſome Eminent Members of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches; and which have not undeniable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Antiquity to ſupport them. I ſhall fix therefore upon two only; and conſider how far they may <hi>bear,</hi> and appear reaſonable to an Impartial Reader.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62979:13"/>1. The <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>Infallibility</hi> of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtanpiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>two firſts</hi> I think them ſo neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd one within the other, that, in proving <hi>one,</hi> we prove <hi>both;</hi> for if the Supream lawful. Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Authority reſides in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as repreſenting in its General Councils the <hi>Catholic Church aſſembled;</hi> then we have the promiſe of our Saviour, that his <hi>holy Spirit ſhall ever aſſiſt them,</hi> and <hi>guide them into all Truth.</hi> This I believe not only with a <hi>Popiſh,</hi> but with a <hi>Proteſtant Faith;</hi> for you have always told me (and I think you do not now deny it) that the Catholic Church cannot err in Fundamentals, or hold the Faith corrupt; the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty only lies in finding the <hi>Chatholic Church,</hi> which, (to avoid ſome unlucky conſequences that might diſturb your quiet) you prudently tell us, <hi>Is not certainly to be found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remains therefore, that we find this Supream lawful Authority which repreſents the viſible Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church. I have given you my Judgment al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: And that you may not believe I have err'd through <hi>Popiſh</hi> Affectation, I will produce alſo for my Juſtification the ſound Judgment of your beſt Reformers. <hi>Luther</hi> tells us, <hi>I do not deny but that the Biſhop of</hi> Rome is,
<note place="margin">Reſp. tred. propoſ.</note> hath been, <hi>and</hi> ought to be <hi>firſt of all; I believe he is above all other Biſhops, it is not lawful to deny his Supremacy. Melancton</hi> (the Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix of learning) ſays, <hi>That the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>is above all the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Card. Belay.</note> 
               <hi>that it is his Office to Judge in Controverſies, to govern, to watch over the Prieſts, to keep all Nations in Conformity, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Doctrines.</hi> Somaiſius. <hi>The Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>hath been, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62979:13"/>the firſt Metropolitan of</hi> Italy, <hi>and not only in</hi> Italy, <hi>nor only in the</hi> Weſt, <hi>but in all the: World. The other Metropolitans have been Chief in their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Diſtricts; but the Pope of</hi> Rome,
<note place="margin">Tract. ad Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondum.</note> (<hi>hath been Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan, and Primate, not only of ſome particular Dioceſs, but of All. Grotius</hi> (for whom I have a great reſpect, and think him a very learned Man) ſays the ſame thing, and proves this Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy belongs to the Pope <hi>de Jure divino:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Annot. Sup. Nov. Teſt.</note> This al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo inferr'd from <hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi> by <hi>Jacob Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright; Huſſe, Beza,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Fathers,</hi> you cannot ſay, but theſe Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Proteſtants were Men of great Learning, and that they had ſearcht, and underſtood Scripture and Hiſtory, as well as your ſelves; and if my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concurs with them in this Point (as I profeſs it doth) then have I found that lawful Supream Authority which I ſearched; and where this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is, there is Infallibility: Or if you can ſhew me Infallibility elſewhere, there alſo I am ſure I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a ſufficient Authority. The differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them I cannot eaſily diſcern: Infallibility is <hi>from God,</hi> and therefore we believe what is dictat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby, as <hi>from God:</hi> Supream Eccleſiaſtical Authority is alſo <hi>from God,</hi> and therefore we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey what it commands us, as the <hi>Ordinance of God.</hi> Infallibility concludes our Reaſons, and binds our Conſciences; Supream Church Authority binds alſo our Conſciences, and Superſedes all private Reaſon. Infallibility is above all humane Authority: The higheſt Church Authority can have no ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon Earth above it. Infallibility eſtabliſheth and ſupports Authority. Authority declares, and makes manifeſt the Infallibility. Infallibility, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62979:14"/>the Promiſes of Chriſt fail when Authority is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd: Authority lives not, when Infallibility ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. In a word, were there no Infallibility (as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there is) I would ſtill ſubmit my Reaſon, and regulate my Conſcience, according to the Decrees of the Supream, lawful Eccleſiaſtical Authority: This is my Belief, pray blame me not, I am <hi>humble,</hi> and have <hi>read Scripture,</hi> and upon my word, I am <hi>Sincere.</hi> You may believe otherwiſe, I preſume not to Judge you.</p>
            <p>After all this (worthy <hi>Fathers</hi>) I muſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to tell you, that I ſtill lay under ſome Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, before I could throughly aſſent to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (now believ'd) in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For you had often told me, that <hi>She</hi> had fallen from her <hi>Primitive Purity,</hi> and <hi>ſeparated her ſelf from that One Holy Catholic, and Apoſtolic Church.</hi> Anſw. to Prot. Quaeries p. 10. Declar'd alſo to be <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and the true Church <hi>Latent</hi> and <hi>Inviſible,</hi> by that famous <hi>Napper</hi> to <hi>King James, Brocard, Fulk, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt. Francus, Hoſpinian,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>Now, good <hi>Fathers,</hi> if She was once a pure, and uncorrupted Church, I preſume She remains ſo ſtill; for, give me leave to tell you, I do not well ſee, how She can ſeparate from her ſelf, for Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> (an Eminent Author among you) lookt upon it, as a thing ridiculous, if not impoſſible: for, ſays he, In the Caſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> p. 174. We have not forſaken, <hi>but only reformed another part of it</hi> (the Catholic Church) <hi>which part, we our ſelves are, and I ſuppoſe, you will not go about to perſwade us, that we have forſaken our ſelves, or</hi> our own Communion. Nor yet can She ſeparate from the Catholic Church; for the ſame Learned perſon tells us immediately after.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62979:14"/>And if you urge <hi>that we joined our ſelves to no other part, therefore were ſeparated from the whole; I ſay it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not, inaſmuch as our ſelves were a part of it, and ſtill continued ſo, and therefore can no more ſeparate from the whole, than from our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But next, ſuppoſing a part may ſeparate from it ſelf, or from the whole, pray be plain with me, worthy <hi>Fathers,</hi> and tell me, where that <hi>part,</hi> or that <hi>whole</hi> remain'd, from whence the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſeparated? For Separation, firſt ſuppoſes the Exiſtence of the thing, from which Separation is made; and is a deadly fault and foretold by the Apoſtles, as a miſchief which would happen in the <hi>laſt</hi> days. <hi>Remember ye the words which were ſpoken before of the Apoſtles, of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; how that they told you, that there ſhould be mockers in the laſt time, who ſhould walk after their own ungodly luſts; theſe be they who</hi> Separated <hi>themſelves,</hi> ſenſual,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude v.</hi> 17, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not the Spirit. Let us confider one another to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke unto love, and to good works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>not forgetting the aſſembling our ſelves together, and ſo much the more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.30.</note> 
               <hi>as ye ſee the day approaching. Alſo of your ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away diſciples after them.</hi> Now the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was not only viſible, but a very Eminent Church; St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>That her Faith is ſpoken of through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World:</hi> And certainly, that <hi>pure</hi> Church fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m which She Separated, muſt needs be by ſo much the <hi>more</hi> Eminent, as <hi>Her</hi> Apoſtacy was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, which forſook her. Tell me therefore where that pure Church remain'd, that we may retrieve the true Chriſtian Doctrine? If ſhe Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from her ſelf, then (beſides Mr. <hi>Chill.</hi> anſwer) I add, theſe Contradictions muſt be reciev'd as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62979:15"/>Truths: The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was at the ſame time, <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>Heterodox; pure</hi> and <hi>corrupt: ſound,</hi> but yet <hi>rotten:</hi> Or if you can diſtinguiſh them, ſhew me the <hi>Orthodox, Pure,</hi> and <hi>Sound</hi> part, which was left by the <hi>Heterodox, corrupt,</hi> and <hi>rotten</hi> Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> declare the time when the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was made, and where <hi>both</hi> were to be found? Theſe are <hi>plain</hi> Queſtions, and I muſt have a <hi>plain</hi> Anſwer, if it can be had.</p>
            <p>If you ſay She <hi>Separated</hi> from the Catholic Church; then tell me where that Catholic Church remain'd from which She Separated, and where She may be found; for in good faith, <hi>Fathers,</hi> my Salvation is highly concern'd in this Queſtion and I muſt be ſatisfied. If you tell me She is inviſible (as others have done) you plainly abuſe me; for I have long ſince learnt from your ſelves, as a Maxim in Philoſophy, that <hi>de non apparentibus, &amp; non exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentibus eadem eſt ratio.</hi> It is the ſame thing <hi>not at all to be,</hi> as <hi>not at all to appear.</hi> Beſides, excuſe me, if I take the word of our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, and all the Prophets in a hundred plain Texts (I preſume) not unknown to your ſelves, rather than your word in this Caſe. I profeſs therefore, tho my Reaſon is not able to cope with yours; yet I'll ſooner ſuffer my ſelf to be knockt down with a true <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Flayl,</hi> than with ſuch a <hi>Proteſtant Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ſay the Catholic Church <hi>fell,</hi> and was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners;</hi> then I anſwer, that Chriſt fail'd of his Promiſe, and ſo good night to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: If you ſay the Catholic Church did <hi>not</hi> fall, but kept the Unity of Faith <hi>Entire,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt,</hi> then I reply again, ſhew me where, and how I may find her? And from this reaſonable,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62979:15"/>and important Requeſt, you ſhall never beat me whilſt I live.</p>
            <p>If you think fit to perſwade me, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſeparated from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that the Church of <hi>England is,</hi> and ever <hi>hath been</hi> a part (at leaſt) of the Catholic Church which <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways</hi> preſerv'd the Faith entire, and uncorrupt; make it appear to me, <hi>Fathers,</hi> and I moſt hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſe to become the moſt <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Subject</hi> that ever liv'd under any Government. But I foreſee many Difficulties which I fear will prove invincible; as firſt, It is evident, that you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few years; and to prove that ſhe ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from you, will be (I doubt) no eaſie Task, nor have I yet ſeen it done. Next, That you were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in the ſame pernicious Errors with her, ever ſince <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the Monk, above a Thouſand years ſince: If my Computation be falſe, blame your own Authors, and rectifie my Judgment.</p>
            <p>Now, how you ſhould riſe a pure Church, after having been buried ſo many Hundred years in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Church, I do not eaſily underſtand. I have heard indeed of ſome Rivers, that have fallen into the Earth; and riſen up again, many Miles off; and of others, which for many Miles in the Sea, have ſtill retain'd the natural ſweetneſs of their own freſh Waters: If theſe compariſons may hold in Religion, yet how will you make them <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate</hi> with the <hi>conſtant, viſibility,</hi> and Demonſtration, in one caſe, and the Succeſſion of the <hi>Original Stream</hi> in the other, if you ſay that that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church was <hi>inviſible,</hi> or <hi>totally fell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you pretend to derive your Authority from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62979:16"/>the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when She was in her Purity and Perfection; let me tell you, here will be a very long Preſcription againſt you; and I know not how your <hi>Jus poſtliminium</hi> can take place in this caſe: But if it would, you muſt be reſtor'd by an Act of the ſame Supream Authority: you <hi>own'd</hi> her; you <hi>held of</hi> her; <hi>you reciev'd your</hi> Doctrine, and your <hi>Orders from</hi> her: Beſides (as hath been ſaid) She could by no means grant away her Authority independent from her; ſhew me <hi>that</hi> lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which reſtor'd you, and I ſubmit: Shew me your extraordinary <hi>Calling</hi> by thoſe Marks appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and practis'd in ſuch Caſes, both under the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Law,</hi> even to our own Century (I mean) <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Miracles,</hi> and I acquieſce.</p>
            <p>If you tell me, no time can preſcribe againſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth; nor is Authority neceſſary to reform an Error: In a general Senſe, I grant <hi>both.</hi> But the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here, is, concerning Truth, and Error themſelves. No body doubts, but that a <hi>certain</hi> Divine Truth is to be reciev'd, and a <hi>certain</hi> Error to be avoided; but we are now ſeeking for that Authority which ſhall declare this <hi>Truth,</hi> and ſet forth this <hi>Error.</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or Sin, is the breach of a Law, for without the Law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> Sin is dead: whence St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>That he had not known Luſt, except the Law had ſaid, thou ſhalt not covet.</hi> Now, as Sin ſuppoſes a Law, ſo Law requires an Authority: And as the <hi>one,</hi> ſo the <hi>other</hi> muſt be viſible. And to ſhew that this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is abſolutely neceſſary, we find our Saviour giving it to his Apoſtles, and themſelves exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and recommending it to others; ſo <hi>S. Paul</hi> adviſes <hi>Titus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Titus</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>To ſpeak, exhort, and rebuke with</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62979:16"/>
            <p>But what need Inſtances of this kind? Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath left us a <hi>Law of Faith,</hi> which in ſome of the moſt neceſſary Points, is not clear, and ſelf-Evident; whence the <hi>Arians</hi> of old (Men of great Learning) denied the Trinity, and Divinity of our Saviour; and they made a very conſiderable <hi>Body;</hi> Authority condemn'd them, and interpreted the Law, in thoſe Caſes, according to our preſent Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Faith. The <hi>Socinians,</hi> and <hi>Antitriniturians</hi> rebel againſt it to this day, and are neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, nor inconſiderable. <hi>Luther</hi> tells us, <hi>That Chriſt is a Saviour of vile, and little worth, and wanted himſelf a Saviour, Chriſtus ille vilis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Confeſ. Maj. de caen. Dom.</note> 
               <hi>nec magni pretij Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator eſt; immo Ipſe quoque Salvatore opus habet.</hi> And, that <hi>his Divinity ſuffer'd for us:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De conſil. part</hi> 2</note> pertinaciſſimè contra me pugnabant, quod Divinitas Chriſti pati non poſſet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>prop.</hi> 3.</note> He tells us further, <hi>That good Works are hurtful to Salvation,</hi> and <hi>that Faith doth not Juſtifie,</hi> except it be, <hi>even, without the leaſt good Works.</hi> Calvin alſo,
<note place="margin">Bilſons Survey.</note> and Beza, <hi>That Chriſt ſuffer'd in his Soul the pains of the damned,</hi> that he <hi>prayed unadviſedly, and was diſturb'd in his Senſes;</hi> That the <hi>Divine Subſtance,</hi> is (not wholly in three Perſons, but) <hi>diſtinct really, and truly,</hi> from <hi>Everlaſting, into three Perſons,</hi> and that there <hi>be three Divinities,</hi> as there <hi>be three Perſons.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanct. <hi>in loco Com. c. de Chriſto;</hi> Beza<hi>'s Confeſſion p.</hi> 1. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1585. Calvin in <hi>Act. Serveti.</hi> Whence <hi>Neuſerus</hi> (a Learned <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> and chief Paſtor at <hi>Heidelburg</hi>) revolting firſt to <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> and thence to <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> writ to <hi>Gerlachius</hi> (a Proteſtant Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher) from <hi>Conſtantinople July</hi> 2. 1574. ſaying, <hi>None is known to me in my time made an Arian, who was not firſt a Calviniſt;</hi> and then names ſeveral ſuch perſons: <hi>That God is the Author of Sin, moving, inclining, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62979:17"/>forcing the Will of man to Sin,</hi> Calvin <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>and l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Zuingl. Bucer,</hi> and ſeveral of our Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Engliſh Reformers, concur with them, in moſt of theſe blaſphemous, and heretical Opinions.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Fathers,</hi> if theſe Inſtances, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (which I abhor to mention) be not ſufficient; and weighty enough, to require a Supream Judge to determine the <hi>right Faith,</hi> and to condemn, and ſilence the <hi>wrong;</hi> then look nearer (at home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelves) and if all cannot prevail with you to believe, That the Law wanted a Judge, and that therefore Chriſt was pleaſed, in his Wiſdom, and Goodneſs to leave us Judges, as long as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his Law ſhould be in force: Then pray excuſe me, if my <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> and the <hi>reverent No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> which I have of a Juſt God, and a Merciful Saviour; totally force my Judgment and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to diſſent from you in this particular; and let us proceed.</p>
            <p>If you ſay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> uſurpt upon you; I anſwer, (if ſuch a thing was) It was in <hi>Diſcipline only,</hi> and <hi>External Government;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> but in <hi>ſome particulars,</hi> with which I meddle not: If you tell me a ſtory of the <hi>Abbot of Bangor;</hi> I anſwer, the particular ground of it is evidently <hi>falſe,</hi> and <hi>forg'd;</hi> and at beſt (all circumſtances conſider'd) of <hi>little conſequence.</hi> The <hi>plain Truth</hi> is <hi>this;</hi> The <hi>Brittains</hi> received the Chriſtian Faith, even in the days of the Apoſtles: But (being perſecuted at home by the <hi>Romans, Picts,</hi> and <hi>Saxons,</hi>) Religion fled to the Mountains, and bordering parts of <hi>Wales.</hi> At the ſame time, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was no leſs afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Heathen Emperours; and no wonder, if in theſe days, and circumſtances, there was but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62979:17"/>little Correſpondence between <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi> But when the Church (brought forth from her ſubterraneous Refuges, and ſet upon a Hill,) began to enlarge her ſelf, and propagate the Goſpel, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Commands of our Saviour, <hi>Go ye and Preach unto all Nations: Gregory</hi> the Great, ſent <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the Monk into <hi>England</hi> (ſomewhat before the year <hi>Six Hundred,</hi>) to ſee how Matters went here in this long interval of ſilence, and diſtractions. In ſhort, the <hi>Brittains</hi> knew him not (and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) until he had confirm'd his Commiſſion by Miracles, and ſuch, as none yet ever denied. The great Errors which he found among them, were chiefly, <hi>two;</hi> Their Aſiatic Error, concerning the <hi>keeping of Eaſter;</hi> and diſſent from the uſe of the Roman Church in the <hi>adminiſtring of Baptiſm:</hi> And altho in ſome other Matters, they differ'd from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet <hi>Auguſtin</hi> promiſed to <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate thoſe,</hi> provided, they would rectifie <hi>theſe,</hi> which the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Biſhops conſented to, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>That it was the right way of Juſtice, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which</hi> Auſtin <hi>taught.</hi>
               <q>Si his tribus mihi ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperare vultis, <hi>ut Paſcha ſuo tempore celebretis;</hi> ut <hi>miniſterium Baptizandi juxta morem Rom. &amp; Apoſt. Ecoleſiae</hi> compleatis: Ut genti Anglorum, una nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum praedicetis Verbum Domini, <hi>Caetera,</hi> quae agitis, quamvis Moribus noſtris contraria, aequanimiter cuncta tolerabimus? Cum Brittones confitentur, Intellexiſſe ſe, <hi>veram eſſe viam Juſtitiae</hi> quam praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caret Auguſtinus.</q> 
               <hi>Beda Hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Hence we may obſerve, That the two great faults which <hi>Auſtin</hi> found with the <hi>Brittains,</hi> were, about <hi>Eaſter</hi> and Baptiſm; that the <hi>Brittains,</hi> at firſt, highly oppos'd this Innovation, but, that in all other
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62979:18"/>
               <hi>Subſtantials,</hi> they agreed. That <hi>Auſtin</hi> is ſeverely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd for bringing into <hi>England</hi> the <hi>Popiſh Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> other Points, <hi>by name,</hi> controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us at this day, is plain, from neer twenty E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Proteſtant Authors, both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad.</hi> And that the Brittiſh Biſhops, did not except againſt any of theſe, ſave only <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and Baptiſm, is confeſt.</p>
            <p>Now, after all this, can we believe that the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> who earneſtly contradicted <hi>Auſtin</hi> in theſe ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Points, and were ſo tenacious of their own Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, would have ſilently recieved <hi>ſo many,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably <hi>much greater</hi> Points of Faith, had they in like manner diſagreed from him therein? <hi>Credat Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus Apella.</hi> The conſequence which I draw from all this, <hi>is,</hi> that <hi>the ſame Doctrines</hi> (theſe two Points excepted) <hi>which</hi> Auſtin <hi>taught the</hi> Saxons, <hi>had been deliver'd to the</hi> Brittains, <hi>from the Apoſtles:</hi> If you underſtand otherwiſe, I ſhall be glad to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; Or, if you can give us a better Authority than venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> you will do well to produce it. In the mean time, when we conſider the great <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> of <hi>St. Gregory,</hi> ſo eſteem'd by all ſober men; the Piety of <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf, and of <hi>Bede</hi> (who writes the Story) He muſt be a bold man, who (without better proof than I have hitherto ſeen) dares accuſe theſe three great Perſons, and the whole Chriſtian World, at that time of Idolatry, and all thoſe other damnable Crimes, then taught, of which you are pleaſed to ſay, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at preſent is guilty. If you go higher, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject a Letter of Pope <hi>Eleutherius</hi> to King <hi>Lucius,</hi> I demur.</p>
            <p>But, I take it for granted, that theſe old Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are <hi>thredbare,</hi> and will not hold Water;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62979:18"/>otherwiſe, I would humbly adviſe you, to inſiſt totally upon them; for if you can make out your <hi>Lawful, Supream, Independent</hi> Authority, in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Matters of Faith <hi>without Appeal;</hi> trouble not your ſelves, nor abuſe your Friends with Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Artificial Pamphlets; about <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Guides</hi> in <hi>Controverſies; Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Senſe,</hi> againſt <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> and, I know not what, to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but ſtick cloſe to your <hi>Authority,</hi> make it out plain, and <hi>you carry all before you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In good earneſt, Reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> I ſee but one way how you'l evade theſe Difficulties which preſs hard upon you, and it is <hi>this;</hi> That you have an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Rule,</hi> Gods Holy Word, containing all things neceſſary to Salvation. And Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> tells us p. 92. <hi>The Scripture is a Rule, as, ſufficiently Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo, ſufficiently Intelligible, in things neceſſary; to all that have underſtanding, whether learned or unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Now, if the <hi>Scripture</hi> be a <hi>Guide</hi> and a <hi>Judge,</hi> as well as a <hi>Rule,</hi> Then have you been to blame all this while that you have not told us particularly, where the Catholic Church was; for certainly, where the Bible is, and where all men that have <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, whether learned, or unlearned,</hi> by reading it, hold all things neceſſary to Salvation, <hi>there</hi> the Catholic Church <hi>is,</hi> whether at <hi>Rome,</hi> or in <hi>London:</hi> and I will not believe ſo ill of any, who, in ſuch Caſe, read the Scripture, as to imagine that they <hi>wilfully</hi> oppoſe a Truth, which is clear to them; and Mr. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingworth</hi> tells me p. 367. That <hi>Believing all that is clear to me in Scripture, I muſt needs believe all Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, and ſo I cannot incur Hereſie, which is oppoſite to ſome Fundamental.</hi> In a word, whereſoever there <hi>is,</hi> or <hi>was</hi> a Bible, and a Man of <hi>underſtanding, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62979:19"/>learned, or unlearned,</hi> that read it; there was a certain number of the true Catholic Church, <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>uncorrupt:</hi> For the ſame hand again tells us, p. 101. <hi>The Scripture ſufficiently informing me what is Faith, muſt alſo of neceſſity teach me what is Hereſie; that which is ſtraight, will plainly teach us what is crooked:</hi> So here is not only a Member, but (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my underſtanding) the Repreſentative of the whole Catholic Church; for here is <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and further than that, I ſeek not. But if the holy Bible be a certain Rule, but withal, that <hi>this Perſon of underſtanding whether learned or unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> be not ſufficiently qualified to find out <hi>certainly</hi> all <hi>things neceſſary to Salvation;</hi> and of <hi>neceſſity to teach what Hereſie is</hi> (and I confeſs I ſhrewdly ſuſpect, that there may be many in the World, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, <hi>with a wet Finger,</hi> perform all this) then are we to ſeek again for a Judge and an Authority; and are got no further than we were ſixteen Hundred years ſince, when the Scripture was firſt acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the Word of God.</p>
            <p>But to do Juſtice (worthy <hi>Fathers</hi>) to you, and to my ſelf, let us <hi>further</hi> conſider, theſe, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeming Abſurdities, which appear (at firſt ſight) ſuch ſurpriſing Doctrines, that they make a Man <hi>gape,</hi> and <hi>ſtare,</hi> as if he were Thunder ſtruck, or had ſome ſtrange Apparition. Why truly your great Champion (the Learned <hi>Chillingworth</hi>) brings you ſtill off, with flying Colours; I'l give you his own Excellent words in <hi>p.</hi> 102. Where he ſays, <hi>For me to believe further this or that to be the true ſenſe of ſome Scriptures; or to believe the true ſenſe of them, and to avoid the falſe, is not neceſſary either to my Faith, or Salvation; for if God would have had
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62979:19"/>his meaning in theſe places certainly known, how could it ſtand with his Wiſdom, to be wanting to his own Will, and End, as to ſpeak obſcurely? Or how can it conſiſt with his Juſtice to require of Men to know certainly the meaning of thoſe words, which he himſelf hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed?</hi> p. 18. <hi>For my Error, or Ignorance in what is not plainly contained in Scripture, after my beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour uſed, to ſay, that God will damn me for ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, who am a lover of Him, and lover of Truth, is, to rob Man of his Comfort, and God of his Goodneſs, is, to make Man deſperate, and God a Tyrant.</hi> But he goes on p. 92. <hi>The Scripture is a Rule, as ſufficiently Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo ſufficiently Intelligible, in things neceſſary, to all who have underſtanding, whether learned, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned; neither is any thing neceſſary to be believed, but what is plainly reveal'd; for to ſay, that when a place in Scripture, by reaſon of ambiguous Terms, lies indifferent between divers Senſes, whereof one is true and the other falſe, that God obligeth men under pain of damnation, not to miſtake through Error, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Frailty, is, to make God a Tyrant, and to ſay, that he requires of us certainly to attain that End, for the attaining whereof, we have no certain means;</hi> What an eaſie, compendious, and certain Rule of Faith is this?</p>
            <p>But before we proceed, let us conſider what our Author underſtands by— <hi>His meaning in theſe places—ſpeaking obſcurely— plainly contain'd in Scripture— things neceſſary— ambiguous Terms lying indifferent between divers Senſes.</hi> By all which he ſeems to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, that there may be ſome <hi>ambiguous Terms</hi> in Scripture, which, becauſe they are not plain to every Underſtanding, therefore not neceſſary to be truly underſtood and believ'd.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62979:20"/>
            <p>Indeed had he told us, what was <hi>not</hi> ambiguous, and what <hi>not</hi> neceſſary, he had made our work much ſhorter. I ſhall preſume therefore to reduce the Queſtion; and affirm, that if he means any thing by all this, he muſt mean the whole <hi>New Teſtament</hi> to be ambiguous; for let him ſhew me any <hi>one</hi> Text of Doctrine from the <hi>firſt</hi> of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> to the <hi>laſt</hi> of the <hi>Revelations</hi> (the Moral Law, and the Law of Nature only excepted) which he thinks to be the moſt clear; and I will produce whole Bodies of learned Chriſtians, who diſpute it, and believe contrary to one another in it. If ſo, then it appears <hi>demonſtrably,</hi> and by <hi>matter of Fact,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> is <hi>ambiguous,</hi> and by conſequence every Man is ſafe, in the Belief of the moſt oppoſite Doctrines, if he uſeth his beſt Endeavours (to which alſo he hath given a great Latitude) to underſtand it aright: For ſays he, <hi>By my beſt endeavour, I mean, ſuch a meaſure of induſtry, as humane Prudence, and ordinary Diſcretion (my abilities and opportunities, my diſtractions, and hindrances, and all other things conſider'd)</hi> marry, and a great conſideration it is; <hi>ſhall adviſe me unto, in a matter of ſuch conſequence.</hi> Chill. p. 18.19.</p>
            <p>The whole Senſe (as far as it concerns my purpoſe) runs thus, There are ſome <hi>ambiguous</hi> Terms which lie indifferent between divers Senſes, whereof one is <hi>true,</hi> and the other falſe; but if a Man of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, whether learn'd, or unlearn'd,</hi> uſes his beſt endeavour to underſtand them (that is, by reading Scripture) he will <hi>ſafely Err,</hi> or, <hi>not Err at all,</hi> or elſe, <hi>God is a Tyrant.</hi> That there are ambiguous Terms, is moſt certain; for we find many moſt Learned, Pious Men, differing from, and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting one another in moſt Points, generally repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62979:20"/>Fundamental. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That in Fundamentals, no man can ſafely Err, becauſe it is of the Eſſence of Chriſts Church, to hold the Unity of Faith, in Fundamentals, uncorrupt. And Laſtly, Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are inclined to believe, that God is no Tyrant. Our Author, from his own Promiſes, and by what hath been already ſaid, ſeems evidently to draw this Concluſion; that <hi>poſſibly</hi> and <hi>very probably,</hi> a Man may ſafely Err in Fundamentals, or God muſt be a Tyrant. Now, for my part, when I read his excellent Works, <hi>lately,</hi> and <hi>ſome years ſince,</hi> I always drew from the <hi>ſame</hi> Premiſes a moſt <hi>different</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; that is, That ſince there are ambiguous Terms in Points highly Fundamental, therefore, leſt we ſhould <hi>damnably Err</hi> in theſe, or, more <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly</hi> think God to be a Tyrant, I concluded, that God, in his Wiſdom and Goodneſs, had certainly left us ſome <hi>infallible, viſible Authority,</hi> which might unerringly deliver to us, the <hi>true Senſe</hi> of theſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous Terms.</p>
            <p>Now beſides the ſtrong Evidences which we have from Scripture to believe this; As for Example, when our Saviour ſays, <hi>Go ye into all the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>and Preach the Goſpel to every Creature, He that believeth, and is baptized ſhall be ſaved, but he that</hi> believeth not <hi>ſhall be damned. As thou haſt ſent me into the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo have I alſo ſent them into the world.</hi> And again,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily Prophets, Thirdly</hi> Teachers, <hi>after that Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, then gifts of healing; helps,</hi> Governments,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of Tongues: So alſo. And he gave ſome Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and</hi> Teachers. And Laſtly, that this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was to continue to the End of the Word. <hi>All
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62979:21"/>power is given unto me in Heaven, and in Earth, go ye therefore and</hi> teach <hi>all Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. c. ult.</note> teaching <hi>them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, and lo,</hi> I am with you always, even unto the End of of the World: I ſay <hi>beſides this,</hi> and much more to this purpoſe, let all ſober Chriſtians witneſs for me, whether it be not more <hi>pious,</hi> more <hi>rational,</hi> more <hi>comfortable to our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>reſpectful to God,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude as I have done; that God hath left us ſuch an Authority (eſpecially ſince ſuch an Authority, with good Reaſon, offers it ſelf to us) than to agree with our Author, That either God is a Tyrant, or, we may ſafely Err in Fundamentals?</p>
            <p>Since therefore from our Authors own Premiſes (notwithſtanding the weight and plainneſs of them) I ſhould have made ſo contrary a Concluſion; it may happen, that in reading the Bible, we might make as different Interpretations; and whilſt he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves Jeſus Chriſt to be the <hi>Son of God, Conſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> and <hi>Equal</hi> with the Father, as to his <hi>Divinity;</hi> I may affirm Chriſt to be <hi>meer Man,</hi> and only Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inſpired. Such things I have heard of; but it may be, <hi>worthy Fathers,</hi> you may not think this a neceſſary Point; then indeed, this Inſtance would be impertinent.</p>
            <p>But we muſt not thus leave our admirable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; for from this his well conſider'd Doctrine, we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That according to this Rule, there can never be Schiſm, or Hereſie in the World, until a man can <hi>divide</hi> from <hi>himſelf;</hi> or, a man, condemning himſelf, <hi>obſtinately</hi> ſtand out againſt his clear Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Scripture, and ſo ſin <hi>wilfully,</hi> and without excuſe; and in this laſt Point Biſhop <hi>Bromhall</hi> and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62979:21"/>Dr. <hi>Still.</hi> unanimouſly concur with our Author. Now believing in Charity, that theſe wonders have ſeldom, or never hapned, therefore I ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> miſtook when he ſaid,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>There muſt be Hereſies among you,</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> much to blame when he wrote his Goſpel (many years after the death of our Saviour) againſt the Hereſies of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion,</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That all Men of underſtanding, whether learned, or unlearned, are in the direct road to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and found Members of the true Catholic Church, provided they be lovers of God, and of Truth, and follow their own Senſe of Scripture, altho they differ in ſome of the moſt Fundamental Points of Faith. Now (beſides the extravagancy of this Opinion in general) it ſeems particularly le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd againſt the poor Papiſts, becauſe they often ſubmit their own <hi>private Interpretations</hi> (with great reaſon) to the Judgment, and Interpretation of the <hi>Church:</hi> But if this be ſo damnable a fault in Papiſts, pray take care not to exact this reſignation from your own Subjects; and ſo farewel to Authority.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, That there are ſome ambiguous Terms which lie indifferent between divers Senſes, whereof the one is true, and the other falſe: This, we readily grant, for the truth of it is ſo manifeſt that there is never a Point in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſtian Faith, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever by you, and us eſteem'd Fundamental, but hath been denied by whole Bodies of Learned Men; who (as you do) made Scripture their Rule. But when you tell us, further, that the true Senſe of them is not neceſſary to Faith, or Salvation (for if God would have <hi>had his meaning in theſe places certainly known,</hi> why <hi>ſhould he ſpeak obſcurely?)</hi> Then methinks,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62979:22"/>
               <hi>Fathers,</hi> you not only make the Apoſtles write <hi>Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently,</hi> and to no purpoſe; but you have brought all ſorts of Sectaries, Schiſmatics, and Heretics (if any ſuch have been) and alſo the <hi>Turks,</hi> themſelves (provided they read the Scripture) within the Pale of the Chriſtian Church: Nay, more, you have made them in ſuch Caſe, equal with the beſt true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in it. And indeed if the good wiſhes, and prayers of our <hi>Teckelites</hi> might prevail as much on one ſide; as the Principles of your Champion, have capacitated the <hi>Turks</hi> on the other ſide; I know no reaſon they have to deſpair of ſeeing the Cathedral of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Conſecrated by the <hi>Mufti</hi> of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> By this time, moſt Reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> I ſhould think that you, as well as my ſelf, ſhould be very weary of this Learned Author. Being fixt therefore to my Authority, and the <hi>more,</hi> from the Eminent danger of his <hi>looſe,</hi> and <hi>pernitious Principles,</hi> I am reſolved, that nothing ſhall move me, except the <hi>abſur'd</hi> and <hi>monſtrous Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation</hi> (as you are pleas'd to call it) may have of it ſelf force enough to ruine, and overturn ſo ſolid a Foundation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="remarks">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62979:22"/>
            <head>REMARKS Upon ſome late DISCOURSES AGAINST <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Muſt confeſs that this great Point ſeem'd the moſt difficult to me, of any that are Controverted between the two Churches: and for theſe Reaſons; <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe I did not rightly apprehend the Catholic Explication of the <hi>Natural</hi> Body of Chriſt in the Sacrament. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe (from this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding of mine) I believed that the Body of Chriſt being in two places, at the ſame time, imply'd a contradiction, which I ſuppos'd the Omnipotency of God could not ſupport. And laſtly, becauſe I thought the <hi>Fathers</hi> had been expreſs againſt this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>I apply'd my ſelf to the reading of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; and diſcourſing with ſome Learned Men, on both ſides; and found <hi>firſt</hi> from the Catholics, That altho they Profeſs and Believe the Natural Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt to be <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; yet they tell us, That it is not there after
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62979:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62979:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62979:24"/>a <hi>Natural</hi> manner, as it was upon the Earth, or upon the Croſs, but after a <hi>Spiritual, Supernatural,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloody</hi> manner. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it is indeed a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to ſay a Body <hi>is</hi> here, and <hi>not</hi> here at the ſame time: but to ſay that the Glorified Body of Chriſt, may be by accident, and by the power of God, in many places, or <hi>ubi's</hi> at the ſame time, is ſo far from a Contradiction, that it gives it not a more ſovereign Exiſtence, than what we allow to Angels, or to the Soul in a Mans Body, which altho it be a Subſtance, is yet really, ſubſtantially and at the ſame time, <hi>totally</hi> in the Finger of a Man, and <hi>totally</hi> in his foot, and <hi>totally</hi> in every part, and yet <hi>totally</hi> in the whole Body, <hi>tota in toto, &amp; tota in qualibe parte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Laſtly, for the <hi>Fathers,</hi> I found in them, not only moſt plain, demonſtrable, and Invincible Authorities aſſerting the Real Preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament after a ſubſtantial manner; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that thoſe very Citations produc'd by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to deſtroy this Doctrine of the Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, were moſt of them (if not all) ſo fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, or ſo agreable to the Catholic Faith, that if any of them remain'd ſtill obſcure, there want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not twenty plain places to Interpret them by; But more of theſe hereafter.</p>
            <p>Here I conſider'd the Proteſtant Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and found them generally diſſatisfactory, and inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; chiefly upon this account, that they brought continually the ſame Objections, which tho they had been anſwer'd a hundred times over by Catholics (both Ancient and Modern) yet I found no Reply to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſe Anſwers, or at leaſt, ſuch as handled thoſe which were moſt material; ſo that I perceiv'd they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62979:24"/>danc't always in a Ring, without advancing a ſtep towards a ſubſtantial and convincing Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. At laſt I was recommended to a late <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe againſt Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which treating parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of that Subject; and being wrote (as I was inform'd) by an Eminent Proteſtant Divine, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to pitch upon that, and from thence take my Meaſures, how far I ought to receive this great Catholic Doctrine. I read it over and over with great attention, and before I ſpeak particularly of any thing contained in it; I think it Juſt to give this Character of it in general, <hi>viz.</hi> that it ſeems to be writ without <hi>Modeſty, Charity, Sincerity,</hi> or <hi>Good Manners.</hi> Without <hi>Modeſty,</hi> In that a private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, upon preſumption of his own Parts, and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhall dare to ridicule ſo great a Myſtery of the Chriſtian Religion (I ſpeak of the Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, according to the Doctrine of Catholics, and Lutherans, excluding at preſent the Mode (as they term it) or Manner, Tranſubſtantiation) and this Doctrine own'd, and profeſt not two Hundred years ſince, generally through the Chriſtian World, and at preſent, by at leaſt eight parts, in ten; and amongſt theſe ſome perſons extreamly above him in Place and Authority; and thouſands (for ought we know) equal, if not above him, in Learning, Piety, and Reaſon; Thus I ſay to ridicule, and burleſque ſo great a Doctrine of the Chriſtian Faith, is much more dangerous, and ſcandalous to the Chriſtian Religion, than that <hi>ſtupid, abſur'd</hi> and <hi>monſtrous</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (as he calls it) againſt which he writes. For my part, I profeſs, if ſo many Men of Senſe and Reaſon, and theſe improv'd to the heigth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62979:25"/>by Study and Learning, may not only be deceiv'd in ſo great a Point of Religion; but miſtaken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>folly, madneſs, non-ſenſe,</hi> and <hi>Contradiction;</hi> I know not what will become of Chriſtianity it ſelf; for if theſe can ſo groſly Err, in Matters which are as equally Evident (upon all accounts) to their Senſe and Reaſon, as to the Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of any other; I am ſure a Man is much leſs ſecure in truſting to this ſingle Diſcourſer, or any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to him; and ſo farewel to Both.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, It is without <hi>Charity,</hi> for ſince he hath made (as he thinks) the Catholic Doctrine ſo demonſtrably falſe and abſur'd; all Catholics who believe it, (tho never ſo Learned, Honeſt and Pious) muſt be either <hi>Knaves</hi> or <hi>Fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Without <hi>Sincerity,</hi> becauſe all his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Objections (and many more) have been Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed formerly above Seventy years ſince: And Lately, within theſe Seventeen years, by Catholics them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; with their Subſtantial Anſwers to them. Now to have dealt ſincerely, he ought to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to theſe Anſwers, which would have ſet us forward, and drawn us to ſome Point; and not have run round, as in a Magical Circle, without ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to break through the infatuation of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Reaſon.</p>
            <p>And next, to have dealt <hi>Sincerely,</hi> he ought not to have produc't a ſcrap of a Sentence from a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and left out thoſe immediate preceeding, or ſucceeding Words which explicated the whole Senſe. For Inſtance, His firſt is from <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> whom he produces ſaying, theſe Words: <hi>Our Blood and Fleſh are nouriſhed, by the Converſion of that Food which we receive in the Euchariſt,</hi> p. 11. But the whole Sentence
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62979:25"/>runs thus; <hi>For we do not receive this as common Bread, or common Drink, but as by the Word of God. Jeſus Chriſt our Redeemer, being made Man, had both Fleſh and Blood for the ſake of our Salvation; juſt ſo are we taught, that That Food over which Thanks are given by Prayers, in his own Words, and whereby our Blood, and Fleſh are by a change nouriſhed,</hi> Is the Fleſh and Blood of the Incarnate Jeſus: <hi>For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in the Commentaries written by them, call'd the Goſpels, have recorded that Jeſus ſo commanded them.</hi> This I think altogether, makes little for our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer; eſpecially if he had been ſincere enough to have told us, how the <hi>Fathers</hi> generally, as St. <hi>Irenaeus, Cyril, Chryſoſt. Greg. Nyſſ.</hi> and others expound the nouriſhment of the Body, and as ſhall be ſhewn hereafter. So alſo he quotes <hi>Theodoret,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The myſtical Symbols after Conſecration, do not paſs out of their own Nature, for they remain in their former Subſtance, Figure, and Appearance: And may be ſeen, and handled</hi> p. 19. <hi>Theoderet</hi> goes on: <hi>The myſtical Signs are underſtood to be that which they are made, and they are believed and</hi> ador'd <hi>as being thoſe very things, which they are believed.</hi> Now if they may be <hi>adored,</hi> I ſuppoſe they mean ſomewhat more than Signs and Figures; or elſe the Adoration of holy Images is more Ancient, than Proteſtants have hitherto allowed: And had our Diſcourſer been <hi>Sincere,</hi> he might have told us, how the Catholics interpret all this, to be moſt conſiſtent with their Faith, and confuted them if he could.</p>
            <p>But Fourthly, His Diſcourſe is writ without <hi>Good Manners,</hi> for (ſetting aſide his diſreſpect to a Religious Duty.) methinks when he knew ſo many <hi>Princes, Kings, Emperors, Biſhops, Metropolitans,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62979:26"/>Patriarchs,</hi> and moſt Learned Men of all Sorts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this Doctrine of the Real Preſence, and Tranſubſtantiation; he ought to have forborn ſuch words as <hi>Impudence.</hi> p. 2. <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> p. 24. <hi>Monſter of Tranſubſtantiation</hi> p. 25. <hi>Monſtrous inſupportably abſur'd ſtupidity of this Doctrine</hi> p. 33. <hi>Abſur'd and Senſeleſs Doctrine, Legerdemain and Jugling Tricks of Falſhood and Impoſture, Hocus Pocus, a cheat and fooliſh Doctrine</hi> p. 34. But here the Diſcourſer is very angry; and indeed <hi>Fathers,</hi> I ſhould even from hence ſhrewdly ſuſpect that our Diſcourſer is no true Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally more moderate and civil; but we ſhall have further occaſion to ſpeak of this hereafter: In the mean time I thought fit to take thus much no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of theſe things; that we might conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a Writer (notwithſtanding all his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial daſhes) be probably endued with that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian humble Temper, which we might expect from a Doctor of Chriſts Church, pretending alſo (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other Miracles than his wonderful Reaſon) to reform almoſt the whole Chriſtian World; but let us ſee whether his good Reaſons will make us amends by giving us ſome better Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>Several Impertinences, and Quibbles appear in many parts of his Diſcourſe; as for Inſtance: He proves in <hi>p.</hi> 4. That a Sacrament may be inſtituted by figurative Expreſſions, becauſe a <hi>Sacrament is a Figare it ſelf of ſome Inviſible Grace, &amp;c.</hi> Now I had always thought, that a Man might deliver a Sign or Figure, exhibiting ſome Inviſible kindneſs in the moſt plain and literal Terms, that poſſibly could be invented; for Example, I am perſwaded the Diſcourſer might have exhibited or deliver'd, his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62979:26"/>Pamphlet; or Picture (which are Figures of his Mind, or Perſon) as a Token of his love to his Friend in a moſt plain litteral Speech; without the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a figurative Sentence, except for the ſake of his Quibble: For my part, I think the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a Figure, or any thing elſe, is beſt in plain words. But then the Pains he takes, and Wit that is ſpent, firſt to obtrude upon Catholics the falſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a <hi>Miracle</hi> (according to his acceptation of a Miracle) and then to laugh at his own Jeſt; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the power of the Prieſt in being able <hi>to work ſo great a Miracle, as to make God.</hi> Pag. 31. is really ſuch Stuff, as certainly he never deſign'd for any other uſe, than to rub the itching Ears of the moſt illiterate among the Vulgar. I confeſs, <hi>Fathers,</hi> it workt no good effect upon me, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will (I ſhould think) upon any ſober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; for every body ſure underſtands his Fallacy concerning the power (of the Prieſt, and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles. But inſtead of that, had he replied to ſome ſolid Diſcourſe of Catholics, concerning the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Sacrament it ſelf, I know not how far the Authority, which my Reaſon had fixt in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> would have ſupported me againſt his Arguments.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſeparated the looſe Accidents of his Diſcourſe from the more ſubſtantial part; I will now examine <hi>that</hi> as far as is neceſſary according to the beſt aſſiſtance of my impertial Reaſon and Underſtanding; and ſhall follow him according to his own Method.</p>
            <p>He ſuppoſes five Grounds or Reaſons, for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, or the Real Preſence (according to a literal Senſe) which he pretends
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62979:27"/>to confute: The firſt is from the <hi>Authority of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and (among other things as little to the purpoſe) he tells us p. 7. <hi>That he doth not believe any ſenſible Man, who had never heard of Tranſubſtantiation being ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon theſe words,</hi> This is my Body, <hi>would upon reading the Inſtitution of the Sacrament in the Goſpel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have imagined any ſuch thing to be meant by our Saviour in thoſe words; but would have underſtood his meaning to have been,—This Bread ſignifies my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And do this for a memorial of me:</hi> Where you may obſerve, worthy <hi>Fathers,</hi> that he excludes alſo the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> in a litteral ſenſe (as ſhall be ſhewn hereafter). He goes on: <hi>But ſure it would never have entred into any Mans mind, to have thought that our Saviour did literally hold himſelf in his hand, and gave away himſelf from himſelf with his own hands.</hi> Now altho I dare not pretend to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret all Scripture (a lawful ſufficient Interpreter being the thing I look for) yet, ſince he hath put the Caſe, I preſume to ſay thus much: That if a ſenſible <hi>Turk,</hi> or <hi>Pagan,</hi> who had never heard of the great Myſteries of Chriſtianity, ſhould ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly read the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> poſſibly he would not have underſtood theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> in a literal ſenſe; neither do I think he would ever have eſtabliſht the Doctrine of the Hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Union; The Conſubſtantiality of the Son; The Trinity; Predeſtination and Free-will; with many other Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if he were govern'd only by his humane Reaſon, as our Diſcourſer ſeems to be) and yet all this while he might have had a great eſteem of the moral part, and have believed Chriſt a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon divinely inſpired: For my part, I fear I ſhould
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62979:27"/>never have overcome theſe Difficulties upon my own ſtrength; and yet I believe the Trinity as firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I believe there is a God. Whether the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer doth ſo or not, I cannot ſay: But ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Man already well grounded in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, and having heard that the Doctrine of the Real Preſence, had been believed, in a lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſenſe, by the greateſt part of moſt Learned, and Pious Chriſtians through all Ages; And, that the Scriptures containing this Doctrine, were writ ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years after the death of our Saviour, in which time the Sacrament had been celebrated by them; and by conſequence, if the Apoſtles had not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood this Myſtery according to a literal Senſe, they had time, and reaſon plainly to have expounded it otherwiſe, and have given us warning of this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty (as was done to the Carnal <hi>Caphernaites</hi>) and not all three punctually agreed in the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, without any caution of a dangerous Figure in them: In ſuch Caſe, I ſay, the Doctrine of the Real Preſence, to ſuch a Perſon (having laid aſide all prejudices) is as clear in Scripture, as moſt of thoſe other great Myſteries are; and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe I cannot imagine why our Bleſſed Saviour ſhould ever have made uſe of theſe Terms, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> beſides many other ſuch like Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, except he really intended a literal Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; for what neceſſary relation hath a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and Blood, to the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, more than to the Sacrament of Baptiſm? Why a Conſecration in that Sacrament, yet none either in Baptiſm or others? Might not Chriſt (with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence be it ſpoken) have ſaid much more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet ſufficiently to the ſame purpoſe; <hi>Take
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62979:28"/>this Bread, and Cup of Bleſſing in remembrance of that Paſſion of mine which is now at hand, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as ye take it worthily, it ſhall conveigh to your Souls, inviſible Grace, and many other Benefits?</hi> Would not this have fully anſwered the End of <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and our Diſcourſer's Doctrine, concerning this Sacrament? But why doth the God of Mercy and Truth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us to eat his Body, and drink his Blood aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring us, that, except we eat his Fleſh we have no life in us, if he did not really intend we ſhould do ſo? But, except he be really and ſubſtantially pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Sacrament, we can neither eat his Body, nor drink his Blood; for to take the Figure for the Subſtance, is idle in any Command, which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively orders the Subſtance, if the Subſtance poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly can be had; and in this Caſe, it is impious, becauſe he that commanded the Subſtance, is able to give it us; and if he did not deſign to give it us, we have reaſon to believe he would not have commanded it in ſuch expreſs terms: Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſince there was no neceſſity, no, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of uſing thoſe words according to our Diſcourſer's Interpretation: For if by his Body, he meant the <hi>Figure</hi> only of his Body, what good doth that Figure do us? Or how doth it ſatisfie the Command, or why ſhould Bread be the Figure of his Body? Since Figures of this Figure, that is to ſay, the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> and <hi>Manna</hi> deſcending from Heaven, were much more noble, and proper <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting,</hi> than the thing <hi>Repreſented;</hi> and yet neither was Manna nor the Lamb called his Body, as the Bread is, in the Sacrament? The Expreſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This Paſſover is our Saviour, and our Refuge</hi> p. 7. Is nothing at all to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62979:28"/>the purpoſe, nor could the Paſchal Lamb be taken <hi>really</hi> and <hi>truly</hi> for God their Saviour, or their expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Meſſian; becauſe there was no ſuch thing men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ted in the Inſtitution of the Paſſover. On the contrary, it was inſtituted in the plaineſt Manner, and moſt intelligible, and ſo free from all figurative Expreſſions, that there are no leſs than 12 <hi>Verſes</hi> in explaining every Circumſtance of the Action. <hi>They ſhall take to them every Man a Lamb, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. c. 12. And can we believe, that the Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, which was indeed a Figure of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould be expreſt, and underſtood, in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable literal Senſe; and that the Sacrament, which was the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the Figure, ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in ſuch a prodigious wonderful Figure (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Diſcourſer's acceptation) as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve the greateſt part of the Chriſtian World, not only in moſt pernicious Miſtakes, but alſo in the moſt deteſtable Sin of Idolatry? Sure, the imagination of it muſt be totally inconſiſtent with the Veracity, Mercy, Goodneſs, and the main deſign of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour. To inſtitute a Figure literally, and the Subſtance figuratively, is a ſtrange Method, and not eaſily ſuppos'd in the God of Truth; and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Nay, more, our Saviour, who eſtabliſht a Law, and a Church to interpret it, who ſuffer'd the Indignities of humane Life, and Death of the Croſs on purpoſe to ſave Sinners: He, to whom the paſt, and future was always preſent, and who knew what would happen to his Spouſe the Church, after his Death, had left ſo great a ſtumbling block to the World (had he intended only a figurative Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that his Cruelty (which is moſt impious to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) would have exceeded his Mercy; eſpecially if
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62979:29"/>it be true (as I believe it is, and hope ſhall be able to prove) that the whole Chriſtian World for a thouſand years together after his Aſcenſion, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally concurr'd in the firm Belief of a literal Senſe, and practis'd accordingly. Good God! So many reputed Saints, ſo many Martyrs, and ſo many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men dying in the guilt, and many of them in defence of groſs Idolatry? This to me (to uſe the expreſſion of our Diſcourſer) is more than ten Thouſand Demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>He tells us indeed, that ſome Learned Catholic Authors have declar'd their Opinions, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which holds the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine to remain after Conſecration, is neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Reaſon nor Scripture. <hi>p.</hi> 5. And what then? They do not exclude the Doctrine of the Real preſence in a literal ſenſe, nor do I know that they did ever doubt of Tranſubſtantiation: But moſt of them have written particularly in defence of it; and <hi>Durandus</hi> wrote a Book conſiſting of nine parts againſt <hi>Berengarius,</hi> who oppos'd it. Now, tho this might be the private Opinion of theſe Men, yet there are (it may be) thouſands as Learned as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, of another Opinion; and all this without either prejudicing, or helping the Doctrine it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Our Diſcourſer cannot think any Man ſo ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to believe, that our Saviour did literally <hi>hold himſelf in his hands, and gave away himſelf from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with his own hands;</hi> and yet we find a very ſenſible Father, and one much eſteemed by all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (I mean <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi>) made no ſuch difficulty to believe all this: For in his Comment upon theſe words, <hi>Et ferebatur in manibus ſuis;</hi> and he was
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62979:29"/>carried in his own hands, he ſpeaks thus of Chriſt. <hi>And can this be</hi> poſſible <hi>in Man? Was ever any Man carried in his own hands,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>How this can be literally underſtood of</hi> David <hi>we cannot diſcover;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comm. in Pſ.</hi> 33.</note> 
               <hi>but in Chriſt we found it verified, for Chriſt was carried in his own hands, when giving his own</hi> very Body <hi>he ſaid, This is my Body.</hi> But if Chriſt carried only the <hi>Figure</hi> of his Body, it was not only <hi>poſſible</hi> for <hi>David,</hi> but for any Man elſe to have done the ſame. Methinks our Diſcourſer ſhould have replied to this obvious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, when he made his Objection: And thus much for the Authority of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Next he tells us, that this Doctrine is <hi>not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the perpetual Belief of the Chriſtian Church;</hi> and for this, he produces many Authorities of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> which may be reduc't to theſe Heads; either where they tell us, <hi>That the Elements are a Sign and Figure of Chriſts Body;</hi> or that they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their former Subſtance;</hi> or that they <hi>go into the Draught,</hi> and our <hi>fleſh encreaſed by them;</hi> or that they are not to be taken <hi>according to the Letter;</hi> for all which he brings ſome Citations. Now altho' the <hi>Fathers</hi> have been their own beſt Interpreters, ſhewing plainly in other places, how theſe are to be underſtood, agreeable to the Catholic Doctrine; yet, that it may appear more Evident, I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome other plain expreſſions, and leave the Ballance to the Judgment of the Reader.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, whereſoever it is ſaid, that the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are <hi>Signs</hi> or <hi>Figures,</hi> there no more is ſaid than what the Catholics believe and profeſs; nay, more, that it is a part of the Definition of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be a <hi>Sign,</hi> That is to ſay, that the <hi>unbloody</hi> Sacrifice of Chriſts Body in the Sacrament, offer'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62979:30"/>in a ſpiritual manner, is a <hi>Figure,</hi> or <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>bloody</hi> Sacrifice, offer'd once for all upon the Croſs, after a natural manner; anſwerable to the words of <hi>S.</hi> Paul, 1 Cor. 11. <hi>Ye ſhall ſhew the Lords death until he come.</hi> About the words we agree; concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the interpretation our Diſcourſer may diſpute as long as he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>Next, That the Elements remain in their <hi>form</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance:</hi> This paſſage of <hi>Theodoret</hi> hath been in part anſwer'd before, where he tells us, <hi>That they are to be</hi> ador'd—And from thence we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that he means the nature of the Accidents; for thoſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which this Greek Father uſeth, contain every kind of Eſſence and Nature, as well of <hi>Accidents,</hi> as of <hi>Subſtances:</hi> And ſo again he expounds himſelf, ſaying, that we may ſee and touch (the ſaid Colour and Form) which have reference on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe Accidents; and in this ſenſe, the Elements may admit of <hi>Co-adoration</hi> with the Body of our Saviour; as when himſelf was Cloth'd upon Earth; otherwiſe not. And <hi>Theodoret</hi> is blam'd by the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiſts, <hi>Cent.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10. Becauſe he affirms, <hi>That the Symbols of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, after the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of the Prieſt, are chang'd, and made other things than they were before:</hi> They mean not Signs I hope, for more than that they believed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But let us hear St. Auguſtin, <hi>As with a faithful heart and</hi> Mouth <hi>we receive the Mediator of God and Man, Chriſt Jeſus, who gives us his Fleſh to be eaten, and his Blood to be drunk, altho' it ſeems to be a thing more full of horror to eat Mans fleſh, than to kill it, and to drink Mans blood, than to ſhed it. L.</hi> 2, <hi>Contr. adv. Leg. &amp; Proph.</hi> But ſure it is not more horrible
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62979:30"/>to eat Mans fleſh in <hi>figure,</hi> than to kill a man in good earneſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let us hear him again, <hi>We have heard</hi> (ſays he) <hi>our Maſter, who always ſpeaks truth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending to us</hi> our Ranſom, <hi>his Blood; for he ſpoke of his Body and Blood; which Body he call'd Meat, and his Blood Drink. But there are ſome who do not believe;</hi> they ſaid. <hi>This is a hard ſaying, who can hear it? 'Tis hard, but to the obſtinate, that is, incredible, but to the Incredulous. L. de verb. Apoſt. Serm.</hi> 2. But is the Figure ſo hard a ſaying? I think not.</p>
            <p>Next St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> a co-temporary, and particular Friend of St. Auguſtin, <hi>It may be you will ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De his qui Myſt. Init. c.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>why do you tell me that I receive the Body of Chriſt, when as I ſee quite another thing? We have this therefore yet to prove: How many Examples therefore do we produce to ſhew, that it is not what Nature fram'd, but what the Benediction hath Conſecrated, and that the force of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction is greater than of Nature, becauſe by Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Nature her ſelf is chang'd.</hi> Moſes <hi>held a Rod in his hand, he caſt it from him, and it became a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> Where he tells of all thoſe real Tranſmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Miracles made by <hi>Moſes.</hi> After which he goes on, <hi>We ſee therefore that the power of Grace is far beyond that of Nature, and yet we have only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd hitherto the effects of Grace in the bleſſing of Prophets; now if the bleſſing of men were of ſo great efficacy, as to change the Nature of things, what ſhall we ſay of the Divine Conſecration, where the very words of Chriſt our Saviour are operative?</hi> Then he ſpeaks of the Creation of the World out of nothing, and goes on, <hi>If therefore Chriſt by his word, was able to make ſomething of nothing, ſhall he not be thought able to change thoſe things which are, into other things
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62979:31"/>which they were not? But what need of Arguments? Let us propoſe his own Example, and aſſert the truth of this Myſtery, by that of his Incarnation. When our Lord Jeſus was born of</hi> Mary, <hi>was it a Natural genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This Body which we make in the Sacrament, is that which was born of the Virgin. Why do ye here require the order of Nature in the Body of Chriſt; when as above all Nature Chriſt was born of a Virgin? The true Fleſh of Chriſt, which was crucified, which was buried.</hi> And are all theſe real Tranſmutations, and Miraculous, Supernatural Examples produc't, only to prove a figurative Change, conferring ſome inviſible Bleſſing? Can our Diſcourſer under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it ſo, and no otherwiſe? Indeed I think he had beſt retreat to the firſt three Hundred years after Chriſt (as ſome others of your late Writers have done) contrary to what I had ever been taught among you; who generally extended the Purity of the Roman Doctrine as far as the firſt Five Hundred years, and accordingly, in my Diſcourſes with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics, I always aſſerted, that we did receive the Roman Doctrine, until about that time: but the Truth would glare too much in our Diſcourſers Eyes, if he ſhould walk in the light of thoſe two latter Centuries, when the Church began to be freed from her Perſecutions, and holy <hi>Fathers</hi> had greater liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Preaching, and Teaching the true Chriſtian Faith, in its Extent. But we ſhall follow him as high as he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>We produce next St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who liv'd in the Age before St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> his words are theſe: <hi>Do not then conſider it as bare Bread, or bare Wine, for it is the Body and Blood of Chriſt, according to the word of our Saviour himſelf: For tho'
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62979:31"/>ſenſe ſhould ſuggeſt this to thee, yet let thy Faith ſo confirm this, as that thou judge not the matter from the Taſt:</hi> And again, <hi>Hoe Sciens,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This knowing, and accounting it as moſt certain, that this Bread which we ſee is not Bread, tho' our Taſt do tell us that it is Bread; but it is the Body of Chriſt; and the Wine which we behold, tho' it ſeem Wine to our ſenſe of Taſt, yet it is not Wine, but the Blood of Chriſt: Catech.</hi> 4. This was ſpoke after a Catechiſtical man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in which, high Metaphors and Figures are not generally very frequent; he was beſides, eſteem'd by all as a learned Perſon, and of this Book, none e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doubted.</p>
            <p>We come now to the third Age, in which S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> treating of our Lords Supper, ſays, <hi>The Bread which our Lord gave to his Diſciples, is changed, not in outward appearance, but in Subſtance, and by the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of the Word, It is made Fleſh. And as in the perſon of Chriſt the Humanity did appear, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity lay hid; ſo in the viſible Sacrament, the Divine Eſſence hath ineffably infuſed it ſelf. Serm. de coena Dom.</hi> This is ſo clear a paſſage, that ſome of the <hi>Sacramentaries,</hi> for want of a better Anſwer, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it was not writ by St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> altho' at the ſame time they are forc't to confeſs that it is of great Antiquity, and had a Learned Author: But ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be ſaid, and Confidence goes a great way.</p>
            <p>I have already ſpoken of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Age; and come now to the firſt Age, even in the days of the Apoſtles; let us hear then the holy Martyr <hi>S.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Smyrnaeos.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>S. John,</hi> who ſpeaking of the Heretics of his time, ſays thus, <hi>They do not allow of Euchariſts and Oblations, becauſe they do not believe the Euchariſt to be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62979:32"/>the Fleſh of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which ſuffer'd for our Sins, and which the Father in his Mercy raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the dead.</hi> A ſtrange concurrence through all Ages of moſt extraordinary Tropes and Figures. I name not <hi>St. Andrew,</hi> becauſe the Authority is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected: Nor is it neceſſary to multiply Teſtimonies of the <hi>Fathers</hi> (which we might have done) becauſe they are in truth but like dead Weights on both ſides, until we ſhall have put life into them by ſuch reaſonable Interpretations, as (reconciling them firſt to themſelves) may make them plainly ſpeak forth the Catholic Doctrine, which I refer to the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>But what do Proteſtants think of all theſe <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</hi> Why truly they blame them All, and tell us, that they were miſtaken. Dr. <hi>Humphrey</hi> ſays, <hi>Gregory and Auſtin brought Tranſubſtantiation into the Engliſh Church,</hi> (Jeſuit. part 2. p. 627) The Centuriſts charge <hi>S. Chryſoſtome, S. Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius, For not wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting well of Tranſubſtantiation</hi> Peter Martyr, for the ſame reaſon blames <hi>S. Cyril, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, S. Cyprian.</hi> The Learned <hi>Melancton</hi> writes thus upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (<hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep. Zuing, &amp; Oecol. f.</hi> 132.) <hi>There is no care (ſays he) that hath more troubled my mind, than this of the Euchariſt: And not only my ſelf have weighed what might be ſaid on either ſide; but I have alſo ſought out the Judgment of old Writers touching the ſame: And when I have laid all together, I find no good reaſon, that may ſatisfie a Conſcience, departing from the</hi> propriety <hi>of Chriſts words, This is my Body.</hi> Many other Teſtimonies of Learned Proteſtants, I omit at preſent for Brevity ſake. In the mean time, I ſuppoſe all theſe may be ſufficient to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> even when you have
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62979:32"/>made the moſt of it, that in reaſon you ought; or elſe my Reaſon and Senſe are much more deceived in this Caſe, than in that of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>But come we to the <hi>Third</hi> Point, <hi>That the Elements go into the draught, and our fleſh encreaſed by them.</hi> Hear what St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſays, <hi>Do you ſee Bread? Do you ſee Wine? Do theſe go into the draught like other common meat? Far be it from thee to imagine it.</hi> Hom. do Euchar. in Encoen. When our Diſcourſer hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd his paſſage of <hi>Origen,</hi> with this of <hi>S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome;</hi> let him then read any Catholic Author, and he will tell him how he ſhall underſtand the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which he hath here produc't; of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>encreaſe of the fleſh,</hi> I find this Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in St. <hi>Greg. Nyſſen. Orat. Catech. c.</hi> 36. and 37. <hi>Even as a little Leaven doth make the whole Maſs like it ſelf; ſo that Body which is made Immortal by God, entring into our Body, doth transfer, and change it into its ſelf.</hi> And after, <hi>That Body is joyned with the Bodies of the faithful, that by the Coujunction with the ſame Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Body, Man may be made partaker of Immortality.</hi> So <hi>S. Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, As a ſpark of fire light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Hay or Straw, doth preſently inflame it all; ſo the Word of God joyned to our corruptible Nature by means of the Euchariſt, doth make it all to riſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and glorious.</hi> The ſame may be ſeen in <hi>Iraen. l.</hi> 8. <hi>contr. Haer c.</hi> 34. And many others, who underſtand the encreaſe of the Fleſh, to be a raiſing of the Fleſh towards a ſtate of Immortality, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it towards a happy Reſurrection; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of <hi>S. John</hi> c. 6. <hi>He that eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, hath life Everlaſting, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> But if theſe Interepreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62979:33"/>ſhould not happen to pleaſe you, I ſhall then recommend you to a late Catholic Author, and leave you to himſelf, or his Excellent Treatiſe, <hi>The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence for the Adoration of the Body and Blood of our Lord,</hi> p. 14. For further ſatisfaction, his words are theſe, 'This External Sign, or Symbol, they (the Catholics) affirm to be <hi>all That</hi> of the Bread and Wine that is perceived by any Senſe. And tho' after Conſecration, the Subſtance of the Bread and Wine is denied to remain, yet is Subſtance here taken in ſuch a ſenſe, as that neither the hardneſs, nor ſoftneſs, nor the frangibility, nor the ſavour, nor the odour, nor the <hi>nutritive vertue of the Bread,</hi> nor nothing viſible, nor tangible, or otherwiſe percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by any ſenſe, are involved in it. All which at laſt we ſhall endeavour to explain.</p>
            <p>The laſt Head is, <hi>That the words of Conſecration are not to be taken in a literal Senſe:</hi> To prove this our Diſcourſer brings ſeveral <hi>killing</hi> Teſtimonies, as he calls them; but I know not whom they hurt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Caphernaites;</hi> for all Catholics own both the Authorities, and the Doctrine contained in them, as abſolutely neceſſary to the true and Orthodox un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding their Doctrine of the Holy Sacrament. That is to ſay, That the Body of Chriſt in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, is not there after a Natural and Corporeal manner, as it was upon the Croſs, that is, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fically, and according to the outward Form, and local Exiſtence; but ſpiritually, ſupernaturally, and without Circumſcription, that is, external Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſuration of, or Co-extenſion with Place. And if <hi>Paſcaſius</hi> meant otherwiſe of the Sacrament, than what is here expreſt, then <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> did well to <hi>oppoſe him with all his might,</hi> as another <hi>Anonymus</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62979:33"/>did (if not the ſame <hi>Rabanus</hi>) in a Tract extant in <hi>Codice Gemblacenſ. Coſnobij cum Heregeri Opuſculo.</hi> But that this good Arch-Biſhop did ſo underſtand him, is plain for theſe two Reaſons. <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe he hath always been acknowledged an Orthodox Biſhop among all Catholics; and next, becauſe his own words have, with good reaſon, confirm'd Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics in this their Opinion of him; and they are theſe,
<q>Who, ſays he, would ever believe that Bread could be turn'd into Fleſh, or Wine into Blood, except our Saviour himſelf had ſaid it, who Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bread and Wine, and made all things out of Nothing, but it is eaſier to make one thing out of another, than all things out of Nothing.</q> 
               <hi>L.</hi> 7. <hi>de Sacris ordin. ad Theatmanum c.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Now after all theſe Authorities from the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and a Hundred more which might be produc't, to ſhew that they believ'd the Real Preſence, together with the agreable concurrent ſenſe of them all, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through their whole Works, beſides their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of Adoration, and Belief of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloody Sacrifice; and many Learned Proteſtants confeſſing, that they did ſo believe: After all this, I ſuppoſe I need not enquire of our Diſcourſer, when this Doctrine of the Real Preſence came into the World, for I am convinc't that it was in the very days of the Apoſtles themſelves; or, to uſe the words of <hi>Sebaſtianus Francus,</hi> and <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> (two E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Proteſtants) <hi>jam tum primo illo tempore, &amp; viventibus adhuc Apoſtolis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But becauſe our Diſcourſer hath made uſe of the name of the good Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and ſupport his falſe Chronology, it is Juſt that I take off this ſcandalous imputation from <hi>Rabanus
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62979:34"/>Maurus.</hi> Now, altho his own words before recited, are more than ſufficient to clear this Excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; yet at preſent I ſhall only make uſe of our Diſcourſer's own computation to deſtroy the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of his unreaſonable Suppoſition, which he calls a <hi>plain Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 21.</note> That in the Second Council of <hi>Nice, Anno Dom.</hi> 787. <hi>The Sacrament was declar'd to be properly the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and that thence this Opinion got footing among the Greeks:</hi> And that in the year 818. <hi>Paſcaſius firſt broacht this Doctrine in the Latin Church,</hi> inſinuating, that until that time, this Doctrine was not receiv'd among the Latins; and, that thereupon, <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> in the year 847 wrote againſt this <hi>Paſcaſius</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing this new Error. Thus far the Story is very well laid; but here are theſe hard difficulties to be digeſted before we can give it that credit which he expects: Firſt, it is certain, that <hi>Peter Arch-Presbyter of the Roman Church,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Monk,</hi> were preſent in the ſaid Council in behalf of Pope <hi>Adrian.</hi> That the ſaid Pope wrote Letters to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and alſo to <hi>Taraſius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which were received by the ſaid Council: And laſtly, that the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy was confirmed in this very Council in theſe words, <hi>Quod Eccleſia Romana ſit Caput omnium Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiarum,</hi> Act 2.</p>
            <p>Now from this Council to <hi>Rabanus Maurus,</hi> there was an Interval of 60 years; from the Council to <hi>Paſcaſius,</hi> of one and Thirty years; and can we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that this Doctrine of the Real Preſence, which was declared in this Council, in the preſence of the Popes Legats, and confirm'd by the Pope
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62979:34"/>himſelf, ſhould be one and Thirty years a getting over from <hi>Nice</hi> into the <hi>Latin</hi> Church? Or that ſo Learned a Man as <hi>Rabanus</hi> (and ſo eſteem'd by our Diſcourſer) ſhould be ignorant ſixty years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Council was held, That this Doctrine had been there declared? And ſo groſly miſtake <hi>Paſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> for the firſt broacher of it? Truly for my part, altho' <hi>Rabanus</hi> had not explain'd himſelf concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Faith, according to thoſe expreſſions before related, yet would I not eaſily have believ'd that he could have been ſo ignorant of the Tranſaction of this Council, or would have accus'd <hi>Paſcaſius</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing ſo groſs an Error into the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, when he knew that he writ no otherwiſe, than as had been Thirty years before, determin'd in a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council: It is plain therefore that <hi>Rabanus</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell'd with ſome Expreſſions of <hi>Paſcaſius,</hi> as import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Erroneous ſenſe before mention'd.</p>
            <p>Our Diſcourſer, being confident that he hath found out the date of Tranſubſtantiation, falls a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle foul upon Mr. <hi>Arnauld,</hi> becauſe he cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſuch a Doctrine ſhould have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon the Chriſtian World, and yet ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally receiv'd, except there had been ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, if not an univerſal Oppoſition; and indeed our Diſcourſer (of all mankind) ought to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd ſo too; for if every man ſhould have had as ill an Opinion of it, as himſelf, its eſtabliſhment had been impoſſible. But that he might find a fit parallel for Mr. <hi>Arnauld,</hi> he takes a long Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Vienna,</hi> the rather (I ſuppoſe) that he might pay his reſpects to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and his Army as he return'd home again; for he tells us, <hi>That by the like Demonſtration (as Mr.</hi> Arnauld's) <hi>one
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62979:35"/>might prove that the Turk did not invade Chriſtendom, becauſe if he had, the moſt Chriſtian King, who had the greateſt Army in Chriſtendom, in a readineſs, would certainly have employed it againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now our Diſcourſer, without croſſing the Seas, might have given as proper an inſtance, even from his own Doors; for who could eaſily imagine that the Real, Subſtantial Preſence of Chriſts Natural Body in the holy Sacrament, ſhould have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd and profeſt by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the days of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; and yet, that in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Second, the figurative Doctrine, in excluſion of the Real Preſence, ſhould be ſo firmly, and peaceably eſtabliſht among us, as that not ſo much as one ſingle Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Man (at leaſt that I have heard of) tho highly dignified by honourable and profitable Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in, and by the ſaid Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould write one word in Vindication of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church: Nor one ſmall Pamphlet, to oppoſe the Innovation of theſe uſurping Sacramentories? But theſe things, worthy <hi>Fathers,</hi> concern you more than me; and leſt you ſhould quite forget that there ever had been any ſuch Doctrine profeſt by your Church of <hi>England,</hi> I ſhall humbly take the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, by and by, to refreſh your memories.</p>
            <p>Much more might be ſaid, to ſhew, from what looſe Conjectures, our Diſcourſer would prove the Innovation of the Doctrine of the Real Preſence; and that it entred not into the <hi>Latin</hi> Church before the Eighth Century. But ſince I deſign nothing of Anſwer, more than to ſatisfie you (worthy <hi>Fathers</hi>) and my ſelf, that I have not ruſhly rejected the Authority of ſo Learned a Perſon, as our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62979:35"/>ſeems to be, without good reaſon and due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, this which is already ſaid, is (I ſuppoſe) ſufficient for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I come now to (what he calls) the Third pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ground of this Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, that is, <hi>The infallible Authority of the preſent Church to make, and declare new Articles of Faith.</hi> Firſt, there is a great difference between <hi>making</hi> an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith, and <hi>declaring</hi> and Article of Faith. I know no power upon Earth that can do the firſt; but certainly the ſecond is within the Juriſdiction of the lawful Church Governours, or otherwiſe, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils would be very inſignificant Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. Now if Tranſubſtantiation ſhould prove to be no more than the true Faith concerning the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, declar'd, or explain'd; then our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer hath no reaſon to quarrel with Church Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or fear any Inconveniences ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen from the Exerciſe of ſuch a Power.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I have ſufficiently ſhewn (at leaſt in my Opinion) that the Doctrine of the Real Preſence, that is, of the Natural Body of Chriſt ſubſtantially, truly, and literally exiſting in the Sacrament (tho' not after a Corporal, and Natural manner,) to have been the conſtant Doctrine of the Catholic Church, from the Apoſtles to the great Council of <hi>Lateran;</hi> when, in the preſence of the Ambaſſadors of the <hi>Greek,</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours; as alſo of the Kings of <hi>Jeruſalem, England, France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> this word Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation was agreed upon by neer Thirteen Hundred <hi>Fathers,</hi> to be a proper Explicative Term of the Apoſtolical Doctrine; and belief of the Real Preſence, or change of the Bread and Wine, into the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt; of this enough
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62979:36"/>hath been ſaid. But becauſe our Diſcourſer is pleas'd to call the Doctrine of the Real Preſence <hi>barbarous,</hi> and <hi>impious,</hi> p. 35. I have thought fit to add to the reſt, the Teſtimonies of Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> and the Learned <hi>Caſaubon</hi> in the name of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the moſt Learned <hi>Fathers</hi> and Profeſſors of the true Engliſh Church.</p>
            <p>I will begin with Biſhop <hi>Andrews, Reſp. ad Apol. Bell. c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 11.
<q>The Cardinal (ſays he) cannot be ignorant, except wilfully, that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> but not <hi>after this manner,</hi> This is my Body. We agree in the object, and differ only in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Concerning the <hi>Hoc eſt,</hi> or this is. We firmly believe that <hi>it is:</hi> Concerning the <hi>after this manner</hi> (i.e. by the Bread Tranſubſtantiated into the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) of the <hi>manner</hi> how it is done, as <hi>by,</hi> or <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>with,</hi> or <hi>under,</hi> or <hi>through,</hi> there is not a word concerning it. We believe the true Preſence, no leſs than your ſelves, but we dare not confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly define any thing concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of this Preſence, nor are we over curious to enquire into it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Again <hi>ib. c.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 194. Speaking of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of Chriſts Body with the Symbols, he ſays,
<q>There is that Conjunction between the viſible Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and the Inviſible Thing of the Sacrament, as between the Divinity and Humanity of Chriſt; where, except you would ſavour of Eutychianiſm, the Humanity is not tranſubſtantiated into the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity:</q> And a little further,
<q>The King hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht it, that Chriſt is truly preſent in the Euchariſt, and to be truly there ador'd: And, we, with <hi>Ambroſe</hi> adore the Fleſh of Chriſt in the Myſteries.</q> Some poſſibly may be ingenious enough to interpret all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62979:36"/>this to ſignifie a meer figurative Preſence, as they have done many clear paſſages of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> but they muſt interpret for themſelves, not for me.</p>
            <p>But let us hear what <hi>Iſ. Caſaubon</hi> writes to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Perron</hi> by the Kings Command, concerning the Real Preſence of Chriſts Body in the Euchariſt, who ſaying, that the Conteſt was not about the <hi>Truth</hi> but only the <hi>Manner</hi> of the thing, returns this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, p. 50.
<q>His Majeſty wonders, ſince your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence confeſſeth that you do not ſo ſolicitouſly require, that Tranſubſtantiation ſhould be believed, as that we ſhould not doubt concerning the Truth of the Real Preſence: That the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould not long ſince have ſatisfied you in that particular, which hath ſo often profeſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, in her public Writings.</q> And then for Explication of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> recites the fore-mention'd words of Biſhop <hi>Andrews, Quod Cardinalem non latet.</hi> Come we next to Mr. <hi>Hooker. Eccl. Polit. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 67. p. 357.
<q>Wherefore ſhould the World continue ſtill diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and rent with ſo manifold contentions, when there remaineth now no Controverſie, ſaving only about the ſubject where Chriſt is? Nor doth any thing reſt doubtful in this; but whether, when the Sacrament is adminiſtred, Chriſt be whole within Man only, or elſe his Body and Blood be alſo externally ſeated in the very Conſecrated Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves.</q> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 360.
<q>All three Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions do thus far accordin one: That theſe holy Myſteries received in due manner, do inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally both make us partakers of the Grace of that Body and Blood, which were given for the Life of the World; and beſides alſo impart unto us, even
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62979:37"/>in a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>real,</hi> tho' Myſtical Manner, the very Perſon of our Lord himſelf, whole, perfect and entire.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Next we offer the Teſtimony of Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> quoted by Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> ſet down in <hi>Fox, p.</hi> 1598.
<q>You (ſays he, the Tranſubſtantialiſts) and I agree in this, That in the Sacrament is the very <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, even that which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Heaven, which ſits on the right hand of God the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> only we differ in <hi>Modo,</hi> in the way and manner of being there—</q>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> who hath written one of the laſt on this Subject, is very clear and particular concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Real Preſence, <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. <hi>N.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 18.
<q>It is enquired (ſays he) whether, when we ſay we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Chriſts Body to be really in the Sacrament, we mean, that Body, that Fleſh, that was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that was Crucified, Dead, and Buried? I anſwer, I know none elſe that he had, or hath; there is but one Body of Chriſt, Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Glorified: But he that faith that Body is Glorified which was Crucified, ſays it is the ſame Body, but not after the ſame manner; and ſo it is in the Sacrament, we eat and drink the Body and Blood of Chriſt that was broken and poured forth, for there is no other Body, no other Blood of Chriſt: But tho' it is the ſame we eat, and drink, yet it is in another manner. And therefore when any of the Proteſtant Divines, or any of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> deny, that Body which was born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> that was Crucified, to be eaten in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; As <hi>Bertram,</hi> as <hi>St. Heirom,</hi> as <hi>Clemens Alexand.</hi> expreſly affirm; The meaning is eaſie,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62979:37"/>They intend that it is not eaten in a natural ſenſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That Body which was Crucified, is not that Body that is eaten in the Sacrament, is true, if the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Propoſition be to ſpeak of the eating it, in the ſame manner of being: But that Body which was Crucified, the ſame Body we do eat (is alſo true) if the intention be to ſpeak of the ſame thing, in ſeveral Manners of being, and Operating.</q> Some alſo, may turn all this into a meer figurative ſenſe, excluding the <hi>Corpus Domini,</hi> or Real Preſence of Chriſts Natural Body in the Sacrament; and it may be they may think that this Doctor himſelf (from ſome other of his expreſſions) may have given them juſt reaſon ſo to do. I ſhall then only obſerve theſe two things; Firſt, that concerning this Real Preſence, a Catholic could not have written more juſtly, nor more plainly than the Doctor hath done in what hath been above recited: And Secondly, That if after all this, the Doctor ſhould mean no more than a Spiritual efficacy or virtue, excluding the <hi>Corpus Domini,</hi> or Subſtantial Preſence of Chriſts Natural Body, (tho' indeed after a Spiritual manner, as we confeſs;) then doth the Doctors Opinion ſeem as contradictory to it ſelf, and as incomprehenſible to me, as the great Myſtery of Tranſubſtantiation it ſelf, or as if he had written in Characters totally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible.</p>
            <p>But let us now hear Biſhop <hi>Forbes de Euchariſt. L.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.
<q>The ſober Proteſtants doubt not but that Chriſt is to be ador'd in the Sacrament; for in the taking of the Euchariſt, Chriſt is to be ador'd with Divine Worſhip, becauſe his Living and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body is preſent, by an unexpreſſible Miracle, to the Worthy Receiver; and this Adoration, is not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62979:38"/>due or performed, to the Bread, or Wine, or the taking, or eating; but to the very Body of Chriſt immediately exhibited to us in the taking of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. And again. <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Fathers</hi> often tell us,</q>
               <q>That the very Body of Chriſt is Offer'd, and <hi>Sacrificed</hi> in the Euchariſt, as appears by almoſt innumerable paſſages; but not that all the properties of a Sacrifice are properly, and really obſerv'd; but it is done by a Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and Repreſentation of that, which being once offer'd in that only Sacrifice of the Croſs, Chriſt our High Prieſt, did thereby conſummate all other Sacrifices; and by pious Supplications, by which the Miniſters of the Church (for the ſake of the perpetual Oblation of that one Sacrifice, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in Heaven at the right hand of the Father, and <hi>preſent after an unexpreſſible manner on the holy Table</hi>) moſt humbly pray God the Father, that he would pleaſe to grant, that the Vertue and Grace of this perpetual Victim may become profitable and efficacious to his Church, for helping all the neceſſities, both of the body and Soul.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> ſays much the ſame thing in his <hi>Rep. Eccleſ. L.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 11. Only he will not admit the Body of Chriſt to be corporally <hi>in</hi> the Bread, or <hi>under</hi> the Bread; but to be taken <hi>with</hi> the Bread; <hi>Sumitur</hi> cum <hi>Pane, Chriſti Corpus reale, illi communioni realiter praeſens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Thorndyke</hi> in his Epilogue to the Tragedy, <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. Says thus,
<q>That which I have already ſaid, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Evidence the Myſtical, and Spiritual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Fleſh, and Blood of Chriſt in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the Sacrament of the Same, before any Man can ſuppoſe that Spiritual Preſence of them to his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62979:38"/>Soul, which the eating and drinking Chriſts Fleſh and Blood ſpiritually by living Faith importeth.</q> And <hi>ibid. c.</hi> 2. where it follows, <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lords Body;</hi>
               <q>Unleſs a man diſcern the Lords Body where it is not, of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it muſt there be, where it is diſcerned to be.</q> And <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.
<q>Having maintained that the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are really changed, from ordinary Bread and Wine, into the Body and Blood of Chriſt myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally preſent as in a Sacrament, and that in vertue of the <hi>Conſecration, not by the Faith</hi> of him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives; I am to admit and maintain whatſoever appears duly conſequent to this Truth; namely, that the Elements ſo conſecrated, are truly the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, in as much as the Body and Blood of Chriſt are contained in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And then, <hi>p.</hi> 46. he further collecteth thus:
<q>And the Sacrifice of the Croſs being neceſſarily propitiatory, and impetratory both, it cannot be denied that the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, in as much as it is the ſame Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, is alſo both propitiatory and impetratory.</q> You may conſult Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Montague,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and many other Learned Proteſtants, too long to be here recited for further ſatisfaction in this Matter.</p>
            <p>Now, worthy Fathers, what would you adviſe me to do in this Caſe? would you have me follow the Judgments of theſe Learned and Pious Men, who wrote, not only their private Opinions, but, ſome of them, in the Name of the King, and whole Church of <hi>England?</hi> Or would you have me believe our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer, and ſome others of our late Sacramentary
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62979:39"/>Pamphleters? If the firſt, then Tranſubſtantiation will not appear ſo <hi>abſurd, ridiculous, ſenſeleſs</hi> and <hi>fooliſh</hi> a Doctrine as he hath ſtyled it, which I hope to prove hereafter. If the ſecond, then to uſe the Argument and Words of our Diſcourſer, <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>Chriſtanity would become a moſt uncertain and endleſs thing;</hi> for if we may thus change our Faith in ſuch high and fundamental Doctrines as theſe are, I know not what ſecurity we have that we ſhall not in time change our Faith in other neceſſaries, and at length loſe it all.</p>
            <p>But to pin up the Basket (as we ſay) I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Teſtimonies of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> men to whom the Church of <hi>England</hi> is obliged for a great part of her Reformation. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>(Take, eat, this is my Body)</hi> ſays thus, <hi>Nor doth Chriſt only offer to us the benefits of his Death and Reſurrection, but</hi> that Body it ſelf <hi>in which he ſuffered and roſe again.</hi> And again, <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Being made partakers of his</hi> Subſtance, <hi>we perceive alſo the vertue of it in the Communication of all good things.</hi> I know no other <hi>Subſtance</hi> he had ſpiritual or corporal, but that which was born of the Bleſſed Virgin. And of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> he ſays: <hi>If they ſo explain their meaning, that whilſt the Bread is delivered there is annext to it the exhibition of his Body, becauſe the Truth is inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from its Sign, I ſhould not much oppoſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſtrengthen this Aſſertion of <hi>Calvin,</hi> I ſhall add the Confeſſion of <hi>Beza,</hi> and others of the ſame Sect, related by <hi>Hoſpinian Hiſt. Sacram. parte altera, p.</hi> 251. <hi>We confeſs that in the Cup of our Lord, not only all the Benefits of Chriſt, but the</hi> very ſubſtance <hi>of the Son of man; I ſay, that</hi> very Fleſh, <hi>and</hi> that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Blood <hi>which he poured out for us, not only</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catively,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62979:39"/>ſymbolically, typically, <hi>or</hi> figuratively, <hi>as a</hi> remembrance <hi>of one abſent; but</hi> truly <hi>and</hi> certainly <hi>repreſented,</hi> exhibited, <hi>and</hi> offer'd, <hi>not as naked Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols, but as having (from God himſelf promiſing and offering) the very</hi> thing it ſelf, truly <hi>and</hi> certainly joyned to them. <hi>Now the manner by which the thing it ſelf,</hi> (i.e. <hi>the very Body, and the very Blood of our Lord) is joyned with the Symbols, we ſay it is Symbolical, or Sacramental; But we call it a Sacramental manner, not that it is only</hi> Figurative, <hi>but that it</hi> truly <hi>and</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>repreſents under the Species of viſible Things, that which God exhibits, and offers with the Symbols, that is (as I ſaid before) the</hi> very Body and Blood <hi>of Chriſt.</hi> And then he tells us, That he differs with others concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of the Preſence only, but for the very <hi>Thing</hi> and <hi>Preſence</hi> it ſelf he retains and defends it.</p>
            <p>And now, Reverend Fathers, I muſt acquaint you, that whilſt I was tranſcribing this very laſt Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, I was inform'd, that there was an Anſwer, lately publiſht, to <hi>Two Diſcourſes printed at</hi> Oxford, which contained in them the Teſtimonies of theſe Learned Proteſtants before mentioned. I ſtopt my Pen, bought the Book, and read it over with great care. I ſhall not at preſent ſpeak any thing more of it in particular, than what relates to this very Subject; but in general give me leave to tell you, that me thoughts this Anſwerer might very well have ſpar'd his Apology at laſt, <hi>p.</hi> 125. for not having <hi>inſiſted more largely upon ſome points,</hi> ſince I have not ſeen Twenty two Sheets written with ſo much magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Confidence, and (in my judgment) with ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Subſtance, even among all the Pamphlets that have come out on both ſides, from the Death of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62979:40"/>late King to this preſent day; but I leave the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examination to the Concluſion of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we thank him for his plainneſs in delivering his opinion concerning the Real Preſence (which is the ſubject Matter in Debate) and by which he tells us, is meant no more than <hi>inviſible Power</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> in excluſion of the Real Preſence of Chriſts Natural Body, even after a ſpiritual manner: Whether the Church of <hi>England</hi> will thank him for it, I know not: I am ſure I was otherwiſe inſtructed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved otherwiſe, whilſt in your Communion.</p>
            <p>But let us hear what he ſays to theſe Teſtimonies. He endeavours to elude their moſt plain indubitable ſenſe, and grammatical conſtruction, (even according to the common Reaſon and Underſtanding of all Mankind) theſe ſeveral ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he tell us that <hi>Becanus</hi> ſays, the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> deny the <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt, to be truly, really and ſubſtantially preſent in the Euchariſt.</hi> Not (I hope) according to that ſenſe, which our Anſwerer would make <hi>Calvin,</hi> and others give of thoſe, and ſuch like expreſſions. But ſure our Anſwerer might have collected among his other Proteſtant Relics, an account of a rigider ſort of Calviniſts, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd even upon <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf, and yet retain'd the name of Calviniſts. But what doth <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf ſay (as this Anſwerer recites out of <hi>Hoſpinian</hi>) Why, <hi>that Chriſt is our Food, becauſe by the incomprehenſible Vertue of the holy Spirit he inſpires his Life into us, that he may communicate it to us,</hi> no leſs <hi>than the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Juice is diffuſed from the Root into all the Branches of the Tree,</hi> &amp;c. No leſs than ſo? then ſure it is as ſubſtantial a Communication of Chriſt's Natural
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62979:40"/>Body after a ſpiritual manner, as the <hi>Oxford</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer in that place pretends to; for if <hi>Calvin</hi> and this Anſwerer do not believe that the Vital Juice of a Tree is a Subſtance, (tho' whilſt a Juice, more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual) and that the very Subſtance of the Tree, is ſubſtantially nouriſhed and increaſed thereby; I fear they will both prove as bad Philoſophers as Divines.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed any further, I muſt inform, or mind our Anſwerer, that tho' Catholics believe Chriſt's Natural Body to be in the Sacrament, yet they deny it to be there bodily, <hi>i.e. Modo Corporeo;</hi> and tho' his Fleſh be there, yet not <hi>Fleſhly;</hi> nor yet doth his Natural Body leave the higheſt Heavens: Theſe premiſed (becauſe we ſhall have occaſion to make theſe diſtinctions) I come to next to <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His words (as recited by the Anſwerer) are theſe: <hi>We do not ſay, that in the Euchariſt there is</hi> only <hi>a</hi> Commemoration <hi>of the Death of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; nor do we ſay that in it we are made partakers</hi> only <hi>of the Fruits of his Death and Paſſion; but we joyn the</hi> Ground <hi>with the</hi> Fruits, <hi>affirming with St.</hi> Paul, <hi>that the Bread which by God's appointment we break, is the participation of the</hi> Body of Chriſt <hi>crucified for us; the Cup which we drink, the Communion of the</hi> true Blood <hi>that was ſhed for us; and that, in</hi> the very ſame Subſtance, which he received in the Womb of the Virgin, and which he carried up with him into the Heavens. And afterwards: <hi>For this honor we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to God, that tho' the Body of Jeſus Chriſt be now in Heaven, and not elſewhere, and we on Earth, and not elſewhere; yet are we made partakers of his Body and Blood, after a</hi> ſpiritual manner (i.e. modo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuali)
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62979:41"/>
               <hi>and by the means of Faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 50.</note> I am afraid (Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) this Anſwerer plays booty with you; for if this be a confutation of what was before alledged from <hi>Beza,</hi> I profeſs I ſhall never quarrel with him about it, nor deſire any other hand than <hi>Beza's</hi> (even in this very paſſage) to expreſs my Belief of the Real Preſence of Chriſt's Natural Body in the Sacrament. What a ſtrange Anſwerer is this? ſure he thinks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Catholics ſubmit their Senſe and Reaſon in ſome things to Divine Revelation, and the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church, therefore they have not Reaſon enough to judge in other Caſes, that three and one make four, as well as two and two.</p>
            <p>Next, he brings in <hi>Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> (when he was among his <hi>Geneva</hi> Brethren, I ſuppoſe) and he might as well have nam'd himſelf, and his Eminent Diſcourſer, againſt Tranſubſtantiation: And what if theſe two firſt were of the ſame opinion concerning the Real Preſence with theſe two laſt? It only proves, that one at <hi>London</hi> contradicted himſelf at <hi>Geneva;</hi> and the other, Men ten times more learned than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Our Anſwerer (that he may take breath) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he comes to our Engliſh Divines above-named (for I perceive he finds that he is like to have a tough piece of work on't) charges the <hi>Oxford</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor with diſingenuity, chiefly in favour of Doctor <hi>Burnets</hi> Hiſtory of the Reformation. Alas, I am apt to believe (tho' I know neither the Diſcourſer nor this Anſwerer, not ſo much as by Name, but only by their Works) I am apt (I ſay) to believe, that this Diſcourſer is much better acquainted with Church Hiſtory, than the Doctor, and applies it with much more Sincerity and Truth, than he hath done. I confeſs (were I worthy to adviſe) I ſhould counſel
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62979:41"/>this Anſwerer to fleſh himſelf firſt upon ſome Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of a lower Claſſis, for I doubt he is here over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match'd, and hath got (as we ſay) a Bear by the Tooth: What the Learned Hiſtorian means by the <hi>Wiſdom of that time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 58.</note> 
               <hi>in leaving a liberty for different ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, as to the manner of the Preſence;</hi> I cannot underſtand; except that they did in <hi>that time</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believe the Real Preſence (as hath been before expreſt) but would not certainly determine the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> that is (as Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> hath ſaid before) whether it was <hi>per,</hi> or <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>cum,</hi> or <hi>ſub,</hi> or <hi>trans;</hi> but if there be no ſuch Real Preſence in any <hi>manner,</hi> I know not what this <hi>Liberty of Speculations</hi> ſignifies, as to the <hi>manner,</hi> when the thing is not really after any manner; and if not (as our Anſwerer ſeems all along to affirm) this then might indeed be great Wiſdom, or humane Policy, not too rudely to choke the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Ears of their late eſtabliſht Reformation: But how it can conſiſt with true Piety, and a Church pretending to reform Errors, we ſhall beſt find by this conſideration.</p>
            <p>If Men had liberty to believe that Chriſt was real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent after <hi>any manner,</hi> it follows neceſſarily, that Chriſt was adorable there, where he was ſo preſent. But if the Church, <hi>in its Wiſdom,</hi> did certainly know, that Chriſt was <hi>not really</hi> preſent after any Manner; then the Church, <hi>in its Wiſdom,</hi> gave Men liberty to be Idolaters; for our Anſwerer hath been pleas'd to deliver us his Opinion, from Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Taylor, p.</hi> 69. who there ſays, <hi>That to give Divine worſhip to a</hi> Non Ens, <hi>muſt needs be Idolatry. For</hi> Idolum nihil eſt in mundo, <hi>ſaith St.</hi> Paul, <hi>and Chriſt as preſent by his Humane Nature in the Sacrament is a</hi> Non Ens, <hi>for it is not true, there is no ſuch thing; he is there
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62979:42"/>by his Diviner Power and Bleſſing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but for any other preſence, it is</hi> Idolum. And that the practice of the Learneder part of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nay, of the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf (if we will believe the Articles of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, in the beginning of the Reformation, or King <hi>James</hi> in the ſtrength of the Reformation) was accordingly Idolatrous; I am moſt abundantly ſatisfied; until ſome ſtronger Pen than our Anſwerers, ſhall fully confute, what is already extant to that purpoſe. In the mean time (leaving the Matter of Fact to the Doctors Conſcience) we will follow our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer.</p>
            <p>He is come now to Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> who tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>That Chriſts Body and Blood,</hi> indeed, <hi>and</hi> verily <hi>is given unto us; that we</hi> verily eat it, <hi>that we</hi> verily drink <hi>it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet we ſay not either that the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine is done away,</hi> (that is, Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is not our Diſpute) <hi>or that Chriſt's Body is let down from Heaven, or made</hi> really <hi>or</hi> fleſhly <hi>preſent in the Sacrament:</hi> If by <hi>really</hi> he means <hi>fleſhly,</hi> I ſubſcribe to all this (as to the Real Preſence.) He goes on: <hi>That ſpiritually</hi> (i. e. modo ſpirituali), <hi>and with the mouth of our Faith, we eat the Body of Chriſt, and drink his Blood, even as</hi> verily <hi>as his Body was</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily broken, <hi>and his Blood</hi> verily ſhed <hi>upon</hi> the Croſs. If the Biſhop was not an Eutychian, then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Body was verily, that is, ſubſtantially and truly broken upon the Croſs. Thus far then, we punctually agree: But the Biſhop explains himſelf: <hi>The Bread (he tells us) is an earthly thing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Figure, as Baptiſm in Water is alſo a Figure.</hi> 'Tis confeſt: Now leſt we ſhould think that by this Figure the Biſhop intended to exclude the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62979:42"/>he adds immediately, <hi>But the Body of Chriſt, that thereby is repreſented, and is there offer'd to our Faith (moſt true)</hi> is the thing (i. e. <hi>the Body of Chriſt</hi>) it ſelf, and not the Figure. As much of this as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer pleaſes, we have reaſon to be thankful to him for it.</p>
            <p>But he now comes to Anſwer for the venerable Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi> You have heard what hath been offer'd from the Diſcourſer. The Anſwerer tells us from Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> p. 61. <hi>That the parts of the Sacrament are the Body and Blood of Chriſt, becauſe they are cauſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental, upon the receipt whereof the participation of his Body and Blood enſueth: And that the Real Preſence of Chriſts moſt bleſſed Body and Blood, is not therefore to be ſought for in the Sacrament, but in the worthy Receiver of the Sacrament:</hi> All this is moſt conſiſtent with the Proteſtant Notion of the Real Preſence here contended for.</p>
            <p>Next Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> comes upon the Stage; and firſt the Anſwerer tells us (as from himſelf only) that this Biſhop inſinuates,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 62.</note> 
               <hi>That the Preſence of Chriſt in the Euchariſt, was much the ſame as in Baptiſm; the very Alluſion which the Holy</hi> Fathers <hi>were wont to make, to expreſs his Preſence by, in this holy Sacrament.</hi> That the Biſhop and the Holy <hi>Fathers</hi> might mean, that Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament, as in Baptiſm, Catholics do not deny; for they alſo conſtantly affirm the ſame thing, as much as either: But if our Anſwerer pretends to perſwade us, that either the Biſhop, or <hi>Fathers,</hi> or Catholics, mean him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo preſent, as to exclude the preſence alſo of his natural Body in the Sacrament; that remains to be prov'd, which hath not been done by himſelf, nor any Man yet, that I have met with; let him
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62979:43"/>therefore learn to underſtand the Catholic Faith, before he writes ſuch magiſterial Impertinences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: But let us hear the Biſhop himſelf; who, telling us, That the Sacrament of Chriſts Body is not meant of his glorified Body, but of his Body when it was Offer'd, Rent, and Slain, and Sacrificed for us; he goes on, <hi>We are (ſays he) in this action, not only carried up to Chriſt</hi> (ſurſum corda); <hi>but we are alſo carried back to Chriſt, as he was at the very inſtant, and in the very act of his offering. So, and no otherwiſe doth this Text teach: So, and no otherwiſe do we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him. By the Incomprehenſible power of his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit, not</hi> he alone, <hi>but</hi> he, as at the very act of his Offering is made preſent to us, <hi>and we incorporate into his death and inveſted in the benefits of it.</hi> Our Anſwerer (to do him Juſtice) is modeſt enough in this place to ſay, he <hi>thinks</hi> the Real Preſence cannot be otherwiſe meant than, either figuratively in the Elements, or Spiritually, in the Souls of thoſe who worthily receive him: But I think, that had this Learned Biſhop believed the manner (as they call it) of the Real Preſence, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> No man could have written more Orthodoxly of it, than this Biſhop here hath done.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 64.</note> The Anſwerer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the Opinions of <hi>Caſaubon</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> in the ſenſe of this paſſage of Biſhop <hi>Andrews;</hi> but why not in that produc'd by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer? However if it will gratifie him, I willingly ſo accept them. He makes Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> to ſing much after the ſame Tune: He ſays little to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Hall, Montague,</hi> and <hi>Bilſon, becauſe he hath not their works by him;</hi> but how he will excuſe their <hi>pacific deſign</hi> as he calls it, we ſhall conſider by and by. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Forbe's Charitable undertaking, has made him too
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62979:43"/>favourable to many corruptions of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>p.</hi> 65.</p>
            <p>And now he tells us but of two of all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines left to prove this new Fancy, which the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer would ſet up for the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> one, is Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi> whom he makes ſay a great deal more, than I am willing to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, for I am very weary of the Employment; and beſides, all ſignifies no more (at moſt) than to prove Doctor <hi>Taylor</hi> contradicts himſelf; or is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (as I hinted before) the moſt unintelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Writer that ever put Pen to Paper: The truth to me ſeems to be this; the Doctor in ſome places meant very plainly that which he as plainly wrote; in others that he was over cautious (conſidering the times, and circumſtances in which he liv'd) to write <hi>more</hi> plainly that which he truly meant. However, upon the Ballance of the whole, I take him to have been much rather a Defender, than an Oppoſer of the Real Preſence we ſpeak of. And now we are got to Mr. <hi>Thorndyke,</hi> where I cannot but ſmile at the confidence of our Anſwerer, who is not aſham'd to ſay (notwithſtanding his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended confutation is a ſtrong confirmation of that Real Preſence aſſerted by the Diſcourſer;) that he fears his Cauſe will be deſperate except Mr.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 69.</note> 
               <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyke</hi> can ſupport it. Well, what ſays Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyke?</hi> The Anſwerer tells us, firſt of a certain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to one <hi>T. G.</hi> in which he ſeems to ſay, <hi>That if the Church</hi> (I ſuppoſe he means the Engliſh Church) <hi>did ever pray the Fleſh and Blood might be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted inſtead of the Elements, under the Accidents of them</hi> (which is plain Tranſubſtantiation) <hi>then he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to call this the Sacramental Preſence of them in the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62979:44"/>Euchariſt:</hi> What is this to the purpoſe? He then tells us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 70.</note> that Mr. <hi>Thorndyke</hi> had a <hi>particular Notion</hi> in this Matter, and a long Story, in which he ſeems to deny Tranſubſtantiation: We do not affirm it of him. And at laſt a great way off in <hi>p.</hi> 90. he puts Biſhop <hi>Forbes</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> into a Sack together, and makes them as errand Knaves in a <hi>reconciling way,</hi> as his <hi>Proteſtant Miniſter,</hi> whom juſt before he mentions; but with this difference, the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſter,</hi> only diſſembled his own Opinion, that is, conceal'd it; but theſe two great Men have ſtrenuouſly defended the Real Preſence; and, not by conſequence, but <hi>poſitively,</hi> an Adoration due; when as our Anſwerer would perſwade us that they did <hi>not</hi> believe the Real Preſence; but did believe the Adoration of it to be Idolatry. That a paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic deſign, and a charitable undertaking might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage ſome Men to relax ſomewhat of Ceremonies, or Diſcipline, I neither wonder at, nor cenſure; but that there ſhould be any juſtifiable cauſe to oblige Men wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly and willingly to profeſs and teach Idolatry, is, I confeſs, beyond my underſtanding. I ſhrewdly ſuſpect that our Anſwerer, from his rare Hiſtorical Relicts, may have imbib'd ſome of <hi>Monſieur De Marolle's</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and from thence think damnable Hypocriſie in Religion, no great Sin; otherwiſe I cannot imagine how, with Charity, he can ſuppoſe it in theſe two great Men, who (I am perſwaded) were they alive, would ſpit in his Face for ſo ſcandalous an Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unworthy either of a Chriſtian, or a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>His laſt ſtroke,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 90.</note> is at the Learned Mr. <hi>Thorndyke,</hi> whom he leaves to ſhift for himſelf, with this Brand upon him, as deep as he can make it, That his Notion of the Real Preſence, was widely different
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62979:44"/>both from theirs, and ours, (and by conſequence from the Truth); but give me leave to tell you Sir, had you been worthy to have carried Mr. <hi>Thorndykes</hi> Papers after him (at leaſt as far as I may judge by theſe twenty two Sheets) you would have writ much leſs, and yet much more to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Thus, Reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> I have given you a Taſt of this freſh Author, I fear it hath not proved a <hi>boccone Saporito;</hi> but it was neceſſary in Vindication of my Teſtimonies, and by Conſequence, of that Learned <hi>Oxford</hi> Diſcourſer, upon whoſe Authority I produc't them. Begging your pardon then for this Digreſſion, I return to my firſt Diſcourſer.</p>
            <p>If it be true, that the Doctrine of the Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, in a literal Senſe, was believed from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times to this great Council of <hi>Lateran;</hi> let us conſider whether this Council exceeded its juſt Authority, or introduc't any Erroneous Doctrine into the Chriſtian Church: For the clearer under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this Matter, we are to note, that one <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> about the year 1060. (beſides other Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) maintain'd, that the Euchariſt was not truly and Subſtantially the Body and Blood of Chriſt, but only a Figure and Shadow of them; and that the Bread and Wine upon the Altar, were not Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially converted into the real Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt, by the Myſtery of holy Prayer, and the words of our Redeemer. Upon this; ſeveral Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men employed their Pens againſt this new and ſtrange falſe Doctrine, as <hi>Adelmannus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Brixia,</hi> formerly Schoolfellow of <hi>Berengarius; Hugo Lingonenſis, Epiſ. Durandus,</hi> before-mention'd; <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>francus,</hi> afterwards Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who, among other things, hath theſe words, <hi>This Faith
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62979:45"/>(ſpeaking of the Real Preſence according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation) the Church (which being ſpread over the whole World, is call'd Catholic) now holds, and hath held from the Primitive Times. But you (ſaith be to</hi> Berengarius) <hi>believe that the Bread and Wine of our Lords Table, remain unchanged, as to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance after Conſecration,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If this be true, which you believe and maintain concerning the Body of Chriſt; then that is falſe which is believed and taught of it by the Church over the whole World; for as many as own the name of Chriſtians, and are really ſuch, do profeſs, that, in the Sacrament they receive, the true Fleſh of Chriſt, and his true Blood; the ſame, which he took of the Virgin.</hi> Moſt wonderfully ſtrange, that ſo <hi>abſurd</hi> a Doctrine ſhould have ſpread ſo univerſally in ſo ſhort a time as our Diſcourſer is pleas'd to allow it. <hi>Guitmundus, Rupertus, Algerus,</hi> and other Learned Men writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him to the ſame effect: And moreover, this his Doctrine was condemn'd as falſe, and himſelf as an Innovator, in no leſs than Eight Councils and Synods before that of <hi>Lateran;</hi> which <hi>miſerable Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods</hi> (as the Anſwerer proudly calls them) may be ſuppoſed to have had as much Learning, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and I am ſure, much more Authority, than Twenty two ſuch Sheets as his, tho' ſtampt with an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> before them.</p>
            <p>Now let us obſerve; This <hi>Monſtrous, Abſurd, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous,</hi> and <hi>Impious</hi> Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation (as our Diſcourſer calls it) in ſomewhat more than two Hundred years, was ſo throughly eſtabliſht all over the Chriſtian World; that theſe Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and the <hi>Fathers</hi> of theſe Eight Councils, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in ſeveral Kingdoms, were ſo totally igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that their own Doctrine had its date from the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62979:45"/>Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> or that the Opinion of <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> had been ever before publickly profeſt, that they make no ſcruple of alledging, the <hi>Antiquity, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality,</hi> and <hi>Conſtant Practice</hi> of their own Doctrine, as a moſt convincing and unanſwerable Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his; <hi>Interroga Graecos, Armenios,</hi> (ſays <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franc) ſeu cujuſlibet nationis quoſcunque homines, uno ore hanc fidem</hi> (i. e. <hi>Tranſubſt.) ſe teſtabuntur habere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I profeſs, that if after this my moſt ſerious, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Enquiry concerning the Belief of the Ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> and the Catholic Church touching the Real Preſence, it ſhould poſſibly be true, that they all, or generally, agreed with our Diſcourſer, and his figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Interpretation, excluding the Subſtance; I would lay aſide all my Books, and conclude, once for all, That even the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf, is more <hi>eaſie</hi> and <hi>rational,</hi> than the true ſenſe of the <hi>Fathers</hi> concerning it, <hi>intelligible,</hi> or <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable.</hi> And tho I will not ſay with the <hi>Bookſellers Wife</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> That if the Primitive <hi>Fathers</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd Tranſubſtantiation, She would no longer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Chriſtianity; yet I may ſay, if they did believe it, and were miſtaken, a Chriſtians Faith, any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than it may be productive of good Works, is the moſt indifferent thing in the World.</p>
            <p>Our Diſcourſer tells us of one <hi>John Scotus,</hi> and <hi>Ratramnus,</hi> and I know not <hi>who,</hi> writing I know not <hi>what,</hi> againſt this Doctrine of the Real Preſence, at leaſt according to his Interpretation (tho I know many Catholics underſtand ſome of them in a very Orthodox ſenſe): But to me it ſeems as impertinent to bring two or three <hi>private</hi> perſons, advancing their <hi>private</hi> Opinions, againſt the Concurrent Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of all Authors, prior, preſent, and others
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62979:46"/>(ſince they wrote) poſterior to them; beſides the Definitions and Decrees of General Councils; as it would be among us, to produce the Authorities of <hi>John Milton,</hi> and <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> to prove that it was lawful among the <hi>Jews</hi> for the People, by their own Supream Power, to murder their Kings; and that in all Governments, the People have the ſame Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Authority, to judge, and puniſh, even by Death, their lawful hereditary Kings, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, if they ſhall ſo think fit.</p>
            <p>Now, having the Hiſtory of the Bible, as well as they, together with the expreſs Command of God, and conſtant Teſtimony and Practice of Learned Men through all Ages, and publick Laws, with Acts of Parliament to the contrary; theſe Men may write till their <hi>Hands, and Hearts ake</hi> (to uſe out Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer's expreſſion) before they ſhall perſwade me to renounce the ſtrongeſt Evidence imaginable, in favour of their private Sentiments. Whether our Diſcourſer be of my mind, or not, I cannot tell; but if he be, I ſee no greater reaſon to believe <hi>John Scotus</hi> than <hi>John Milton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now to the <hi>Church Authority,</hi> which ſo much offends him. Our indulgent Mother (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her favourable Diſcipline) permitted the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> (as ſhe had done for many years, that of the <hi>Conſubſtantiality</hi>) to paſs upward of Twelve Hundred years, without any other judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial determination of the <hi>Modus</hi> (as they call it) than ſuch as had been Originally planted in the hearts and minds of the Faithful, and cultivated in every Age, by Pious and Learned Men, in their Sermons, Catechiſms, and other Diſcourſes, as occaſion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But <hi>Berengarius</hi> (a Man fond of his own No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62979:46"/>and valuing himſelf much upon his own Reaſon) reſolved to ſet up for a new Light of the Church; and (among other Errors) taught the figurative acceptation of the Words of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as hath been before related.</p>
            <p>Upon this, he was admoniſht by ſeveral Pious and Learned Catholics, to retract betimes ſo new and pernicious a Hereſie. But the Arguments of ſenſe, procuring him a party among the Vulgar, he proſecuted his deſign with great vigor, until, at laſt, he was taken notice of by the Supream Church-Governors; and in a Council at <hi>Rome, An. Dom.</hi> 1050. his Doctrine was <hi>condemn'd,</hi> and himſelf <hi>excommunicated:</hi> At length, having ſeveral times ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd this his Hereſie, and as often return'd to his Vomit, he burnt the Book of <hi>Scotus,</hi> from whence he confeſt to have ſuckt part of his Poyſon; renounc'd (for the laſt time) with all Sincerity, his former Opinions; and ſpending the reſidue of his days in Piety and Devotion, died in the Unity of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholic Church, full of ſorrow and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Jan.</hi> 6. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1088. as may be ſeen in <hi>Membranis Taureacenſ.</hi> in <hi>Chronic. Clarii Floriacenſ. Monach. S. Petri vivi.</hi> in <hi>Will.</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury, l.</hi> 3. <hi>de geſtis Reg. Angl.</hi> In <hi>Baldrico Burgalienſi Abbate,</hi> and in the Manuſcript <hi>B. Martini Turonenſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, the Seeds of Hereſie thus ſown, were not eaſily rooted out: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſome Catholics themſelves (taking occaſion from this Hereſie) had writ-concerning this great Myſtery, according as they beſt apprenended it; But ſometimes the obſcurity of their Expreſſions, the double ſenſe which they admitted, and not clearly ſhewing what they themſelves believed (Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62979:47"/>which happen to moſt men, who write con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch high Myſteries without Authority) the Governours of the Church thought fit (as the beſt means to obviate theſe Inconveniences) to call a General Council under Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, which was the greateſt that ever had been ſince the Apoſtles; and therein, it was determined by near 1300 Fathers, that (according to the Doctrine of the moſt Ancient and Holy Fathers, Tradition of the Church, and former Councils) the Converſion of the Subſtance of Bread and Wine, after Conſecration, into the Subſtance of the Natural Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, the Accidents of Bread and Wine only remaining, ſhould thenceforward be call'd Tranſubſtantiation; which had been ſufficiently before expreſt and explain'd, by that wonderful Tranſmutation, and <hi>Tranſelementation</hi> aſſerted by the Fathers. This our Diſcourſer believes (with <hi>Scotus</hi>) to have been the neceſſary conſequence of the Council of <hi>Lateran, p.</hi> 21. and ſo do I too: Tho' in truth this explicative Term was (I think) more particularly eſtabliſht (as here expreſt) in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, to me, the Church ſeems ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worthy of blame, for decreeing what appears almoſt the neceſſary conſequence of the real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence (I mean) Tranſubſtantiation, that (as the Caſe and Circumſtances then ſtood) the Church had been very negligent, if ſhe had not ſo decreed. For it being always believ'd (which I think is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fully proved) That the Elements of Bread and Wine, after Conſecration, were moſt wonderfully, and by the Omnipotence of God converted into the Body and Blood of Chriſt; It is clear then,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62979:47"/>that either the <hi>Accidents,</hi> or the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of Bread and Wine muſt be changed into the Subſtance of the Body of Chriſt; But the <hi>Accidents</hi> are not ſo changed, therefore the <hi>Subſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the Subſtance of the Body of Chriſt is in the Bleſſed Sacrament, either <hi>with</hi> the Subſtance of Bread, or <hi>without</hi> the Subſtance of Bread. If the firſt, then Catholics, and our Diſcourſer are in the wrong. If the laſt, then <hi>Luther,</hi> and our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer are in the wrong: So which way our Diſcourſer ſhould happen to be in the right, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend, except <hi>Zuinglius</hi> ſhould have been more than <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and our Diſcourſer (the Diſciple of <hi>Zuinglius</hi>) greater than St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle of our Lord. Now beſides that the choice is eaſie in this Caſe, even from the Authority of one ſide, greater than of the other; yet whoſoever ſhall endeavour to reconcile the Real Preſence, with the Doctrine of Conſubſtantiation, or Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, will find harder difficulties in theſe, than of that of Tranſubſtantiation, ſo much condemn'd. The Authorities therefore which he brings from <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, Eraſmus, Tonſtal,</hi> and ſome others, to ſhew that before this Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> Men were at liberty concerning the <hi>modus,</hi> or manner of Chriſt's Real Preſence in the Sacrament, might have been ſome kind of Argument for a Lutheran; But how our Diſcourſer becomes concerned in it, I ſee not; ſince quite through his Diſcourſe, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in <hi>p.</hi> 35. he hath (with ſcorn) excluded Both.</p>
            <p>Our Diſcourſer hath yet one Argument relating to the <hi>time,</hi> when he ſuppoſeth this Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation to have come into the World,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62979:48"/>which is very remarkable. He tells us, That the <hi>Iconomachi</hi> (or oppoſers of Images) were very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous againſt the Reverence due to them, in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> about the year 750, arguing, <hi>That our Lord having left us no other Image of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but the Sacrament, in which the Subſtance of the Bread, is the Image of his Body, we ought to make no other Image of our Lord;</hi> But in the year 787. in the Second Council of <hi>Nice</hi> theſe ſcrupulous Greeks, in thirty ſeven years time, were grown ſo hardy in their Faith, and ſo extreamly fond of this new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, concerning the Corporal Preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, that they ſwallow'd it imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and from that time were very ſolicitous and careful to admoniſh us, that the Euchariſt is not the Figure or Image of the Body of our Lord, but his true Body, as appears from the ſeventh Synod; and he brings <hi>Bellarmin</hi> to vouch for him, <hi>p.</hi> 21, 22.</p>
            <p>Here we ſee theſe nice Greeks, who were ſo very exact and curious in ſmaller Matters, were content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make ſo great a paſſage in one Council, as, from the Figure of Chriſt in the Sacrament, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of his Subſtance; nay, and were ſo pleaſed with it, that from thence, and that time they took care to admoniſh us concerning it. But the ſqueamiſh Latins (notwithſtanding the Greeks had advanc'd ſo far in one ſingle Council) were little leſs than three hundred years according to our Diſcourſers computation, <hi>licking this miſhapen Monſter of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> (ſuch is the Elegancy of his Style) into that Form, in which it is now ſetled in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Indeed he hath been over generous to the Latins, in allowing them ſo conſiderable a time to reliſh and digeſt only the Mode of a thing, when
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62979:48"/>the eaſſe Greeks at one ſitting had diſpatcht the thing it ſelf, in which (according to our Diſcourſers Opinion) the great Barbarouſneſs and Impiety con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts. For (ſays he) <hi>The Impiety and Barbarouſneſs of the thing is not in truth extenuated, but only the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of it, by being done under the Species of Bread and Wine; for the thing, they acknowledge, is really done, and they believe, that they verily eat and drink the Natural Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> In truth, the Latins are obliged to him in confeſſing them to have been ſo extream cautious about the leſſer part; but how he will come off with the Greeks, for being ſo raſh and inconſiderate about the greater and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part, muſt be his care, if he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, had <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaid this, to have proved that the Greeks did <hi>then,</hi> and <hi>not till then,</hi> receive the Doctrine of the Real Preſence; Our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer, could he make any advantage of it (with good Reaſon) would have caſt it out, as the moſt improbable, and ridiculous conjecture, in the World: And yet here, becauſe he thinks it may help to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour his falſe account, he produceth it with as much gravity, as if he knew Catholics had leſs ſenſe to <hi>ſee a blot,</hi> than himſelf, raſhneſs <hi>to make one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to his fourth pretended Ground of this Doctrine, that is, <hi>The neceſſity of ſuch a Change in the Sacrament, to the Comfort and Benefit of thoſe who receive it, p.</hi> 30. To this, my Anſwer at preſent, is very ſhort. If I be ſatisfied, that our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the thing, I am convinc'd there was a good Reaſon for it, without over-curiouſly examining <hi>what,</hi> or <hi>why,</hi> in this Caſe, more than <hi>why</hi> he cured not thoſe who <hi>touched the Hem of his Garment,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Ceremony; or the <hi>blind;</hi> with out <hi>clay and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62979:49"/>ſpittle:</hi> And yet the Fathers, and many late Authors, will furniſh thoſe who are more inquiſitive, with many very good Reaſons, why this Change in the Sacrament, is more advantageous to the worthy Receiver, than the Figure would be, and I ſhall ſay ſomewhat of it my ſelf, hereafter.</p>
            <p>The laſt pretended Ground of this Doctrine, is (as he tells us) to <hi>magnifie the Power of the Prieſt,</hi> in being able to work ſo great a Miracle. Indeed, if the great Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> did make this a Ground of introducing Tranſubſtantiation, never did 1200 Learned Men take wronger Meaſures; For notwithſtanding a due reſpect be generally paid by all good Catholics to Prieſts (as their Character requires) yet I will be judged by all ſuch as have travell'd abroad, Whether a Presbyterian Parſon in his Conventicle, or a <hi>London</hi> Miniſter in his Pariſh, or a Calviniſt Predicator in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> who make <hi>nothing</hi> of the Sacrament; Do not yet pretend (both <hi>Males</hi> and <hi>Females</hi>) to have as much reſpect paid them, as ere a Prieſt, of equal quality, in <hi>France, Italy</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> who nevertheleſs are the Inſtruments by which this unexpreſſible Change is made? But our Diſcourſer labours hard here, to prove that this Change is no Miracle to Senſe; But, had he advis'd with any Catholic, he might have ſpar'd his pains, for I will engage they would have confeſt it to him at the firſt word.</p>
            <p>Our Diſcourſer having hitherto (with great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs) deſtroy'd the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; yet (to make ſure work) he kills it again with four deadly Objections drawn from the infinite <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> of this Doctrine to the Chriſtian Religion; As, 1. The <hi>Stupidity.</hi> 2. The <hi>Real Barbarouſneſs</hi> of this
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62979:49"/>Doctrine, ſuppoſing it be true. 3. The <hi>bloody Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences.</hi> And, 4. The <hi>danger of Idolatry,</hi> if it be not true, <hi>p.</hi> 33.</p>
            <p>To prove the <hi>Stupidity</hi> of this Doctrine, our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer produceth two Learned <hi>Heathens, Tully</hi> and <hi>Averroes,</hi> wondring that any Men ſhould be ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, as to pretend to eat their God. Now, that there is Stupidity in the Caſe, is moſt certain; But, whether it be in the Doctrine; Or in <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Averroes;</hi> Or in our Diſcourſer, who brings two <hi>Heathens</hi> Teſtimonies againſt a Myſtery of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Religion, I leave to Judgment. I ſuppoſe he may have heard of ſuch an Epiſtle, as the firſt of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> I would recommend to him the firſt Chapter, and particularly, Verſ. 18.19, 20. where it is written, <hi>For the preaching of the Croſs is to them that periſh, fooliſhneſs. Where is the wiſe, where is the ſcribe, where is the diſputer of this world? hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of the world?</hi> And verſ. 27 <hi>God hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world to confound the wiſe.</hi> Now whether <hi>Averroes,</hi> and our Diſcourſer were the Wiſe Men, or the Fooliſh, here intended, I muſt leave again to Judgment.</p>
            <p>But I have not yet done with <hi>Averroes,</hi> for his words cited by our Diſcourſer, <hi>p.</hi> 34. are very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable. <hi>I have travel'd</hi> (ſays he) <hi>over the world, and have found divers Sects; but ſo ſottiſh a Sect, or Law, I never found, as is the Sect of the Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with their own Teeth, they devour the God whom they worſhip.</hi> What ill luck it was, that this great Philoſopher ſhould not have met with the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Rabanus Maurus,</hi> or ſome <hi>One</hi> other of our Diſcourſers Predeceſſors in Opinion, at leaſt, in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62979:50"/>ſome Corner of the World, who might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd him of his miſtake, and reconcil'd him a little better to the Chriſtian Religion! But not to have found <hi>one</hi> Chriſtian over the whole World (neer ſix Hundred years ſince, after <hi>Rabanus</hi> had writ againſt <hi>Paſcaſius</hi>) leſs ſottiſh than the reſt; will ſerve (at leaſt) to prove a Sottiſhneſs alſo in this Caſe; but whether in thoſe Chriſtians, or, in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſer (who hath brought ſo ſtrong a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, to prove the <hi>Univerſality</hi> of this Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, even of ſo learned a Man, who had travell'd <hi>all the World over</hi>) I muſt once more leave to Judgment.</p>
            <p>But ſure I am, from <hi>Averroes</hi> his own Works, and the knowledge which he had of that vaſt difference between Bodies in their <hi>Natural, Groſs,</hi> and <hi>Earthly</hi> Compoſition; and the <hi>pure</hi> Subſtances of theſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſeparated from their <hi>foeces,</hi> or <hi>accidents,</hi> by <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> or <hi>putrefaction, diſtillations, digeſtions,</hi> and <hi>ſublimations,</hi> until they become <hi>Eſſences,</hi> or <hi>pure Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;</hi> I ſay, from his Experimental Philoſophy of Common Bodies thus <hi>alter'd,</hi> and <hi>ſublimated,</hi> he would have made no difficulty to have ſolv'd moſt of our Diſcourſers <hi>abſurdities</hi> concerning this Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; and yet there is no Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon between theſe Common Bodies, tho never ſo purely <hi>defoecated,</hi> and <hi>exalted,</hi> which can bear any proportion with the glorified Body of our Saviour united with his Divinity: So that I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, had <hi>Averroes</hi> been ſatisfied concerning the other Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, and rightly inform'd concerning the Doctrine of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, he would have been as good a Chriſtian in that Point, as Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> 3d. or <hi>Pius</hi> 4th.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:62979:50"/>
            <p>But our Diſcourſer tells us; that the ſtupidity of this Doctrine breeds <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Infidels:</hi> Even ſo the warmth of the Sun breeds <hi>Maggots,</hi> and many other Inſucts, but the Matter muſt be firſt diſpoſed to Corruption. Now altho the Sun be much hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>France, Spain, Portugal,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> than in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or in <hi>Holland,</hi> yet I appeal to all Men who have any knowledge of thoſe Kingdoms, whether there be not as many reputed Atheiſts in theſe two laſt Governments, where the Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation is not ſo publickly, nor generally profeſt, as in any other part of the Chriſtian World <hi>propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably</hi> where it is? And what indeed have been the true parents of Atheiſm, and Infidelity, but the deviliſh <hi>pride</hi> of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſet up againſt the bleſſed <hi>Humility</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience?</hi> But our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer in this Page begins to be very ſeriouſly idle, and impertinent; out of ſome reſpect therefore to himſelf, we will paſs it over, and come to <hi>p.</hi> 35. where he moſt grievouſly accuſeth this Sacrament of Barbarouſneſs, upon the Suppoſition of the truth of this Doctrine: But ſure if this Doctrine <hi>be true,</hi> then it is impoſſible that it ſhould be barbarous, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our Saviour himſelf, who commanded it, and is there voluntarily preſent in it, ſhould have inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted a barbarous Sacrament; which, whether our Diſcourſer can believe, I know not; but ſure I am, if the Doctrine be <hi>not</hi> true, it cannot be barbarous to eat him in <hi>imagination</hi> only, except our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers opinion be alſo barbarous. He tells us, <hi>'tis very unworthily done to our friend, and barbarous to feaſt upon his Fleſh and Blood.</hi> I am glad to find our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer capable of ſo much Tenderneſs: But he might have read of very many Provinces in the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62979:51"/>
               <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> who count it their greateſt glory, to eat their beſt deceaſed Friends, perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, that thereby, they do (as it were) regenerate, or reanimate thoſe to whom they were firſt obliged for their own lives, by transforming them thus into their own Nature, and Subſtance. With indignation therefore they reproach our manner of Burials as moſt inhumane. <hi>O pauvre Gens</hi> (ſaith my Author) <hi>comment laiſſez vous manger cette chair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieuſe aux Sales vers de la terre? Et que monument plus digne lui pouvez vous donner, que celuy de vos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres entrailles?</hi> And upon this conſideration it was, that the renowned <hi>Artemiſe</hi> drank the Aſhes of her dear departed Husband. The Barbarouſneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore objected by our Diſcourſer (ſuppoſe this eating were according to his falſe Conceptions) proceeds from the narrowneſs of his own thoughts, who would judge, and meaſure the Civility and Reaſon of the whole World, according to the Cuſtoms (it may be) of his own little Province.</p>
            <p>But, tho no Catholic thus pretended to eat the Body and Blood of Chriſt (for that they all know he is immortal, and uncapable of Death, or Suffering, or Corruption, or any other indignities) yet our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer will needs compare this eating in the holy Sacrament, to the violent hacking and ſlaſhing of our living Friends, and carnally devouring their raw Fleſh, like the worſt of <hi>Cannibals:</hi> What an odious and diſproportionate Compariſon hath he made, on purpoſe to deceive his Friends, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, and ſcandalize thoſe, whom he ſuppoſes, his Enemies?</p>
            <p>But before I quit this Page, I muſt pay my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to one main Demonſtration of his, which
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62979:51"/>(he ſays) is worth a thouſand; and it is this; <hi>That the Heathens objected no ſuch Cuſtom to the Chriſtians, therefore no ſuch Doctrine believed.</hi> Now this piece of Malice might have paſt undiſturb'd, with many others which I have not taken notice of, had he not had the confidence (I will not uſe his own expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Impudence</hi>) to have provok't an Anſwer by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the half Teſtimony of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 11. to countenance his own Error; where, that very <hi>Father,</hi> in that very place, is making an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy to the Heathen Emperor <hi>Antoninus,</hi> and is ſo far from mincing the Matter, or explaining it by a figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Senſe, That he there tells the Emperor, <hi>We are taught that the</hi> Food (ſpeaking of the Sacrament) <hi>being Conſecrated by the Prayer of the Word. Is the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt Jeſus himſelf Incarnate. Illius incarnati Jeſu, &amp; Carnem, &amp; Sanguinem eſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docti ſumus. Apol.</hi> 2. It is moſt prodigiouſly ſtrange, and inexcuſable in this holy Father, to have us'd this ſcandalous Metaphor to a Heathen Emperor (which they cautiouſly expreſt to the Chriſtian <hi>Catechumens</hi>) if he intended nothing more than a figurative Senſe: For I will refer my ſelf to any Man, whether it had not been more prudent, and (it may be) pious, to have ſoftned and moderated the expreſſion to a Heathen, tho the Father had truly believed the Real Preſence, than thus to have expos'd himſelf, and laid an unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſtumbling-block before the Emperor, if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he did not believe it.</p>
            <p>But our Diſcourſer (not ſatisfied with this) tells us a Story p. 12. <hi>That the Heathen Greeks, having taken ſome Servants of the Chriſtian</hi> Catechumeni, <hi>urg'd them by violence to tell them ſome Secrets of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; who confeſt, That they had heard from their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62979:52"/>that the Divine Communion was the (Body and Blood of Chriſt; and, that they (i. e. the</hi> Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni) <hi>thinking that it was really Fleſh and Blood de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd as much to the</hi> Greeks. And yet our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer in <hi>p.</hi> 35. will not admit, that any ſuch thing was ever objected by the Heathens to the Chriſtians, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' by violence the Chriſtians themſelves confeſt it. What a bold, conceited Diſcourſer is this who whilſt he manifeſtly confutes himſelf, thinks his Adverſaries ſo impotent, as not only, not to have any defenſive Arms of their own, but alſo not to dare to make uſe of <hi>his,</hi> when he ſo fairly offers them againſt his own falſe Arguments? His miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> application of the whole Story, from the Anſwer of <hi>Blandina</hi> (which he ſtrangely miſtakes) is very ſilly; For what Catholics ever thought that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Sacrament, was a breach of their Faſt? If any had, by miſtake, ſome ſuch thoughts (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſeems to inſinuate) the breach of their Faſt muſt be imputed to the receipt of the Symbols, or Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Bread and Wine, which indeed may nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; but not to the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now had not our Diſcourſer thus demonſtrably anſwered himſelf, and ſaved us thereby a further la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I could have recommended him to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Greg. Nazian.</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and ſeveral others of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> where he would have found theſe Objections made to the Chriſtians, and their Anſwers to them, much after the manner of <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi> And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is told us more plainly in the Hiſtories of thoſe times, than, that the Heathens, having a confuſed Notion of the great Myſtery of the Sacrament, did commonly accuſe the Chriſtians of eating Mans
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62979:52"/>Fleſh, or young Children, or ſometimes their God. Sure our Diſcourſer intended to prevent us from uſing this Argument our ſelves, for this Objection of the Heathens hath ever been accounted a kind of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Antiquity of our Doctrine.</p>
            <p>His third Objection is, <hi>from the bloody Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of this Doctrine:</hi> But he gives us no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inſtances, and he doth well to grow more wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt; for he hath been very unlucky in them: Since therefore he is pleaſed only to affirm in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, I am contented to deny in general, and ſo we are upon even ground.</p>
            <p>His laſt Objection is, <hi>from the danger of Idolatry, if this Doctrine be not true;</hi> and I add, the danger of our Diſcourſers moſt execrable Blaſphemies if this Doctrine be true; let us therefore both conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly of it, ſince the danger on both ſides is very great: However we have the Authorities of many Learned Church of <hi>England</hi> Men (as may be ſeen at large in the <hi>Oxford</hi> Diſcourſer) who have acquitted us of Idolatry. Whilſt our Diſcourſer ſtands almoſt ſingle, in the ſcurrilous bitterneſs of his rude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly expreſſions.</p>
            <p>And here I thought our Diſcourſer would have ended his dire wrath againſt Tranſubſtantiation; but to be yet more ſecure (and with good Reaſon too) that it may never riſe up in Judgment againſt him; he comes back again, and in <hi>p.</hi> 37. gives it four wounds more for the abſurdity of its Doctrine; and theſe are performed by way of Four very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Queſtions; As Firſt, <hi>p.</hi> 38. Whether this Doctrine doth not contradict his <hi>Senſes?</hi> Secondly, Whether it can be proved by his <hi>Senſes?</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Whether it be not againſt the certainty of his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62979:53"/>
               <hi>Senſes?</hi> And Laſtly, Whether it be not againſt the Evidence of his <hi>Senſes?</hi> Now becauſe to me theſe retail'd Queſtions ſeem to import much the ſame thing; I will take the liberty (for the ſake of a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier Concluſion) to give my Opinion concerning them <hi>in groſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before we conſider the <hi>monſtrous Abſurdities</hi> of this Doctrine, ſet forth in theſe four great Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it is reaſonable that we ſeriouſly think with our ſelves, upon what account this <hi>Senſleſs</hi> Doctrine ſhould happen to get ſuch firm footing in the World, as to have ſpread (in a very ſhort time as our Diſcourſer ſuppoſes) over the face of the whole Chriſtian Church: Nay more, That in all probability it might have been univerſally receiv'd, even at this day, had not the extraordinary <hi>Learning, Reaſon, Senſe</hi> (and I know not what other qualifications) of <hi>John Scotus, Berengarius, Zuinglius,</hi> and our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, opened the Eyes of poor blinded Chriſtians, and ſhewn them, how their Senſes were lead Captivity Captive by the <hi>Jugling tricks, Hocus Pocus,</hi> and <hi>Cheat</hi> of this Doctrine (for ſo he is pleas'd to call) Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation <hi>p.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>I name not <hi>Luther</hi> among the great Reformers, as to this Point, for he agrees with Catholics, as to the Real Preſence, tho' he differs in the <hi>Modus;</hi> and with his whole heart Anathematizes and Curſes the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Diſcourſer (under the name of <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius</hi>) and all his Adherents,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. contr. Art. Iovan. Theſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2.</note> in theſe words, <hi>We cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in earneſt the Zuinglians and all the Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for Hereticks, and alienated from the Church of God.</hi> And again, <hi>Curſed be the Charity, and Concord of the Sacramentaries for ever, and ever, to all Eternity,</hi> Tom. Wittemb. fol. 381.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:62979:53"/>
            <p>Now upon the beſt enquiry I could make concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Eſtabliſhment of this Doctrine, I found but Four tolerable good Reaſons how it came to get ſo great credit among Chriſtians. The Firſt is, becauſe our Bleſſed Saviour (who is the Fountain of Wiſdom and Truth) did inſtitute this Sacrament in ſuch plain words, as, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> That no Propoſition upon Earth can be made to us in more expreſs and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Terms. Secondly, Becauſe the Apoſtles did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our Saviour ſpake in earneſt, and really meant as he ſaid (at leaſt) if we will believe the aforenam'd <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> who tells us, <hi>That the Apoſtles in the Commentaries written by them have recorded that Jeſus ſo commanded.</hi> Thirdly, Becauſe all the Ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> who have written of the Holy Euchariſt, have expreſt themſelves ſo fully concerning their firm Belief of the Real Preſence in a literal Senſe, That I defie <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and all his Works (allowing me ſome Senſe, or preſerving that little which I have) to underſtand them totally in a figurative Senſe. And Laſtly, Becauſe General Councils (taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that ſome vain-glorious ſelf-conceited Men, had impudently preſum'd to interpret thoſe words of our Saviour contrary to the ſenſe of the Apoſtles, and Primitive Fathers, and practice of the whole Chriſtian Church) had authoritatively decreed, That the Judgment of the bleſſed Apoſtles, and holy <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> ſhould be follow'd in this Matter, that is, That the Subſtance of Bread and Wine, after Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was converted into the Subſtance of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and that the Hereſie of theſe new Upſtarts ſhould be condemned, and themſelves excommunicated.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Reaſons, methinks, might be ſufficient
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62979:54"/>to ſhew that a Doctrine thus inſtituted, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us, might very probably be generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived among Men, who own the Authority of the Inſtitutor, and Fidelity of thoſe, who, being Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Action, have aſſured us of its meaning.</p>
            <p>Nor can I perſwade my ſelf there is any Man ſo prejudiced and uncharitable upon Earth (except thoſe whoſe Charity <hi>Luther</hi> curſt) as to believe, That ſo many Learned Men, in ſuch Auguſt and Sacred Aſſemblies, ſhould <hi>ſolemnly, wittingly,</hi> and <hi>willingly</hi> impoſe upon the World ſo pernicious, and damnable a Doctrine, if they themſelves knew, or could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that this Doctrine was falſe: Except ſome vaſt, and wonderful temporal Intereſt ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with theſe <hi>Fathers,</hi> and Doctors (whoſe reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been high in the World) thus dangerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to expoſe their own Souls, and the Souls of all who belonged to them, or depended upon them, for the obtaining this ſuppoſed worldly Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>A learned Proteſtant, in his <hi>Anſwer to ſome Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> ſeems to have a great reſpect for General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, but tells us, p. 3. <hi>That Men are liable to hopes and fears; and therefore we cannot depend upon them.</hi> Now <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> in this place relate only to Temporal Concerns, which we will ſuppoſe <hi>Intereſt</hi> in its lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt acceptation. But, in the name of God, what Intereſt is this, for which ſo much is thus deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately engaged? Why truly our Anſwerer ſays no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it; But our Diſcourſer, who hath left no Stone unturn'd, but <hi>flies at all,</hi> tells us at laſt, p. 30. <hi>That it is to magnifie the power of the Prieſt in being able to work ſo great a Miracle.</hi> I have already hinted how much theſe <hi>Fathers</hi> have been all along miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62979:54"/>if this was their deſign. But Secondly, from the diſproportion between the poorneſs of the reward, and ineſtimable price that is paid, even <hi>eternal Silva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> I might moſt convincingly argue the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the deſign, and fix it only in the mean and unworthy thoughts of our trifling Diſcourſer. But that I may clear theſe holy <hi>Fathers,</hi> and Councils, beyond all further doubt or diſpute; I do affirm this little deſign to have been ſo far from their thoughts, that they have conſtantly declar'd this wonderful tranſmutation to proceed, not from any <hi>power</hi> of the Prieſt, but by the ſole Omnipotency of Almighty God. And becauſe our Diſcourſer ſeems to have ſome value for St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> I ſhall produce his Teſtimony as it is cited <hi>be Conſecratione Diſt.</hi> 2. c. 72. His words are theſe, <hi>In the Myſtery of the Body of Chriſt performed within the holy Church, there is nothing more done by a good Prieſt, and nothing leſs by a wicked one; becauſe what is wrought there</hi> is not by the Merit of him who Conſecrates, <hi>but by the word of our Creator, and the power of the Holy Ghoſt; for if it were by</hi> the merit of the Prieſt, <hi>'twould not at all belong to Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> If St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> could have propheſied that a malicious Diſcourſer Twelve Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after his death ſhould have propos'd ſuch a fooliſh Cauſe, to have produc'd ſo abſur'd a Doctrine (in the Language of our Diſcourſer) I know not how he would have anſwer'd him more pertinently. I ſhall not trouble you therefore with the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>St. Ambr. l. de his qui miſt. init.</hi> and ſeveral other <hi>Fathers,</hi> together with General Councils, particularly that of <hi>Florence, de Sacram. Euch.</hi> to the ſame purpoſe; but conclude, that the Apoſtles, <hi>Fathers,</hi> and Councils, having no
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62979:55"/>deſign or proſpect, of any valuable conſideration, for ſo great a riſque, as their Eternal Salvation; muſt have impos'd this Doctrine upon mankind, either through groſs Ignorance, or meer wilful, and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh premeditated Malice: But having no manner of reaſon to believe the firſt, and from my heart dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſo curſed a thought as the laſt, we will next conſider, what inducements they might have had (from the conſideration of Spiritual advantages, ariſing from thence to the Chriſtian World) to have preſt this Doctrine (believing it to be true) with the greater earneſtneſs. And indeed the advantages are very many, and very great. As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Euchariſt is a pledge of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, That we are, not only by <hi>Faith,</hi> but even <hi>Corporally</hi> united with Chriſt. Thirdly, That, in regard of this Union, the Euchariſt is a Seal to us of our Reſurrection. Fourthly, That through it, we are made partakers of the Divine Nature. Fifthly, That by being thus truly, and really unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chriſt, we cannot be altogether divided from ſuch influences as proceed from Chriſt. Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That our Faith is encreaſed proportionable to the difficulties which encompaſs this Doctrine. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venthly, That our Hope is raiſed hereby to a ſublimer pitch; for by the participation of the Body of our Lord, and his Preſence in the bleſſed Euchariſt, we anticipate, as it were, the Joys of Heaven, even in our mortal Bodies;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> 24.</note> whence St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tells us, that, <hi>Dum in hac vita ſumus, ut terra nobis coelum ſit, facit hoc myſterium.</hi> Eightly, That from the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of our bleſſed Saviours Love, who being touched even in the Bowels of Tenderneſs towards us, left us at his departure, his Sacred Body to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62979:55"/>our Souls and Bodies unto Life Everlaſting; we alſo might return the pureſt Love and Affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him, and Charity toward one another, who are thus ſubſtantially united by the Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Spiritual Food according to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>For we being many are one Bread and one Body, for we are all partakers of that one Bread.</hi> And, Ninthly, That it is a Commemoration of our Lords Paſſion, a Confirmation of his Teſtament, and a propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sacrifice, not only for the living, but for the dead.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many more weighty Conſiderations of this kind together with the Teſtimony of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> Authority of General Councils, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal practice of all Chriſtians until theſe two laſt Centuries, will enable us I hope to encounter the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed abſurdities of our Diſcourſer: We ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage therefore this <hi>uncircumciſed Philiſtine,</hi> (I mean) this <hi>Goliah</hi> Argument, with all its boaſting train of ſenſleſs Queſtions. And</p>
            <p>Firſt, I know not how Philoſophy can be much concern'd on either ſide; for what Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher will tell me, how the Divine Nature, identifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Perſon of the Father, ſhould be Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Son, without alſo communicating the Perſon? Or how the Unity, or Individuality of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhould be in a diverſity of Perſons, neither confounding the Perſons, nor dividing the Subſtance? How in the Myſtery of the Incarnation God ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth from the Humanity of Chriſt, his manner of ſubſiſtence, inſerting it in his Divinity? How the Son ſhould be Conſubſtantial, and Co-eternal with the Father? How ſomething may be made out of nothing, and that ſomething reduc'd again to nothing? How Eternity, which is <hi>inſtans durationis
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62979:56"/>non fluens,</hi> an inſtant of duration, may be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to ſubſiſt without reſpect to time paſt, or time to come? How God Almighty, who is one ſimple, and indiviſible <hi>Being,</hi> ſhould be at once ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially preſent in all places, and things? A Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſo inexplicable, that it forced St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to ſay, <hi>Miratur hoc Mens humana, &amp; quia non capit, fortaſſe non credit.</hi> Nay more, how our Soul, which is the Light of our Bodies in this our Pilgrimage upon Earth, can be totally in the Head, and totally in the Feet, and totally at the ſame time in the whole Body, and in every part of it; Or how the Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which is our Common Guide through the paths of the deep, ſhould point always towards the <hi>North;</hi> or if ſometimes it varies, whence ſhould proceed its variation? When Philoſophy hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd all theſe, with many more hitherto invincible Difficulties, I make no doubt, but She will then free alſo Tranſubſtantiation from the Calumny of our Diſcourſers <hi>monſtrous Abſurdities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, that we may the better deal with them, we ſhall divide them into ſuch as ſeem to appear ſo, Firſt to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Secondly to <hi>Senſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Firſt, our Diſcourſer ſeems to have been modeſt, ſince of a thouſand inſinuated; he is pleaſed to name but two, Firſt, <hi>the groſs contradiction of the ſame Body being in ſo many ſeveral places at once;</hi> And Secondly of <hi>our Saviours giving away himſelf with his own hands, and yet keeping himſelf to himſelf,</hi> p. 37. The latter hath received a particular Anſwer from <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> in his <hi>Comment upon Pſal.</hi> 33. as hath been already ſhewn, and I ſhall not preſume to mend it. Nor, will this <hi>Fathers</hi> own <hi>quodammodo,</hi> in another place; or that of <hi>Bedes</hi> upon the ſame <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. help
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62979:56"/>him in the leaſt; for all Catholics willingly accept the word and moſt juſtly interpret it to be <hi>modo Spirituali,</hi> which manner they all profeſs and teach.</p>
            <p>But for the Firſt, which as much concerns the Real Preſence (a Doctrine own'd by Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and at preſent by all <hi>Lutherans</hi>) as Tranſubſtantiation believ'd by Catholics, I ſhall ſpeak of <hi>That,</hi> and the reſt of his Queſtions about Senſe (which are common Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in all Proteſtant Authors againſt this Subject) when I come to the Concluſion, to which I haſten.</p>
            <p>Our Diſcourſer hath one Argument more to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the Novelty of Tranſubſtantiation, which, being more particularly urg'd by himſelf than ſome others, I ſhall endeavour to give a reaſonable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it, and ſo take my leave of him, until we meet again in the Concluſion, backt with the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of ſome other late Authors, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them all.</p>
            <p>He tells us, p. 26. <hi>That the firſt-riſe of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was about the beginning of the Ninth Age, tho it did not take firm root until towards the end of the Eleventh; And this time (he ſays) was the moſt likely of all others, it being by the conſent of their own Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, the moſt dark and diſmal time, that ever happened to the Chriſtian Church both for Ignorance, and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Vice.</hi> And then illuſtrates all this by the Parable of the Tares, which he conceives the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my might have ſown in ſo dark and long a night. The Conjecture is very plauſible until it be well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, and then (I am perſwaded) his Argument will not only vaniſh, but be turn'd againſt himſelf (as many others have been) with no ſmall advantage to our Cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:62979:57"/>
            <p>I readily grant, that ſome part of the time aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him for the introducing of this Doctrine, was diſmal enough, upon thoſe three accounts mentioned by him: But I alſo affirm, That ſuch a Doctrine could never have met men in Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more contrary and averſe to its eſtabliſhment, than to be thus overwhelmed with Ignorance, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Vice. And firſt for <hi>Ignorance,</hi> It is Evident to all Mankind (and therefore the more ſtrongly Objected againſt us by our Diſcourſer, and all Proteſtants) That Tranſubſtantiation is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which highly contradicts our Common Senſes. Now as ſuch, the abuſes of it, muſt needs have been, Firſt, moſt notoriouſly viſible to the moſt Vulgar and illiterate, for they (ſeldom looking further into things than the Common appearances) would certainly have taken the firſt, and ſtrongeſt Alarm, upon the Propoſition only, of ſo new, and inſupportably ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a Doctrine (as our Diſcourſer calls it) if they had not from Age to Age, ſuckt it in with their firſt nouriſhment, and ſeen it ſo univerſally receiv'd, that they no more conſider'd the conſequences of it, than they did thoſe of ſome other Myſteries of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which they equally alike received as matter of Faith from the Authority and veracity of their Spiritual Guides, and Governours.</p>
            <p>But when as <hi>Berengarius</hi> (about the Tenth Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) was bold enough to teach, and write againſt it, ſhewing the ſtrong difficulties which he thought en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſt it; we then ſee a Party of the Vulgar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in to him apace, whilſt nevertheleſs, the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſc. of the Holy Euch. p.</hi> 31.</note> from many parts of the World, judiciouſly and ſtrenuouſly oppos'd him. The ſame thing may be obſerved from the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> whoſe Ring-leader
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62979:57"/>
               <hi>Waldo,</hi> a moſt illiterate Merchant of <hi>Lions</hi> (as all Hiſtorians confeſs) procured alſo a miſerable Crew, who, from their poverty were ignominiouſly call'd, the poor Men of <hi>Lions;</hi> and their Poſterity fixt themſelves among the Barbarous and ignorant Mountancers, about, and upon the <hi>Alpes,</hi> who have remained obſtinate Oppoſers of this Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, even unto this preſent Age. The laſt Inſtance I ſhall give, is of the <hi>Wickliſſiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> who following in a great meaſure the Doctrines of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> and ſome other Hereſies, had got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two Hundred Thouſand of the Rabble, who with Rebellious Arms in their Hands, had well nigh reduc'd the King himſelf to the laſt extremities: However his Hereſies were condemn'd by the learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of the Univerſities, as far as the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of thoſe diſtracted times would permit, and the intereſt which (upon ſome other account) <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff</hi> himſelf had gotten in the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and ſome other Perſons of Quality. The ſame might be ſaid of the <hi>Huſſites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and many more too long to mention, who became irreconcileable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to this Doctrine. Whence it is moſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, even by undeniable matter of Fact, that the Eſtabliſhment of Tranſubſtantiation; could hope for no advantage from an <hi>ignorant</hi> Age; ſince the <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> have been the firſt, and greateſt Oppoſers of it, and the moſt <hi>Learned</hi> Men, generally its Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>Neither Secondly, can a <hi>vitious</hi> Generation poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be favourers of this Doctrine: For, whether it be true, or falſe, yet whilſt it is believed to be true, it is certainly the greateſt promoter of Piety, and Devotion, of any Article (it may be) in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62979:58"/>Religion: For when we conſider, That Chriſt was not only pleas'd once to die, but to become alſo a daily Sacrifice for us, and to offer his very Body to us, for the nouriſhment of our Souls and Bodies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Everlaſting Life; How is it poſſible that Men ſhould be leſs ſenſible of Gods great Goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and our own unexpreſſible Love and Duty towards him, believing this Doctrine to be true, than not believing it at all? Vice therefore could have no hand, either in the contriving, or ſetling ſo pious, ſo venerable, and ſo comfortable a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let us conſider whether <hi>Superſtition</hi> could probably have introduc'd this ſuppoſed damnable Error. I cannot deny that Superſtition is it ſelf an Error, yet totally inconſiſtent with what we call <hi>formal Vice;</hi> for it is rather an Erroneous exceſs in Devotion, and is the effect of an unreaſonable fear; at leaſt, if we will believe Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> who thus diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth it from Atheiſm. <hi>Superſtitio</hi> (ſays he) <hi>à metu ſine recta ratione: Atheiſmus à rationis opinione ſine metu proficiſcitur:</hi> So that altho it be an Error, yet it is ſuch a one, as is accompanied with <hi>fear;</hi> whereas Vice proceeds from a want of that due <hi>fear,</hi> which we ought to have of Gods Juſtice, and the puniſhment due from thence to our Sins: And by conſequence <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> can never meet (according to our Diſcourſers acceptation of Vice) together in this place.</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to ſhew, by the plain, natural conſequences of <hi>Ignorance, Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Vice,</hi> that they could not have given any encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to impoſe a Doctrine, which hath ever been the Subject of the moſt <hi>Learned</hi> Pens, in magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62979:58"/>or explaining its Myſtery; and in its Practice, one of the greateſt advancers of a <hi>vertuous,</hi> and a <hi>holy</hi> Life.</p>
            <p>But having already frankly confeſt, that <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> reigned more powerfully during ſome part of thoſe Centuries, than (it may be) in any others ſince, or before; let us now (complying with our Diſcourſers Hiſtorical account concerning the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of thoſe times) examine what real effect they might have had upon this great Article of Faith, Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>Let us then Suppoſe (what I hope is ſufficiently proved) that this Doctrine had been implicitely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd from the Apoſtles days: It is then confeſt by our Diſcourſer, that about the Eighth and Ninth Century, ſome Men began to write copiouſly for, and againſt it, and alſo down to the Eleventh and Twelfth. And here, whilſt we truly lament, ſo muſt we juſtly apply the Vice, and Ignorance of thoſe unhappy times, to the great ſcandals, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties under which that Apoſtolic Doctrine lies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our own Age.</p>
            <p>The Vices of ſome, and affected Noveltie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, might probably have induced ſome well meaning Men to write concerning this great Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but whilſt nothing had been Authoritatively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd concerning (what they call) the <hi>Modus,</hi> or manner of Chriſts Real Preſence in the Sacrament; ſome, by endeavouring to explain it, made the Text (by their private Notions) become ten times more obſcure than before: Other good Men, build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill upon the firſt falſe Foundation (I mean Comment) and endeavouring to maintain a ground which was not firm at Bottom, The Council of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62979:59"/>
               <hi>Trent</hi> moſt judiciouſly, and (if I may ſay) divinely Decreed (what ſome call the <hi>Modus</hi>) Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation; and that in ſuch admirable terms, and words, that I am convinc'd the Divine Wiſdom in the thing <hi>determined,</hi> exceeded the Natural Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the perſons <hi>determining:</hi> But no ſooner were the Canons eſtabliſhed, and this Council diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd; but ſome Men (in Oppoſition to theſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies which have diſturb'd the Church ever ſince) fell to work again in explaining theſe holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; but nothing having been <hi>explicitely</hi> decreed in this Council, more than what had been always <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely</hi> believ'd before; they generally kept to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Notions, and inſtead of reconciling this Divine Truth to Senſe, to Reaſon, and to the Word of God, have made it almoſt incompatible with all three; whilſt nevertheleſs the Doctrine it ſelf remains in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably true, and againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail. Thus we ſee how Vice and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance may have accidentally introduc'd an erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Explication, but could not poſſibly have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Doctrine it ſelf (much leſs the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) had it been guilty of ſo much Novelty as it is accus'd of, by our Diſcourſer.</p>
            <p>Having thus finiſht (with all plainneſs and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) my Remarks upon ſuch particular Objections as he hath offer'd againſt this Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation; I muſt now reaſſume the Conſideration of our late Anſwerer, and ſome others, who have emptied their whole Quivers of ſharpeſt (tho fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) Arguments againſt an Article of Faith, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely placed by the Promiſes and Providence of the Almighty, far above the reach of humane Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or Power.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:62979:59"/>
            <p>Firſt, our Anſwerer hath a particular Notion, and (very ingeniouſly) hath made a Parallel between many Circumſtances in the Inſtitution of the Jewiſh Paſſover, (or rather the Memorial of it) and that of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: And indeed, could he have reconciled the plain <hi>literal</hi> Inſtitution of the Paſſover, with his <hi>figurative</hi> expreſſion in the Sacrament, he had gon ſomewhat farther towards the Point he aim'd at; But if we take them both in a literal ſenſe (and ſo in reaſon the Parallel ought to run) Alas! his conſequence is confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all his Parallels come to little or nothing. But granting him the benefit of his Clerkſhip, and Reading, in its utmoſt Latitude, will this ſave him? truly I think not, for theſe Reaſons. Firſt, it hath been the received Opinion of all Parties, that the Jewiſh Paſſover, was a Type of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sacrament, and my ſelf was preſent when a Learned
<note n="*" place="margin">Biſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> Biſhop made a whole Sermon before the late King at <hi>White Hall</hi> upon this Suppoſition: If ſo, how comes it then to paſs, that this Type or Figure ſhould be no more than a Figure of a Figure? It was what the <hi>Fathers</hi> could not endure to hear. But, Secondly, according to our Authors Parallel, the Sacrament is no more (at moſt) than a Figure (of the Memorial, that is) of the Figure, of this Figure (that is) the Paſſover. But in truth it appears not clear to me, that the eating of unleavened Bread, had any particular relation to the Paſſover it ſelf; but that they were the Memorials of two <hi>diſtinct,</hi> and <hi>different</hi> actions: The <hi>one,</hi> That God did <hi>Paſs over,</hi> or ſpare the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he ſlew the Children of the <hi>Egyptians:</hi> The <hi>other,</hi> That <hi>God brought them forth out of the Land of Egypt,</hi> which
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62979:60"/>is thus fully expreſt in Exod. 13. v. 8. and 9. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſhew thy Son in that day, ſaying, This is done becauſe of that which the Lord did unto me when I came forth out of Egypt: And it ſhall be for a ſign unto thee upon thine hand, and for a memorial between thine eyes, that the Lords Law may be in thy mouth; for with a ſtrong hand hath the Lord brought thee out of Egypt.</hi> This our Author confeſſeth himſelf in his <hi>Introduction, p.</hi> 4. and it is again ſet forth in <hi>Exod. c.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, (and with ſubmiſſion I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it is) what then becomes of our Anſwerers Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels? Since now they have no relation to the Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or Paſchal Lamb? Why, ſince they lie thus fair for us, we will preſume to make uſe of them, to prove ſtill further the undoubted Truth of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Doctrine.</p>
            <p>The Body of Chriſt then in the Sacrament, is the <hi>Subſtance</hi> ſignified by the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> which was a <hi>Figure</hi> of it; by means of which holy Sacrifice, God is pleaſed to ſpare us, and <hi>paſs over us,</hi> as he did the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and take us into his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Protection.</p>
            <p>The Elements, Symbols, or Accidents, may be the Subſtances ſignified by the unleavened Bread, and (among other ſignifications) are the Memorials of our deliverance from the bondage of Sin and Satan. Thus the Parallels run right upon all four, and when our Anſwerer ſhall have better conſider'd of it, poſſibly he may not think ſo well of what he calls, <hi>almoſt a Demonſtration,</hi> Introd. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The next Remark from our Anſwerers Diſcourſe, is this, That he hath brought ſeveral Learned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics (profeſſedly remaining ſuch) not only, <hi>not</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:62979:60"/>to have believed, but alſo to have written againſt Tranſubſtantiation. If this be really true (as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he imagines it is) then ſurely (if their <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> were no greater than their <hi>Honeſty</hi>) their <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> will not do him much honor; for, to profeſs a Doctrine of that Importance, and yet not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, muſt unavoidably convince the World, that they were falſe, intereſted, hypocritical Knaves; and in this Character will I include the late Author of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but with this additional aggravation of partiality; that he admits of the Engliſh <hi>Real Preſence, Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Impanation, Zuingli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or any thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Tranſubſtantiation: And had he been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ſincere, he ſhould have produc'd the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of the ſame <hi>Fathers</hi> plainly aſſerting what he would make them deny; and have reconcll'd them to <hi>his</hi> Interpretation, if he could.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, we have nothing but his word for the truth of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relics, now if we ſhould ridicule thoſe as moſt probably he hath done ſome <hi>Popiſh</hi> Relics, which he might have met withal in his Travels, I know not how he will help himſelf; we ſhall have reaſon to queſtion his own Sincerity, as immediately ſhall be ſhewn.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a great queſtion, whether all theſe Eminent perſons whom he hath named, did really deny the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation it ſelf, or rather, ſome particular manner among the School. Men of explaining it; which is a conſiderable difference, and may render them totally excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, it is Evident, That ſome of theſe perſons did certainly believe the Doctrine it ſelf,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62979:61"/>and moreover, have explain'd it moſt conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Canons of the Council of <hi>Trent:</hi> And Firſt, Monſieur <hi>de Marca,</hi> the Learned Arch-biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> (taking our Anſwerers own Account in his Preface, <hi>p.</hi> 13.) hath given an admirable Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, and however Mr. <hi>de Baluze,</hi> or the <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctors might miſunderſtand him, my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion as there ſet down is much the ſame with Monſieur <hi>de Marca's;</hi> and in the Concluſion, I ſhall endeavour to make it conſiſtent with Scripture, the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and General Councils, and moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Senſe and Reaſon. The ſame I believe of Cardinal <hi>Perron,</hi> rather than make him ſuch a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain as <hi>Drelincourt</hi> (a profeſt Enemy) hath repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him to the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe.</hi> Our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer, for want of a right underſtanding, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes Monſieur <hi>de Meaux,</hi> and others, whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations he hath ignorantly (not to ſay malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly) endeavour'd to blaſt, which if it were much to my preſent purpoſe, I would further make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p>The laſt particular which I ſhall obſerve (for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who ſhall think it worth their pains may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large if they pleaſe) is his great <hi>diſingenuity,</hi> and <hi>partiality</hi> in his Anſwer to the Learned <hi>Oxford</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer, concerning the Adoration of our Bleſſed Saviour in the Holy Sacrament. The Diſcourſer propoſeth (and one would think with very good Reaſon) That Catholics (here our Anſwerer tells us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 99.</note> 
               <hi>he means Papiſts ſtill,</hi> and this he childiſhly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats ſo often, that it is ten times more inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, than the <hi>Crambe bis cocta,</hi> or Cabbage twice boil'd which (the Poet ſays) was ſo nautious to the Maſters). The Diſcourſer, I ſay, propoſeth, <hi>That Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62979:61"/>grounding their adoration not upon Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, but on a Real Preſence with the Symbols, which in general is agreed on by the</hi> Lutherans, <hi>together with them, ought to be freed from Idolatry therein, as well as the</hi> Lutherans. What ſays the Anſwerer? <hi>That if by this aſſertion, he means only to make this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, That Chriſts Real Preſence, together with the Subſtance of the Bread and Wine, is, in his Opinion as good a ground for Adoration, as if he mere there only with the Species of the Bread, the Subſtance being changed into his Body: I have no more to ſay it.</hi> Here then he grants it, for the one is as good as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>But if (he goes on) he would hereby make us believe, That 'tis all one whether Chriſt be adored, as ſuppoſed here by the</hi> Lutherans <hi>in this holy Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, and as imagined there by the Papiſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 100.</note> 
               <hi>I muſt then deny his Aſſertion:</hi> What ill luck is this — but why? Truly becauſe the one offers more violence to the Senſes, than the other. I could wiſh our Anſwerer would offer leſs violence to his own, and his Readers Senſes; for what have Senſes to do with an equal ſuppoſition of Chriſts Inviſible Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, tho after a different manner? For Inſtance, Suppoſe one man ſhould adore Chriſt under a Veil, believing, that, that which Supported the Veil, was the real Natural Body of Chriſt; the other, equally ador'd Chriſt under the ſome Veil, but upon the Suppoſition, that Chriſts Natural Body was under it, or with it, but together with ſome other Subſtance which totally Supported this Veil, would not any Man judge that the firſt is (at leaſt) as excuſable as the latter?</p>
            <p>But Secondly, He tells us, <hi>That the</hi> Lutheran do <hi>undoubtedly right in the object, and in that he is not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:62979:62"/>miſtaken;</hi> But the Papiſt (altho' he terminates his Adoration upon the ſame Object, Chriſt, as ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed really Preſent, and no otherwiſe would adore, yet) he is miſtaken; ſo the one, only adores Chriſt as in a <hi>place</hi> where he is not, the other as in a <hi>thing</hi> in which he is not; and this makes the vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. A difference there is, I confeſs, for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores <hi>nothing</hi> for Chriſt; the other, Chriſt believed in, or under <hi>ſomething;</hi> but both upon the ſame Suppoſition, of Chriſts Inviſible Preſence, and this is the State of the Caſe in Short. The queſtion is, <hi>Whether they be both equally excuſable or guilty of Idolatry?</hi> Here the Anſwerer paſſeth Sentence clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the Papiſt; but had he writ leſs, and cloſer, he would not ſurely have ſo eaſily forgot what himſelf (from Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>) was pleas'd to urge in <hi>p.</hi> 68. Where he lays it down for a Rule (and gives reaſons for it) That to worſhip Chriſt where he is not, is to worſhip <hi>nothing,</hi> a <hi>Non Ens, which muſt needs be Idolatry. Well, but ſtill it may be the Biſhop, (ſays the Anſwerer) does not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to exclude the</hi> Corpus Domini, <hi>but only the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, or Natural manner of that Body: Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hear how he goes on;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 69.</note> 
               <hi>for</hi> Idolum nihil eſt in Mundo, <hi>ſaith St.</hi> Paul, <hi>and Chriſt as Preſent by his Humane Nature in the Sacrament (or with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament) is a</hi> Non Ens: <hi>For it is not true; there is</hi> no ſuch thing. <hi>What (ſays the Anſwerer) not as Chriſt there,</hi> no way <hi>as to his Humane Nature? No, he is</hi> (ſaith the Biſhop) <hi>preſent there, by his Divine Power, and his Divine Bleſſing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But for any other Preſence, it is</hi> Idolum; <hi>It is</hi> nothing in the World. It ſeems then, to worſhip <hi>nothing</hi> for Chriſt, in the Biſhops Judgment (produc'd
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62979:62"/>by the Anſwerer) is Idolatry; The Queſtion is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning Idolatry, therefore ſure both are equally culpable, or equally innocent of that Crime. What a deal of Stuff then hath our Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer heapt up, to no other purpoſe, than to ſnew himſelf a partial Scribler? Let him not be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then, if I moſt juſtly apply to himſelf, what he produces in reference to another;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 96.</note> 
               <hi>That for a Book which carried a great appearance of Reaſoning, it hath the leaſt in it of any I ever met with.</hi> But I leave the Learned <hi>Oxford</hi> Diſcourſer, to manage his own Defence againſt this Anſwerer, if he ſhall think it worthy of a thought.</p>
            <p>The laſt publick Enemy to Tranſubſtantiation that I ſhall mention, is, <hi>The Defender of the</hi> Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin <hi>Letter.</hi> I muſt confeſs he ſeems to be a Man of Learning and Judgment, tho equally unknown to me as the reſt; but becauſe his Defence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends chiefly upon the Authorities of <hi>Fathers,</hi> whoſe Senſe (I humbly conceive) he miſtakes, or miſapplies; I ſhall endeavour to reconcile them, in the Concluſion, to other expreſſions of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and all, to the Catholic Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</p>
            <p>Thus, Reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> I have made ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Remarks upon theſe Authors <hi>againſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation</hi> as I thought neceſſary toward the clearing our way to the right underſtanding of that great Myſtery; and if I have ſaid ought which might hitherto offend <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>them,</hi> I know not how to ask your Pardons; for as (being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their Perſons) I can have no malice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; ſo when I find Men writing magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62979:63"/>and pragmatically againſt Learned Men, and Chriſtian Doctrines, when (as I believe) they are themſelves in the wrong, I thought it a part of my Duty, to preſent the <hi>Glaſs,</hi> to them that by ſeeing how ill their Reflections appear, they might call to mind that admirable Rule of Juſtice and Equity, <hi>Quod tibi non vis fieri, alteri ne feceris.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>HAving endeavour'd to remove ſome prejudices againſt the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, which every Author had kept, as particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, over and above thoſe Vulgar Objections, which are common to them all; I ſhould now to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally apply my ſelf to the reconciling part, and I have made ſome conſiderable Progreſs in it; but finding that I have already exceeded the limits which I at firſt propoſed to my ſelf, and that the weightineſs of this Subject, together with the variety of Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions againſt it, and of Opinions concerning it, will engage me in a larger Diſcourſe than is proper for this time and place, I reſolv'd to make a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of it by it ſelf, and this I am the rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to do, becauſe we may probably ſee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this kind in public, done by a better hand, which likely, may ſave both you and me a further labor. I ſhall content my ſelf therefore at preſent to ſay ſomething in General, and for Particulars, muſt refer you to what I further deſign, if need require, and God ſhall enable us.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:62979:63"/>
               <p>The main Objections againſt Tranſubſtantiation are chiefly theſe two.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That <hi>the natural Body of Chriſt cannot be in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places at the ſame time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. That it is againſt the <hi>Evidences of our Senſes to believe, that what we ſee, and feel, and taſt, and ſmell, and which nouriſheth, ſhould not be what it ſeems to be:</hi> Or, that <hi>Accidents ſhould exiſt without a Subject af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of a Subſtance, and yet be nothing.</hi> Theſe and many others which are the conſequences of theſe (bating ſeveral groſs miſtakes) are obvious in moſt Proteſtant Authors.</p>
               <p>To the Firſt, The Reaſons given why the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Body of Chriſt cannot be in ſeveral places at the ſame time, are, <hi>Becauſe a Body cannot exiſt after the manner of a Spirit, That a Body cannot be inviſible and impoſſible,</hi> Anſw. p. 34. Or, as it is in the Rubric, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is againſt the truth of Chriſts Natural Body to be at one time in more places than one.</hi> Now if we can Evidently ſhew out of Scripture, that the Body of Chriſt here upon Earth, did ſometimes exiſt after the manner of a Spirit, and was Inviſible, I hope the two firſt Reaſons will be taken off by conſent. And firſt it is underſtood (I think) by all,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.</note> that the Body of Chriſt when he was transfigur'd, did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt after a Supernatural manner, and was freed (for the time being) from the clog, and earthly limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of common humane Bodies.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is plain that after his Reſurrection <hi>Jeſus</hi> made his Body become Inviſible. The Text tells us, <hi>That he appear'd in ſeveral Forms. After that he appear'd in another Form unto two of them,</hi> Mark 16. v. 12. Which I ſuppoſe is ſomewhat above Nature: Alſo the third time when <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62979:64"/>to his Diſciples at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> he had changed again his Form, <hi>for they knew him not,</hi> John c. 21. Nor was he known the firſt time by <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> but was miſtaken by her for the Gardiner. But in <hi>Luke</hi> 24. It is clearly expreſt, That Jeſus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to his Diſciples after the manner of a Spirit, for it is ſaid in v. 36. <hi>And as they thus ſpake, Jeſus himſelf ſtood in the midſt of them, and ſaid unto them, peace be unto you, But they were terrified and affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuppoſed that they ſeen a ſpirit.</hi> Now altho' the Circumſtances in this Text ſufficiently denote, that our Saviour came not to his Diſciples <hi>progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively</hi> after the manner of humane Bodies, but that <hi>eodem inſtante</hi> he appear'd in the midſt of them, which was the cauſe of their fear (for they were told before that our Lord was riſen): Yet the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding <hi>v.</hi> 31. of the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> leads ſo manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this Interpretation, that there is no colour left to doubt; for it is there written, That after our Lord had been ignorantly entertain'd by the two Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, at <hi>Emmaus,</hi> at laſt, <hi>Their eyes were opened, and they knew him, and he</hi> vaniſhed <hi>out of their ſight.</hi> This agrees alſo with the account which we have from St. <hi>John, c.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 19. Where it is ſaid, <hi>The ſame day at Evening when the</hi> Dores were ſhut, <hi>came Jeſus and ſtood in the midſt of them.</hi> The ſame Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance is alſo repeated in <hi>v.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>In vain do ye therefore ſo often Object to us, Worthy <hi>Fathers,</hi> the neceſſity of believing our Senſes, in all things, and upon all Occaſions, ſince you ſee how the Apoſtles themſelves were deceived by them, even concerning the real, viſible, corporal Preſence of Chriſt upon Earth. As for St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the Confirmation from the Evidence of his Senſes, our
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62979:64"/>Saviour reproacht his want of Faith, and ſuffer'd him to put his doubting hand into his Sacred Wounds, not ſo much to ſhew him that he was <hi>meer Man,</hi> as to convince <hi>them</hi> that he was <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man: God,</hi> from his infinite Power, in being able to make his Natural Body exiſt after the manner of a Spirit, which they had ſeen before, and were terrified at it: And <hi>Man,</hi> in that nevertheleſs he had the ſhape and Subſtance of that very Body in which he ſuffer'd.</p>
               <p>Nor muſt we think that theſe Supernatural changes were done by chance, or without the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed deſign of the Divine Wiſdome; for the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who hitherto had doubted concerning the great Article of the Reſurrection of the Fleſh, were not only hereby convinced of this neceſſary truth, but were alſo taught after what manner their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhould be raiſed from the dead; Or, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſays, 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 15. What Bodies they do become: <hi>S. Paul</hi> gives them their Anſwer, <hi>v.</hi> 36. <hi>Thou fool, that which thou ſoweſt is not quickened except it die.</hi> Then telling us of the ſeveral differences between Bodies, ſome more, and ſome leſs glorified, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds <hi>v.</hi> 42. <hi>So alſo is the Reſurrection of the Dead: It is ſown in Corruption, it is raiſed in Incorruption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is ſown in Diſhonor, it is raiſed in Glory; It is ſown in Weakneſs, it is raiſed in Power; It is ſown a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Body, it is raiſed a</hi> Spiritual <hi>Body.</hi> And this our Saviour had before experimentally taught them, by the differing, and Spiritual manner of the Exiſtence of his own Body; confirming alſo has Divinity, by that Power which he exerciſed upon it, according to that of <hi>S. Matthew, c.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>All Power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> If then our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62979:65"/>Sinful Bodies ſhall have this <hi>Glory, Power</hi> and <hi>Spirituality,</hi> when they are raiſed from the Dead, and probably be ſubject <hi>then</hi> to the Soul, as the Soul is <hi>now</hi> to the Body, who will dare to preſcribe Laws to the holy and ſpotleſs Body of our Lord, united to his Divinity?</p>
               <p>However it be, the vindication of the Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſeems to concern your ſelves, worthy <hi>Fathers,</hi> or at leaſt many other Proteſtants, no leſs than Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics; and if that be admitted, methinks Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation ſhould not be ſo rudely refuſed Entrance: For give me leave to ask you, from what Authority you pretend to tell us, That Chriſt is <hi>really Preſent</hi> in the Sacrament, except you mean, as in all other pious Duties? If you deny this <hi>real Preſence,</hi> you ſtand ſeparate from the whole Chriſtian World, <hi>Lutherans,</hi> as well as Catholics; which is no very good Argument that you are in the right. If you confeſs it, ſolve theſe difficulties your ſelves, for it concerns you, no leſs than us. But if again, you do not confeſs it, then tell me (I ſay) what ground you have from Scripture to name thoſe words, except as a conſequence from theſe, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> and upon the Suppoſition, that (at leaſt) the Subſtance of the Bread is become, after Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very Body of our Lord?</p>
               <p>You tell us again, That we do <hi>verily, truly,</hi> and <hi>indeed</hi> receive the <hi>very Body</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>That,</hi> born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which ſuffer'd for us, and roſe from the Dead: Let me enquire again, what Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity you have to uſe thoſe words, if you do not lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally intend the thing? Spiritual Graces proceed not from his Humanity, but from his Divinity: Faith is one of theſe Spiritual Graces, and the immediate
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:62979:65"/>Gift of God, and ſignifies only this (at leaſt in this place) That Chriſt was the Son of God; that he became Man; that he died for us, and roſe again from the dead. What hath this to do with eating his Body, and drinking his Blood?</p>
               <p>A Commemoration only of his Death it cannot mean, nor could the Apoſtles ſo underſtand it, except you can ſhew me ſome ſuch like Metaphor uſed to expreſs the memorial of a Man after his death: But if neither before our Saviours Paſſion, nor ſince, amongſt Jews, Heathens, or Chriſtians ſuch an Expreſſion was ever uſed, why muſt we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that, Chriſt ſpake, or the Apoſtles underſtood different from all the expreſſions of mankind ſince the Creation of <hi>Adam?</hi> When the Maſter of the Houſe, in Celebrating the Paſchal Supper, ſaid, <hi>This is the Bread of affliction which our Fathers eat in Egypt;</hi> true Bread was really deliver'd, and the Memorial was proper. When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Behold the Blood of the Covenant, which the Lord hath made with you,</hi> It was very Blood which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſprinkled on the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 8. But to tell us we eat and drink the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as a Memorial of him, when you profeſs we do no ſuch thing, is the moſt extravagant of all Metaphors, and unparallell'd in Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>That ſome have eaten their deceaſed Friends, and that others have drank their Aſhes, I have already hinted; but to ſay, eat and drink the Body and Blood of King <hi>Charls,</hi> that is, remember that he was Martyr'd, would be ſuch an expreſſion as ſtands ſingle (at leaſt as far as I have read) from all the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legories of the moſt phantaſtical Poets. Why then do you tells us, That we indeed eat and drink his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:62979:66"/>Body and Blood, and not <hi>rather,</hi> and <hi>only</hi> ſay that we break Bread in remembrance that Chriſt was ſo broken, and pour forth Wine, as a Memorial that his Blood was ſo ſhed for us? Give me leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Anſwer; I fear, that whilſt you want Faith to believe the truth intended by the words, you are aſhamed to neglect the words themſelves, leſt you ſhould become a ſcandal and reproach to all ſober Chriſtians, who had ever read the Holy Bible or the beſt of <hi>Fathers.</hi> Deceive not therefore your ſelves and thoſe poor Souls who depend upon you, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give them <hi>in truth</hi> the laſt Sacred <hi>Legacy</hi> of our moſt dear and ever Bleſſed Maſter, or tell them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is departed and hath left them nothing; for a <hi>Body,</hi> which is <hi>no Body,</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> which is <hi>no thing,</hi> is (at leaſt) as <hi>abſur'd</hi> and <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> a Propoſition, as your ſo often objected <hi>Smelling, Taſting, nouriſhing Accidents</hi> without a <hi>Subſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> hath given us a long Beadroll of Objections in <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>Et ſequent.</hi> Which he ſays contradicts <hi>right Reaſon:</hi> I could have furniſht him with a great many more, and much more pertinent, from an Ancient Catholic Author, call'd, The <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Manna,</hi> where he would alſo have found their Anſwers, to which I muſt recommend him. In ſome of his <hi>repugnancies</hi> (as he calls them) he ſhews himſelf ſo ignorant, or malicious, that he is, either way inexcuſable: So <hi>p.</hi> 35. In <hi>p.</hi> 33. he ſeems neither to underſtand Catholic Divinity, nor common Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, but talks ſo crudely of both, that he deſerves not a ſober Reply. What he (from <hi>Blondel)</hi> tells us of the <hi>Fathers, p.</hi> 34. I do not rightly underſtand, nor did I think it worth my pains to procure <hi>Blondel</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account; but if either of them would make
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62979:66"/>us believe, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> thought it <hi>abſurd,</hi> and <hi>impoſſible,</hi> that God ſhould act beyond and above the Power of Nature, the <hi>Fathers</hi> are much obliged to them for their good Opinion; but if he would make them ſay, that naturally a thing cannot exiſt, act, or be produc'd contrary to, or above Nature, he hath made a wiſe Speech for them, which he may keep for his own uſe.</p>
               <p>In his 36 <hi>P.</hi> he is come to his Senſes; but becauſe he hath only a ſlight touch of them, and thoſe the ſame with our firſt Diſcourſer, I ſhall conſider them (as far as I intend at preſent) together.</p>
               <p>The firſt Objection is, that what we taſt, and ſmell, and ſee, and touch, and which nouriſh our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſhould be <hi>Nothing;</hi> and as it is reduced to an Objection againſt Senſe, it runs thus,
<q>That what we ſee in the Sacrament is not Bread, but the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt.</q> I have told you that I muſt defer my more particular Anſwer, to a particular Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe upon that Subject, in which I hope to reconcile all difficulties, not only to Senſe and Reaſon, but to the words of Conſecration, to the Canons of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and to the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to themſelves, quite throughout: In the mean time I will give you the general Faith of all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics, and ſo conclude.</p>
               <p>The indiſpenſable Faith of all Catholics is this. That the Subſtance of the Bread and Wine, after Conſecration, is converted into the Subſtance of the Body and Blood of Chriſt united with his Soul and his Divinity: No good Catholics diſpute this altho' ſeveral Opinions alſo there are concerning the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> how <hi>this</hi> is done. The great Queſtion is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Accidents which remain, and it is the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62979:67"/>more receiv'd Opinion, that they are real (tho' not properly call'd ſubſtantial) <hi>things;</hi> and that, as ſuch, they may nouriſh the Body, ſuffer digeſtion and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and are the true Objects of our Senſes, in which (we ſay) all the vertues and qualities of Bread exiſt: This we are told is conſiſtent with <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Philoſophy; but if you think otherwiſe, diſpute your Opinion as long as you pleaſe, and (if you can) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige your Adverſaries to find out ſome more ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory Anſwer, for there are ſome others, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter. The Faith in the mean time remains inviolably among all, which, their different Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons pretend not to deſtroy: All believe the Subſtance is converted; but for the Accidents, whether they be more, or leſs; whether they exiſt with, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Subject; what that Subject is; or whether they may not have Subſtances of themſelves, theſe are Matters of Opinion and Philoſophy, and we muſt remember, that Chriſt came not to teach us Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and Logic, but Faith and Obedience unto Good Works.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall enter no further upon this Diſcourſe at preſent; nor ſhall I here anſwer our Diſcourſers four laſt Queſtions, which, depending upon the Doctrine of Accidents, ſhall be conſider'd together with them, in our deſigned Treatiſe: I ſhall only therefore add my hearty Prayers, that you would once lay aſide your prejudices, and affections, and many other temporal conſiderations, and ſincerely and calmly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour with us, to find where the truth lies. I know no Body intends any harm to you, or other good to themſelves, than that we might be all United under one Head, Chriſt Jeſus, holding the Unity of Faith, in the Bond of Peace.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:62979:67"/>
               <p>It would be a defect of Charity not to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd, ſhould you believe all Catholics to be Knaves, or Fools; or that they did not ſee, and know, or would not know what can be ſaid againſt them, as well as Proteſtants; ſince your greateſt Objections which I have ever read againſt us, are found in our own Authors, and their Anſwers to them, of which you are pleaſed to be ſilent. It were beſides, a ſtrange Inſtance of Spiritual Pride, to think yourſelves the only Children of Light, and this, grounded upon no other Authority, than your own private Opinions, and a partial Judgment paſt upon your ſelves, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the much greater part of the whole Chriſtian World.</p>
               <p>The Glorious Epinikeas, and lofty Triumphs which you ſing in all your Papers, might become the Buskins of a Pagan Conqueror; but in me, they move only my Compaſſion to ſee you ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pleas'd, and inſulting in the wrong. Alas, you miſtake the Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for in our Caſe, the Conquered wins the Priz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and yet the Victor loſeth not his honor. What would it profit him (ſays our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) <hi>If a man ſhould gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul?</hi> It is a ſerious conſideration, and deſerves a ſober thought or two, free from paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or prejudice. Now whether it be adviſeable to venture ſo great a Treaſure upon the ſingle Bottom of every mans private Opinion? Whether our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt would leave his own Church in a much more dangerous condition, than <hi>that</hi> in which he found the Jewiſh Church? Whether Certainty was to be had among the Jews from the Chair of <hi>Moſes,</hi> concerning what they were to believe, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:62979:68"/>do; but no Certainty to Chriſtians from the Chair of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> or any other Chriſtian Church upon the face of the Earth? Whether Hereſie and Schiſm be terms to affright us, and only different names for Knavery, and Hypocriſie? Or, whether a man who truly believes himſelf to be in the right, may not be deſperately, and dangerouſly in the wrong; and highly puniſhable for his preſumption, and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to lawful Authority? And Laſtly, whether you will tell us roundly and plainly. That <hi>to believe Chriſt to be the Son of the Living God,</hi> and to live a moral Life, be all that is required of us, as ſome of you have very boldly inſinuated? Theſe things I recommend to your pious and ingenuous Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, until we meet again.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
